<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 THE MANTRA on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 THE MANTRA on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 Meaning</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/1_Meaning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/1_Meaning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How should we understand the text of the Gāyatrī-Mantra, and how can we translate it? The list of more than seventy translations given in Appendix 1 illustrates that many writers have felt the need to create their own rendition of the mantra. No single standard translation of the GM has ever become widely accepted. In my view, the primary reason for the existence of so many translations and paraphrases is not that the GM itself allows for such a great variety of different readings, but rather, when it comes to the GM, many authors seem to have felt that a famous mantra such as this one must have, or allow for, several interpretations and translations, and that their own rendition may therefore easily be included among them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 Designations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/2_Designations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/2_Designations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As outlined in the Introduction, the verse ṚV III 62.10 is known under two names: sāvitrī (Sāvitrī, Savitri, Savitree, etc.) and Gāyatrī (other spellings include gāyatrī, Gayatri, Gaayatree, or even Gayutree). As will be seen, sāvitrī  is the older of the two names. The history of this name is closely connected to the early history and rise of the mantra itself, which will be discussed in detail in the remainder of Part I.²³⁵ In the following, I will only briefly summarize some of the basic facts about the designation sāvitrī. For reasons that will soon become clear, the history of the designation “Gāyatrī” is a much more contested topic, and reconstructing it will indeed be the main task of this chapter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 Adaptive Reuse in Śrauta Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/3_Adaptive_Reuse_in_shrauta_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/3_Adaptive_Reuse_in_shrauta_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Gāyatrī-Mantra had already been adaptively reused³⁴⁷ in Śrauta rituals since at least 1100 bce, when the Yajurvedic mantra texts were composed.³⁴⁸ The aim of this chapter is to show how the GM was employed in those rituals and how that employment developed over time and across the various Vedic schools.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Domestic ritual, which certainly must have existed in one form or another when the elaborate Śrauta ceremonies were devised,³⁴⁹ is discussed in Chapters 4 and 5.) To this end, I have surveyed a great number of Vedic texts, using the mantra corpus provided by the UVC  as a basis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Selection as Initiation Mantra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/4_Selection_as_Initiation_Mantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/4_Selection_as_Initiation_Mantra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The upanáyana (the “leading to”), or upā́yana (the “going to”) as it is sometimes also called,⁴⁵⁷ takes place when a boy is led to his teacher to be initiated into the study of the Vedic texts. By undergoing this ritual, the boy enters the state called brahmacárya  and becomes a brahmacārín, that is, “someone who is engaged with [learning] the bráhman s (potent Vedic formulations).”⁴⁵⁸ Probably since the late-Vedic period – that is, sometime between 800 and 500 bce – the initiation has also included the ritual teaching of a sāvitrī  verse that authorizes the student to learn the Vedic texts.⁴⁵⁹&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Status in Early Hinduism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/5_Status_in_Early_Hinduism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/1_THE_MANTRA/5_Status_in_Early_Hinduism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 4 I argued that a sāvitrī  was sought to inaugurate Vedic studentship due to the fact that Savitṛ was often invoked at the beginning of rituals and litanies in Śrauta ritual. While occasionally sāvitrī s in other meters were prescribed as well, the gāyatrī  was always considered primary. The Gāyatrī-Mantra was selected from a variety of sāvitrī s because it was already frequently reused in Śrauta ritual. It is likely that the GM was the first gāyatrī sāvitrī  to be chosen in this way, even though the earliest sources are surprisingly unspecific in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
