<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;06 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;06 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST CHAPTER. (On the Offices of the Grāvastut and Subrahmanya.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(On the Origin of the Office of the Grāvastut. The Serpent&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Riṣi Arbuda.) The gods held (once upon a time) a sacrificial session in Sarvacbaru. They did not succeed in [880] destroying the consequences of guilt. Arbuda, the son of Kadru, the Serpent Riṣi, the framer of mantras, said to them, “You have overlooked one ceremony which is to be performed by the Hotar. I will perform it for you, then you will destroy the consequences of guilt.&amp;quot; They said, “Well, let it be done.&amp;quot; At every midday libation, he then came forth (from his hole), approached them, and repeated spells over the Soma, squeezing stones. Thence they repeat spells at every midday libation over the Soma squeezing stones, in imitation of him (the Serpent Riṣi). The way on which this Serpent Riṣi used to go when coming from his holo) is now known by the name Arbudoda Sarpant (at the sacrificial compound).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND CHAPTER. On the Sustras of the Minor Hotri-priests at the Sattras.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(On the Sastras of Minor Hotri-priests at the Morning and&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Evening Libations.) The Devas spread the sacrifice. When doing so, the Asuras approach ed them, thinking, let us obstruct their sacrifice. They attacked them from the right side, thinking this to be the weak point. The Devas awoke, and posted two of their number, Mitra and Varuṇa, on the right side. Through the assistance of these two, the Devas drove the Asuras and Rakṣasas away from the morning libation. And thus the sacrificers drive them away (if they have the Maitrāvaruṇa Sastra repeated); thence the Maitrāvaruṇa priest repeats the Maitrāvaruṇa Sastra (887) at the morning libation. The Asuras, defeated on the right side, attacked the centre of the sacrifice. The Devas awoke, posted then Indra, and defeated through his assistance the enemies. Therefore the Brāhmanāchchhamsi repeats at the morning libation the Indra Shastra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD CHAPTER.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The hymns for lifting the Chamasa (Soma cups).. The Praṣthita Yājyds&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;of the seven Llotars concluding this ceremony. The two different kinds of Hotars. Explanation of some apparent anomalies in the perforo mances of the minor Hotris. The Jagati hymns for Indra. The concluding verses of the minor Hotri-priests. On a peculiarity in the Sastras of the Achchháváha.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The number of verses which the Hotar has to repeat at the time of the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH CHAPTER.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The Sarpāta hymns. The Vālakhilyas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Dürohanam.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(See 6, 5.) When they make at Soma sacrifices, which require several days for their performance (ahinas) in order to make them continuous, at the morning libation, the singing verse (Stotriya) of the following day, the Anurūpa of the preceding day, it is just the same as with the performance of a Soma sacrifiice which lasts for one day only (ekdha.) For just as the (three) libations of the one day&amp;rsquo;s Soma sacrifice are connected with each other, in the same way are the days of a Soma sacrifice which lasts for several days connected with one another. The reason that they make at the morning libation, the singing verse (Stotriya) of the following day, the Anurapa of the preceding day, is to make the days during which the sacrifice lasts one continuous series. Thus they make the days of the Abina sacrifices one continuous whole.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/06/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIFTH CHAPTER. (The so-called Silpas, viz. the Nābhānediṣtha, Nardsansa, Dalakhil ya, Sukirti, Vriṣākapi, and Evayāmarut hymns. The Kuntapa Sastra.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Nábhānediṣtha and Narasamsa hymns repeated by the Hotar)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They repeat the Silpas (hymns for producing [424] wonderful pieces of art). There are such wonder-works of the gods, and the arts in this world are to be understood as an imitation thereof. The gilded cloth spread over an elephant, the carriage to which a mule is yoked, are such a wonder-work. This work is understood in this world by him, who has such a knowledge. The Silpas make ready the soul, and imbue it with the knowledge of the sacred hymns. By means of them the Hotri-priest prepares the soul for the sacrificer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
