<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 History of the R̥gvedic Text on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 History of the R̥gvedic Text on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Language and Compositional Technique</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/A_Language_and_Compositional_Technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/A_Language_and_Compositional_Technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The R̥gveda was composed in an archaic form of Sanskrit that is richer in forms  and less grammatically fixed than Classical Sanskrit, but essentially identical in  structure. For further discussion of the language, see section VII below. The text was composed entirely orally and transmitted entirely orally for a very long time,  probably several millennia. But it was a type of oral composition very different  from what that designation now generally brings to mind in scholarly, especially  Homeric, circles. It was not an anonymous floating body of infinitely variable verbal material (re-)composed anew at every performance, generated in great part from  fixed formulae that formed the poet’s repertoire.+++(4)+++ In contrast to the vast sprawl of  epic, on which the usual model of oral-formulaic composition was formed and  tested, R̥gvedic oral composition was small-scale and verbally complex. Though  orally composed and making use of traditional verbal material, each hymn was  composed by a particular poet, who fixed the hymn at the time of composition and  who “owned” it, and it was transmitted in this fixed form thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B Preservation and Transmission</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/B_Preservation_and_Transmission/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/B_Preservation_and_Transmission/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The structure of the R̥gveda points to several stages in the creation of the R̥gvedic  text as we now have it. Collections of hymns were first made by the families of poets  who produced them, and these early collections defined the various poetic tradi tions and helped train new poets within those traditions. At some point a unified  consolidation was made of six family traditions, which formed the original collec tion of the Family Books, II–VII. As discussed above, the books were arranged  from shortest to longest and the hymns of each book were organized according to  the same principles. Then, probably at several intervals, the hymns of books I and  VIII (except for the Vālakhilya hymns) were added+++(4)+++, and book IX was assembled  from hymns composed by poets of the other books of the R̥gveda and from hymns  of younger poets. The last major additions to the collection were the hymns of  book X.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C Indigenous Commentarial Tradition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/C_Indigenous_Commentarial_Tradition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/C_Indigenous_Commentarial_Tradition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With regard to indigenous commentary, the situation of the R̥gveda differs markedly from that of standard Classical Sanskrit texts, in that there is no unbroken  commentarial tradition that might preserve the understanding of the text by the  authors and audience at the time of composition. Although we find implicit commentary on some parts of the R̥gveda already in later Vedic texts, it is clear that in  many case this “commentary” is based more on adaptation, speculation, or fancy  than on a direct transmission of the purport of the text, as when the Śatapatha  Brāhmaṇa (XI.5.1) sketches a narrative background for the Purūravas and Urvaśī dialogue (R̥V X.95) that distorts or misunderstands crucial portions of the hymn.+++(5)+++ The first complete de facto commentary on the R̥gveda, dating probably from  the late Vedic period, is Śākalya’s Padapāṭha mentioned above, which simply consists of an effectively linguistic analysis of the continuous text (the Saṃhitāpāṭha)  of the R̥gveda into individual words (padas). Because of sandhi, an important and  pervasive feature of the Sanskrit language whereby all words undergo significant  phonological adjustment to adjacent words in context, the phonological restora tion of the underlying pausal forms of words from the continuous reading is no mere mechanical operation, but presupposes a grammatical and semantic analysis  of the text.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D Western Scholarship on the R̥gveda and Major Resources</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/D_Western_Scholarship_on_the_Rgveda_and_Major_Resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/02_History_of_the_Rgvedic_Text/D_Western_Scholarship_on_the_Rgveda_and_Major_Resources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Because the transmission of the R̥gveda has preserved the text remarkably well, we  have a trustworthy and uniform text of the R̥gveda. The published editions of the  R̥gveda differ in their presentation of the text, not in the text itself. The landmark  edition of the R̥gveda was that of Max Müller (1849–74), who published both the  Saṃhitā and Padapāṭha text in devanāgarī script, together with Sāyaṇa’s commentary. Before the completion of Müller’s R̥gveda, in 1861–63 Theodor Aufrecht published the text in Roman transliteration, together with selected Padapāṭha analyses.  A  second edition, the standard edition of Aufrecht’s R̥gveda, appeared in 1877.  The R̥gveda and Sāyaṇa’s commentary were published again under the editorship  of N. S. Sontakke (1933–51), together with the Padapāṭha. Also noteworthy is the  aforementioned publication of the metrically restored version of the R̥gveda text by  Barend A. van Nooten and Gary B. Holland (1994).+++(4)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
