<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अध्य्-ऋग्वेदम् on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अध्य्-ऋग्वेदम् on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>&#43;शाखाः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/shAkhAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/shAkhAH/</guid>
      <description>शकल-शाखा &amp;ldquo;Nambudiris of Kerala recite even the Brahmana and Aranyaka with accents. Accented manuscripts of Brahmana and Aranyaka are available to this day.&amp;rdquo; शाङ्खायनशाखा वैदिकभारतसंस्थया पुनर् उज्जीव्यमाना। बाष्कल-शाखा &amp;ldquo;Claims have been made about its existence in Kerala, Rajasthan, Bengal and Assam as a living tradition, but have never been verified. The Samhita exists in manuscript. &amp;quot; &amp;ldquo;Nambudiris of Kerala are said to follow this Shakha of RV as far as the Samhita is concerned but studies of their oral tradition do not seem to bear this out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>खिलेषु काशीकरः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/khileShu_kAshIkaraH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/khileShu_kAshIkaraH/</guid>
      <description>Introductory The R̥gveda Saṁhitā has, according to the Sakala śākhā, 1017 hymns. According to the Caraṇavyūha, the R̥gveda Saṁhitā has come down in five recensions: Sākala, Başkala, Āśvalāyana, Sārkhāyana and Mândūkāyana. (Besides these five, many more Sakhas (21, 25 or 27) are said to have existed.) Of these, the Sākala recension is well known and has come down in a definite form. (2. It is to be noted that Kausitaki is different from Sānkhāyana.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>परम्परा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/paramparA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/paramparA/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
व्यासः पैलः इन्द्रप्रमतिः, बाष्कलः मार्कण्डेयः सत्यश्रवाः तत्पुत्रः सत्याहितः सत्यरतः सत्यश्रीः शाकल्यः (याज्ञवल्क्येन वादे मृतः) रथिथरः शाकपूर्णः शतबलकः, केतवः, दालकी, नैगमः बाष्कलिः भारद्वाजः अर्यवः, पन्नगारिः, नन्दायनीयः बाष्कलः शिष्याः - वोध्य अग्निमाठर पराशर, याज्ञवल्क्य</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>सूत्राणि</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/sUtrANi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/meta/sUtrANi/</guid>
      <description> ऋग्वेदः वसिष्ठ-धर्मसूत्रम् कौषीतक-गृह्यसूत्रम् ऋग्वेदः - शकल-शाखा आश्वलायन-गृह्यसूत्रम् आश्वलायन-श्रौतसूत्रम् ऋग्वेदः - शङ्खायन-शाखा शाङ्खायन-श्रौतसूत्रम् </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
