<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 Ritual on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 Ritual on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Model of the Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/A_Model_of_the_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/A_Model_of_the_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>The ritual as depicted both in the R̥gveda and in the later Vedic texts treating the classical śrauta system (and indeed the much later pūjā of classical Hinduism) is modeled as a hospitality ceremony and festive meal, offered to the visiting gods. The poets eagerly invite the gods to journey to attend the sacrifice. When they arrive, they are greeted and provided with seats near the center of the action, on a special grass strewn on the ritual ground to make the ground more comfortable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>B Basic Elements of the Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/B_Basic_Elements_of_the_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/B_Basic_Elements_of_the_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>Changes in classical rites Later Vedic texts give detailed descriptions of the soma rituals, which varied in length and complexity. The problem for the interpretation of the R̥gveda is that these classical rites were clearly not the same as the rites of the R̥gvedic period itself. While the classical rites drew on R̥gvedic traditions, they did not simply continue them. In the R̥gvedic period these rituals were probably much more variable, for even though their rituals were based on a shared inherited tradition, different priestly families performed the rites differently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>C Soma Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/C_Soma_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/C_Soma_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>As we have frequently had occasion to remark, most of the hymns of the R̥gveda were composed for the soma ritual. The central rite of this sacrifice was the prepa ration of the soma juice, which was then offered to the gods and shared among male participants in the rite. In the R̥gvedic period the stalks of the soma plant were probably placed on a stone and crushed using another stone or stones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>D Other Rituals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/D_Other_Rituals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/D_Other_Rituals/</guid>
      <description>Pravargya In describing Vedic ritual we have thus far been discussing the soma sacrifice. But while the soma sacrifice dominates the R̥gveda, the collection includes hymns composed for other rites as well. One of the sub-rites of the classical soma ritual is the Pravargya, which according to most ritual sūtras is performed twice daily on the three days leading up to the soma-pressing day. At an earlier stage, likely represented by the R̥gveda, the Pravargya was an independent rite, which was only later incorporated into the soma tradition.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
