<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 Ritual on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 Ritual on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Model of the Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/A_Model_of_the_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/A_Model_of_the_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ritual as depicted both in the R̥gveda and in the later Vedic texts treating the  classical śrauta system (and indeed the much later pūjā of classical Hinduism) is  modeled as a hospitality ceremony and festive meal, offered to the visiting gods. The  poets eagerly invite the gods to journey to attend the sacrifice. When they arrive, they are greeted and provided with seats near the center of the action, on a special  grass strewn on the ritual ground to make the ground more comfortable. This grass  strew is called barhís and it has an exact cognate in Avestan barziš “cushion, pillow.”+++(4)+++  In some hymns the horses pulling the gods’ chariots, particularly Indra’s two fallow+++(=yellowish-brown)+++  bays+++(=reddish brown horse)+++, are unhitched and offered refreshment of their own. The gods are then offered  a meal, that is, the oblations, generally consisting of ghee, little grain cakes, and,  in the most important sacrifices, soma, and they are entertained while they eat, by  the hymns of praise that constitute the R̥gvedic corpus.+++(4)+++ The end of this entertain ment is often announced in the final verse of the hymn, and sometimes the gods are  explicitly sent on their way back to heaven. Particularly nice examples of this envoi+++(=concluding poem)+++  are found in I.61–63 and I.82, hymns designed to accompany the Hāriyojana or  “Fallow-bay-yoking” oblation, the ritualized hitching up of Indra’s horses for the  return journey; in I.82.5–6 Indra is charmingly urged to go home to his “dear wife.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B Basic Elements of the Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/B_Basic_Elements_of_the_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/B_Basic_Elements_of_the_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-in-classical-rites&#34;&gt;Changes in classical rites&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Later Vedic texts give detailed descriptions of the soma rituals, which varied in  length and complexity. The problem for the interpretation of the R̥gveda is that  these classical rites were clearly not the same as the rites of the R̥gvedic period  itself. While the classical rites drew on R̥gvedic traditions, they did not simply continue them. In the R̥gvedic period these rituals were probably much more variable,  for even though their rituals were based on a shared inherited tradition, different  priestly families performed the rites differently. For example, in the classical one-day  soma rite, soma juice is pressed out of the soma plant and offered to various deities  in the morning, at midday, and in the evening. But the third or evening pressing  stands apart from the other two. While soma plants are freshly pressed in the morning and at midday, in the evening the soma is extracted from the already-mangled  soma stems left over from the earlier pressings. Not only the soma preparation but  also the overall character of the Third Pressing is different. It has a greater focus on  the sacrificer and his wife, the gods of the Third Pressing form a less coherent group  than those of the other pressings, and in general, the rites of the Third Pressing  have the appearance of an appendix.+++(5)+++ It is possible that some family traditions did  not have a Third Pressing and that, among those that did, the form of the Third  Pressing was more fluid. Or again, in the Midday Pressing of the classical soma  ritual, there are offerings to Indra alone and to Indra along with the Maruts. This  form may represent a compromise between family traditions that offered soma only  to Indra at this second pressing and those that also included the Maruts.+++(4)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C Soma Ritual</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/C_Soma_Ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/C_Soma_Ritual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As we have frequently had occasion to remark, most of the hymns of the R̥gveda  were composed for the soma ritual. The central rite of this sacrifice was the prepa ration of the soma juice, which was then offered to the gods and shared among  male participants in the rite. In the R̥gvedic period the stalks of the soma plant  were probably placed on a stone and crushed using another stone or stones. The  extracted juice was either transferred to a vessel that contained water and then poured through or onto a woolen filter to purify it. In either case the soma then ran  into another vessel, in which it was mixed with milk. In the Agniṣṭoma of the classical tradition, there are three soma-pressings in a single day, although, as remarked  above, this may not have been true for the whole R̥gvedic period or for all ritual  traditions during the R̥gvedic period. The R̥gveda also knows the Atirātra or “over-night” form of the soma ritual, in which there are still three pressings on one day,  but in which the rite continues across the night. The final offerings of the Atirātra  are then made on the morning of the second day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D Other Rituals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/D_Other_Rituals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/04_Ritual/D_Other_Rituals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pravargya&#34;&gt;Pravargya&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In describing Vedic ritual we have thus far been discussing the soma sacrifice. But  while the soma sacrifice dominates the R̥gveda, the collection includes hymns composed for other rites as well. One of the sub-rites of the classical soma ritual is the  Pravargya, which according to most ritual sūtras is performed twice daily on the  three days leading up to the soma-pressing day. At an earlier stage, likely represented by the R̥gveda, the Pravargya was an independent rite, which was only later  incorporated into the soma tradition. Although the Pravargya is not mentioned by  name in R̥gveda, the text refers to the rite at the center of the Pravargya, an offering  to the Aśvins of gharmá, a mixture of hot milk and ghee, and the underlying verbal  lexeme prá √vr̥j is used in ritual context.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
