<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 Who, What, Where, When? on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 Who, What, Where, When? on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Veda and R̥gveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/A_Veda_and_Rgveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/A_Veda_and_Rgveda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The R̥gveda is the oldest Sanskrit text, composed in an archaic form of the language, known as Vedic or Vedic Sanskrit. It is a collection of over a thousand  poems, composed by a number of different poets over the course of some consid erable period of time. The poems are primarily hymns praising various gods and  ritual elements and procedures, designed to be recited during ritual performance;  that is, they are liturgical compositions. However, they are also finely crafted and  self-conscious literary productions of the highest quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B Date and Cultural Context of the R̥gveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/B_Date_and_Cultural_Context_of_the_Rgveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/B_Date_and_Cultural_Context_of_the_Rgveda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As was mentioned above, the R̥gveda is part of the long tradition of Indo-European  praise poetry, composed and performed orally and deploying inherited set verbal  formulae, on which the poets also ring changes. Thus, whatever date(s) we assign  to the actual composition of the particular hymns found in the text, the temporal  horizon of the R̥gveda stretches a good deal further back, in that the poetic techniques and even some of its precise verbal realizations go back many centuries, even  millennia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C What Do the Hymns Do?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/C_What_Do_the_Hymns_Do/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/C_What_Do_the_Hymns_Do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The overwhelming majority of R̥gvedic hymns have as their major aim to praise the  god(s) to whom the hymn is dedicated and to induce said god(s) to repay the praise  with requested favors. To a certain extent different gods receive different types of  praise, but the praise generally focuses on the appearance, qualities, and power of  the gods and on their remarkable deeds. Some divinities attract particular attention to their appearance: for instance, the seductive beauty of Dawn, the glittering  ostentation of the Maruts, the endlessly fascinating transformations of physical fire  and its divine embodiment Agni.+++(5)+++ Others, like the Ādityas, have few if any physical  characteristics, but are more celebrated for their mental and moral qualities. The  supernatural powers of almost all the gods receive abundant praise, though again  the types of power lauded differ from god to god.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D The Poet</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/D_The_Poet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/D_The_Poet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Who is the poet, and why is he composing poetry? The poets participate in an  elaborate patronage system. They are hirelings, but of a very superior sort. As  craftsmen of the word, their contribution to the success of the sacrifice that establishes and maintains the mutually beneficial relationship between men and gods is  critical, and they serve the patrons, often royal patrons (whatever “royal” meant at  this period), who arrange for and underwrite the sacrifice. The poet provides the  praise poetry that the patron needs to put the gods in his debt, and he speaks on  behalf of his patron, in making specific requests of the gods for goods and services.  The poet’s reward comes as a second-hand or indirect benefit of the success of his  verbal labors: the patron should receive from the gods what he asked for, and he  provides some portion of that bounty to the poet in recompense.+++(5)+++ This payment  from his patron is sometimes celebrated by the poet at the end of his hymn, in a  genre known as the dānastuti+++(5)+++, literally “praise of the gift,” in which the largesse of  the patron—cows, horses, gold, women—is catalogued and glorified. Or, if it is less  than expected or desired, scorned. The tone of the dānastuti is often teasing and  jokey, and the language colloquial.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E Structure of the R̥gveda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/E_Structure_of_the_Rgveda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/01_Who_What_Where_When/E_Structure_of_the_Rgveda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The R̥gveda comprises 1028 sūktas or hymns, which contain a total of slightly more  than 10,500 verses and which are divided into ten maṇḍalas, or books, of uneven  size. Within each maṇḍala there is a further division of the hymns into anuvākas  or “recitations” consisting of several hymns. The number of hymns in an anuvāka  varies within a maṇḍala, and the number of anuvākas in each maṇḍala varies from  maṇḍala to maṇḍala. As its name suggests, the anuvāka division was created prin cipally to provide convenient units for memorization and recitation. Although this  division is occasionally indicated in editions of the R̥gveda, we have not included  it in the translation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
