<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;00 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/00/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;00 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/00/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>CONTENTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/00/CONTENTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/00/CONTENTS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;II.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Foreward by the Editor&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PAGE,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Preface Contents&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; iii-yi&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;. vii-viii Introduction&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; ix&amp;ndash;1v FIRST BOOK. CHAPTER 1. The Dīkṣanīya Isti, with the Initiatory Rites&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1- 11 CHAPTER 2. Prāyanīya İṣçi&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; 11-18 CHAPTER 3, The buying and bringing of the Soma. The producing of Fire by&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;friction. The Atithya Iṣti ..&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;. 18- 28 CHAPTER 4. The Pravargya Ceremony. Upasad and Tānunaptram&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; 28 40 CHAPTER 5. The ceremonies of carrying the fire, Soma and the offerings from&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FOREWARD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/00/FOREWARD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/00/FOREWARD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE EDITOR. Dr. Martin Haug&amp;rsquo;s translation of the Aitareya Brahmana has been out of print for a long time, and so it has been reprinted as an extra volume in the series of the Sacred Books of the Hindus. To facilitate references to the original edition, paging of that edition has been given in Square brackets, thus [ ]. It has not been considered necessary to reprint the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit text, as better editions of that text are now available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/00/INTRODUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/00/INTRODUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On the Mantras, Brāhmanas, and Sūtras, and their mutual relationship.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Probable origin and age of the Mantras, and Brāhmanas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Veda, or Scripture of the Brāhmans, consists, according to the opinion of the most eminent divines of Hindustan, of two principal parts, viz., Mantra and Brahmanam. All that is regarded as revelation must be brought under these two heads. What of the revealed word is no Mantra, that is a Brāhmaṇam ; and what is no Brahmanam, must be a Mantra. This is the line of argument followed by the Brāhmanic theologians. But this does neither make clear what a Mantra is, nor what we have to understand by a Brāhmaṇam. Both terms are technical, and their full bearing, and characteristic difference from one another, is to be comprehended only from a careful study of those works which bear either of these titles. The Brāhmanical divines have, of course, not failed to give definitions of both, and shown what topics fall under the head of either. But, as Sayaṇa (in his preface to his Comment ary on the Aitareya Brahmaṇam) justly remarks, all definitions of either term which were attempted, are unsatisfactory. [2] We have here nothing to do with the theological definitions of these two terms; we are only concerned with their meaning, from a literary point of view. And this we can state without reference to Brāhmanic authorities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
