<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Reviews on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/reviews/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Reviews on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/reviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Karen Review</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/reviews/karen_review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/reviews/karen_review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Speak for itself&lt;br&gt;&#xA;How the long history of guesswork and commentary on a unique corpus of poetry has rendered it incomprehensible&lt;br&gt;&#xA;By KAREN THOMSON.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Reviewing:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Stephanie W. Jamison and Joel P. Brereton, translators&lt;br&gt;&#xA;THE RIGVEDA, The earliest religious poetry of India&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Roberto Calasso&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ARDOR, Translated by Richard Dixon&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first translation into English for over a century of the earliest Indo European poetic anthology has at last appeared, the work of two distinguished American indologists. Within its soberly academic trio of hardback volumes, however, seethes an incoherent mix of mumbo-jumbo and misplaced obscenity, most of it apparently meaningless. It reads like a burlesque version,in the style of &lt;em&gt;Hamlet Travestie&lt;/em&gt; +++(→ a parody of hamlet)+++, of a long lost original – except that the original is not lost, on the contrary, it has been immaculately preserved. “What”, as the Prince of Morocco said when he opened the golden casket, “have we here?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MT review</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/reviews/mt-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/reviews/mt-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Talking of academic plagiarism &amp;ndash; it is rampant in  academic circles, often perpetrated by powerful labs, especially in magazines &amp;amp; high stakes journals but nobody bothers as he powerful can do what they want. Coming to the American strain of white indology 1 could say that the recent translation of the R^igveda into English by 2 American indologists is in a sense a plagiarism because it is in large part a translation of the German translation of the RV by Karl Friedrich Geldner. Evidence for this comes from the fact that they repeat Geldner&amp;rsquo;s mistakes/misunderstandings. Geldner, himself was a pioneering scholar but there is more to the RV than accepting his translation as final.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
