<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST CHAPTER (The Characteristics and Sastras of the Third and Fourth&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Days of the Dvadasáha)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The Characteristics of the Third-Day. The Sastras of the Morning&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;and Midday Libations) The leading deities of the third day are the Visvedevah; its (leading) Stoma is the so-called Saptadasa (seventeen-fold), its Sāman the Vairūpam, its metre the Jagati. He who knows what deity, what Stoma, what Saman, what metre (are required on the third day), becomes successful by it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND CHAPTER. (The Characteristics and Sastras of the Fifth and Sixth Days of the Dvádasdha)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;6 The Characteristics of the Fifth day. The Sastras&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;of the Morning and Midday Libations) The leading deity of the fifth day is Gdus (the cow). Its Stoma is the Triṇata (twenty-seven-fold), the Saman is the Sakvaram, the metre is Pañkti. He who knows what deity, what Stoma, what Sāman, what metre (are required on this day), succeeds by it. What is not ā and not pra, what is fixed (stapding), that is a characteristic of the fifth day. Besides, the characteristics of the second day re-occur in the fifth, such as urdhva, prati, antar, vriṣan, vridhan: the mentioning of the deity in the middle pada, an allusion to the airy region. (In addition to these, there are the following peculiar characteristics), dugdha, (duh to milk) udha (udder), dhenu (cow) przśni (cloud, cow) mad (drunk), the animal form, an increase (adhyásah),&amp;rsquo; for the animals differ in size, as it were, one being smaller or bigger than the other.&amp;rsquo; This (fifth) day is jagatam, i.e., it refers to the movable jagat) things (or the Jagati metre), for [381] the animals are movable ; it is bárhatam, for the animals have reference to the Bșihatī metre; it is páriktam, for the animals refer to the Pañkti metre; it is vāman, i.e., left, because the animals are of this quality. It is haviṣmat, i.e., having offerings; because the animals&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD CHAPTER (The Characteristics and Sastras of the Seventh and Eighth Days.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Characteristics of the Seventh Day. The Sastras of the Morning&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;and Midday Libation.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;• The terms a and pra are the characteristics of the seventh day. The seventh day is just like the first, yakta, ratha, đšu, piba, the deity mentioned in the first pada, the allusion to this world (earth,) jata, anirukta, kariṣyat (future), these are the characteristics of the seventh day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH CHAPTER. (The Ninth and Tenth Days of the Dvadašaha. Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;of this Sacrifice.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Characteristics of the Ninth Day. The Sastras of the Morning and&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Midday Libations.) What has the same refrain, is a characteristic of the ninth day. This day has the same characteristics as [854] the third, viz., aśva, anta, punara vrāttam, punarninrittam, rata, paryasta, the number three, antarūpa, the mentioning of the deity in the last pada, an allusion to that world, suchi splendour, satya truth, kṣeti to reside, gata gone, oka house, the past tense.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/05/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIFTH CHAPTER. (The Agnihotram. On the Duties of the Brahma Priest).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Agnihotram. When the Sacrificer has to Order his Priest to Bring Fire to the Ahavaniya. The Sixteen Parts of the Agnihotram.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Agnihotri says to his Adhvaryu, &amp;quot; Take from ” (here the Gārha patya fire) the Ahavaniya fire.” Thus he says at evening ; for what good he was doing during the day, all that is taken away (together with [864] the fire and brought) eastwards and put in safety. If he says at morning time, &amp;ldquo;Take from (here) the Ahavaniya,” then he takes with him all the good he was doing during the night (brings it) eastwards and puts it in safety. The Ahavaniya fire is the sacrifice (sacrificial fire); the Ahavaniya is the heaven-world. He who has this knowledge, places the heaven-world (the real heaven) in the heaven-world, which (is represented by) the sacrifice alone. Who knows the Agnihotram which belongs to all gods, which consists of sixteen parts, and is placed among cattle, is successful by means of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
