<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 The Gods on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 The Gods on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Nature of the Gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/A_Nature_of_the_Gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/A_Nature_of_the_Gods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yāskas-classification&#34;&gt;Yāska&amp;rsquo;s classification&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The great majority of R̥gvedic hymns are dedicated to individual gods or to groups  of gods. Following a classification articulated already in I.139.11, Yāska (Nir.  VII.5) divided the gods into three categories: gods of the earth, gods of the mid space, and gods of heaven. This simple scheme has the advantage of being clear  and the disadvantage of being misleading. For while the R̥gvedic pantheon includes  deities who represent the visible realities and powers of the natural world, it is not  fully composed of such gods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B Devas and Asuras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/B_Devas_and_Asuras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/B_Devas_and_Asuras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Beginning with the Vedic prose texts, one of the most enduring mythological struc tures is the perpetual conflict between Devas (devá being the Sanskrit word for  “god”) and Asuras, with the two (almost) balanced groups contending with each  other in numerous myths and myth fragments in all sorts of situations. The Asuras  are, as it were, the anti-Devas, with negative traits exactly corresponding to the posi tive ones possessed by the Devas. In the various combats depicted, the Devas always  prevail, but only barely. This conflict continues to be prominent in the post-Vedic  religious landscape, as in the well-known story of the churning of the ocean of milk  in which the two moieties fight over the treasures churned up.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C Viśve DevĀḤ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/C_Visve_DevAH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/C_Visve_DevAH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The term víśve devā́ḥ “all the gods” or “the All Gods” is common in the R̥gveda,  and the Anukramaṇī identifies the divinity of a large number of hymns as víśve  devā́ḥ. The term, both in its usage in the text and in its application to a hymn type,  is employed in a number of different senses. On the one hand, it is a handy way to  refer to the whole divine community, to ensure that no god has been left out of a  generic eulogy or request for aid. In this usage the gods are not treated as individuals but as an undifferentiated group, opposed to mortals or, later, the Asuras (see  just above). This group ultimately becomes conceived of as a sort of corporate  entity, the All Gods. On the other hand, many Viśve Devāḥ hymns do not encompass the whole group, but name a series of individual gods, each one often allotted  a single verse in a list hymn (e.g., VI.49). Here the phrase “all the gods” is a way  of indicating that the hymn is not targeting a single god, as in the majority or  R̥gvedic hymns, but selecting from the group. And finally a number of hymns with  the Anukramaṇī designation “all gods” actually have very little to do with the gods  at all, but contain meditations on the mysteries of the cosmos, of the sacrifice, or of  the powers of poetry and ritual speech (see, e.g., I.105).+++(4)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D Indra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/D_Indra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/D_Indra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As the preeminent god of the R̥gveda, Indra has a variety of roles. But first of  all Indra is a warrior, upon whom depend the protection and prosperity of his  worshipers. His weapon is the vájra, the mace. In later tradition, when Indra was  reduced to a storm god, the vajra became a thunderbolt. But in the R̥gveda it was a  weapon, which could be thrown at an enemy or smashed down upon him, and the  principal means by which Indra asserted his power.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E Agni “Fire”</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/E_Agni_Fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/E_Agni_Fire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The word agní is both the common noun meaning “fire” and the name of the god  who is deified fire. As with sóma (see below), it is often difficult to draw the line  between these uses. The sacrificial system of the R̥gveda (and later Vedic texts), like  that of the cognate Old Iranian Avestan texts, is focused around the ritual fire. The  sacrificial ground is defined by the presence of sanctified fire(s), oblations are made  into them, and the gods and priests gather round them. Thus, first and foremost,  Agni is the god always present at our ritual performances and the immediate recipient of our offerings. He is the most prominent of the R̥gvedic gods after Indra, and  all the Family Books and most of the smaller bardic collections open with their  Agni hymns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F Soma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/F_Soma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/F_Soma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like Agni, Soma is both a god and a crucial ritual substance, and the boundary  between them is not always clear. As has already been discussed, the juice of the  soma plant (whatever that may have been), pressed from the plant and elaborately prepared, is the chief offering of the most important complex of rituals, the  soma sacrifice. This sacrificial substance and its ritual preparation go back to the  Indo-Iranian period, since Avestan attests to the substance haoma, an exact cognate  to Sanskrit sóma, and to its pressing and offering (see especially the so-called Hōm  Yašt, Y 9–10). In both traditions the substance is also deified.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>G Aditi and the ādityas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/G_Aditi_and_the_adityas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/G_Aditi_and_the_adityas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a group, the Ādityas generally represent the powers that order human society.+++(5)+++  This function is most evident in the three principal Ādityas, Varuṇa, Mitra, and  Aryaman. In addition to these three, however, there are minor deities who are also  called Ādityas—Dakṣa, Bhaga, and Aṃśa—and a number of other gods, such as  Savitar and Sūrya, who may be called Ādityas when they exercise functions like  those of the major Ādityas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H Savitar</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/H_Savitar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/H_Savitar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes linked to the Ādityas and especially to Bhaga is the god Savitar. He is  the god who “impels” or “compels” beings—and these can include mortals, gods, animals, and objects. He especially acts at the beginning of night, when he sends  beings to rest (cf. I.35.2, IV.53.3, VII.45.1). But he also commands the end of the  night and the beginning of the day, when he brings forth the sun (I.35.9) and impels  beings to action. Because he is associated with the night, he is also connected with  the generation of offspring, who would be conceived during the night.+++(4)+++ Savitar is  bright, with golden eyes, golden arms, and golden hands. He stretches out his arms  in a gesture of command (II.38.2). Falk (1988: 17–22) reasonably suggests that his  brilliance during the night and his outstretched arms point to the Milky Way as a  manifestation of Savitar.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I SŪrya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/I_SUrya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/I_SUrya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If the Milky Way is the celestial embodiment of Savitar, Sūrya, the Sun, comes  close to being that of Mitra and Varuṇa. The Sun is their eye, for his gaze is wide  (VII.35.8) and falls on everyone (I.50.2). The Sun watches over the good and evil  deeds of humans (VI.51.2, VII.60.2–3) and, so the poet hopes, declares the innocence of the sacrificers to Mitra and Varuṇa (VII.60.1, 62.2). The Sun is the felly  that rolls toward Mitra and Varuṇa (V.62.2) or the chariot that the two gods set  in heaven (V.63.7). Since he is so closely linked to the Ādityas, he himself is called  an Āditya (I.50.13, 191.9; VIII.101.11). His link to the Ādityas is also a link to the  king, who oversees his subjects the way that the Sun oversees all beings (X.121 and  Proferes 2007: 137–41).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>J UṢas “Dawn”</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/J_USas_Dawn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/J_USas_Dawn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dawn is one of the few female divinities in the R̥gveda and the most prominent  among them. Twenty-one hymns are dedicated to her alone (every maṇḍala but  II, VIII, and of course IX containing at least one), many of them displaying high  poetic artistry and beauty of imagery, and she is mentioned hundreds of times in the text. She also has an Indo-European pedigree, being cognate with the Greek  goddess Eos and the Latin goddess Aurora.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>K VĀyu / VĀta “Wind”</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/K_vAyu_VAta_Wind/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/K_vAyu_VAta_Wind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As his name indicates, Vāyu is an ancient god of the Wind, although verses to Vāyu  that refer to the phenomenon of wind are somewhat rare and oblique. For example, the roar of Vāyu echoes the sound of the wind, his hundredfold (I.135.3) or thou sandfold (I.135.1) team reflects the wind’s speed, and the Maruts, who personify  thunderstorms especially the monsoon storms, are born from his belly (I.134.4).  Such characteristics show Vāyu’s close connection to the wind, even though he does  not represent the wind directly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L AŚvins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/L_ASvins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/L_ASvins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Aśvins, the two “Horsemen,” are old Indo-Iranian or even Indo-European dei ties who have been brought into the soma rite.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nāsatyas&#34;&gt;Nāsatyas&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They are also called Nāsatyas, a  name of obscure meaning and etymology, found already in an ancient Near Eastern  Hatti-Mitanni treaty dating from the fourteenth century bce (in the form Na-ša-at ti-i̯a) and in the Avestan cognate, Nā̊ŋhaiθya.+++(4)+++ It is probably the older name of  this pair, with the lexically transparent aśvín originally an epithet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>M Maruts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/M_Maruts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/M_Maruts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Maruts are a troop of male gods. Though they lack individual identities, they  are quite prominent as a group: over thirty hymns are dedicated to them alone and  several more to them in conjunction with Indra, and they are frequently mentioned  elsewhere. Their character has both naturalistic and social aspects. On the one  hand, they are the embodiments of the thunderstorm, especially of the monsoon,  and many of their aspects reflect this natural phenomenon: like lightning, they are  brilliant and flashing, bedecked with ornaments and glittering weapons; like thunder, they are excessively noisy on their wild chariot journeys, causing the earth to  shake with fear, bending the trees and even the mountain; like thunderclouds, they  are shape-shifting and sometimes clothed in gray; and they are accompanied by  floods of rain.+++(4)+++ The terror they inspire is more than balanced by the fructifying rains  they bring. All these physical aspects of the Maruts often inspire the poets to vivid  and imaginative language.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>N Heaven and Earth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/N_Heaven_and_Earth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/N_Heaven_and_Earth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most remarkable and satisfying phrasal equations across the older  Indo-European languages is that of Vedic dyaúṣ pitā́ “father Heaven” with Greek  Zeus Pater and Latin Jupiter, thus attesting to a deified paternal Heaven for  Proto-Indo-European as well as the older daughter languages. Ironically perhaps,  the Vedic god, the meaning of whose name is still transparent and lexically additive, is far less important in the Vedic pantheon than his correspondents in the  Classical languages, where the original semantics have become attenuated or have  disappeared entirely.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>O TvaṢṬar</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/O_TvaSTar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/O_TvaSTar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The meaning of Tvaṣṭar’s name is fully transparent:  he is the “Fashioner,” who  “adorned all the creatures with their forms” (X.110.9) and who knows all living  things (IV.42.3). But his role is more complex than his name might imply. He is the  father of Indra (III.48.2–4, IV.18), whom Indra displaced and from whom Indra  stole the soma (III.48.4). On the other hand, Tvaṣṭar fashioned Indra’s distinctive weapon, the mace, for him (I.32.2, V.31.4, VI.17.10, X.48.3). Tvaṣṭar is also  sometimes called the father of Agni (III.7.4), and he is the god who has begotten  offspring (III.55.19; cf. III.4.9). His role as a father perhaps explains his close relationship with the Wives of the Gods (I.22.9, 161.4; II.1.5, 31.4, 36.3; VII.35.6), with  whom he is ritually joined.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>P R̥bhus</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/P_Rbhus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/P_Rbhus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In some forms of the soma sacrifice, the three R̥bhus have a significant role as principal soma recipients in the Third Pressing. But despite that role, they have a limited  presence in the R̥gveda itself. Only ten hymns are dedicated to the R̥bhus, together  with one other that invokes the R̥bhus along with Indra. Nonetheless, despite their  decidedly low profile in the R̥gveda, their principal actions emerge clearly. The  R̥bhu hymns repeatedly return to five great deeds for which the R̥bhus are famed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Q PŪṢan</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/Q_PUSan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/Q_PUSan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although Pūṣan is a minor god in the R̥gveda, with only eight hymns dedicated  to him alone and several more shared with more prominent divinities (Indra and  Soma), his idiosyncratic characteristics and the special diction used in his hymns  attract more than his share of attention to him. Of the bardic families, only the  Bharadvājas of Maṇḍala VI favor this god; they dedicate five hymns to him (VI.53– 56, 58) with a further one to Pūṣan and Indra (VI.57) and a significant portion of  the composite hymn VI.48; the three other hymns exclusive to him are found in  I and X.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R ViṢṆu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/R_ViSNu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/R_ViSNu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the middle Vedic period, Viṣṇu became a central figure as the embodiment of the  sacrifice itself+++(4)+++ and therefore of a power that can exceed even the might of the gods.  In classical India, of course, he finds an even greater destiny.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is little sign of  those futures of Viṣṇu in the R̥gveda, since it has only a half dozen hymns dedicated  to Viṣṇu or to Indra and Viṣṇu (I.154, 155, 156; VI.69; VII.99, 100).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S Rudra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/S_Rudra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/S_Rudra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although Rudra, under his euphemistic epithet Śiva, “the kindly one,” has, of  course, an extraordinarily great future in classical Hinduism, in the R̥gveda he has  a very circumscribed role, with only three complete hymns dedicated to him. He  has two major and complementary characteristics:  on the one hand, he is fierce  and malevolent, with an often inexplicable anger that needs to be appeased; on  the other, he is a healer, who controls the remedies for disease. He is also, as noted  above, the father of the Maruts, who are much more prominent in our text.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T Sarasvatī and the Rivers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/T_Sarasvati_and_the_Rivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/T_Sarasvati_and_the_Rivers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another divinity with a great future ahead but little prominence in our text is the  goddess Sarasvatī. Again the R̥gveda provides little or no evidence for her later role  as patron of learning and the arts, though a number of scholars have attempted  to find it. Instead she is celebrated, in the three hymns dedicated to her and in  other mentions in the text, simply as a physical river with a powerful flow, which is  sometimes destructive but which also provides fecundity with its fructifying waters.  Other rivers are also praised in the R̥gveda, especially the Sindhu in a hymn dedicated to the rivers in general.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>U VĀc “Speech”</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/U_VAc_Speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/05_The_Gods/U_VAc_Speech/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One last goddess should be mentioned, Vāc or deified Speech (a noun with feminine  gender). Although this goddess figures in a number of mythological narratives in  the middle Vedic period, and although she ultimately seems to have become conflated with Sarasvatī, thus amplifying the status of both goddesses, in the R̥gveda  she appears as a clear personage very rarely, most prominently in a late hymn  (X.125), which is a 1st-person self-praise (ātmastuti) spoken by Vāc herself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
