<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;08 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;08 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST CHAPTER. (The Sastras and Stotras required at the Soma Day of the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rajastya.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;y&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Use of Both the Rathantaran and Brihat at the Midday Libation)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now, as regards the Stotras and Sastras (required at the king&amp;rsquo;s liba tion), both the morning and the evening libations do not differ in this point from the rule of the Aikāhikas (Soma sacrifice of one day&amp;rsquo;s duration): for both these libations at the Aikāhika sacrifices are indisturbable, well arrangeri, aod firmly standing, and they produce quiet, good order, firm footing, and security.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND CHAPTER. (Pungra bhiṣeka, or Repetition of the Inauguration Ceremony.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Implements and Preparation for Punarabhiṣeka.) Now follows (the rule) of Punarabhiseka of the Ksattriya who is inaugurated as a sacrificer, and whose Kṣattram is in (such a way) new born. After having undergone the ceremonies of ablutions and perform ed the animal sacrifice (anubandhya), he performs the concluding Isti.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After this Isti is finished (and thus the Soma day of the Rājaṣūya concluded), they sprinkle him again with the boly water (they make punarabhiṣeka). Before it commences, all implements must be in readiness, viz., a throne, made from Udumbara wood, with feet only as large as the span between the thumb and forefinger, and successive helmets of the length of half an arm, (besides there must be provided for) cords for bind ing made of Muñja grass, a tiger skin for covering the throne, a (large) ladle of Udumbara wood and a (small) branch of the Udumbara tree. In this ladle the following eight substances are thrown: curds, honey, clarified butter, rain-water fallen, during sunshine, young sprouts of grass and of green barley, liquor and Dūb grass (Dūrvā). The throne is to be placed in the southern line, drawn by a wooden sword (sphya) in the Vedi, the front part (508] turned eastwards. Two of its feet are to be within the Vedi and two outside. For this earth is (the goddess of) fortune; the little space within the Vedi is thus allotted to her, as well as the large (infinite) region outside. If thus two feet of the throne are inside and two outside the Vedi, both kinds of desires, those obtainable from the place within as well as from outside the Vedi, are to be gained.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD CHAPTER (The Molābhiseko or Grand Inaugurution Cervui&amp;rsquo;ney of Indra.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Elevation of Indra to the Royalty over the Gods. His Throne-scat.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By what blantrus ke Ascended it. The Gods Proclaim him as King by mentioning all his Titles.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now follows the great inauguration (mahabhiṣcka) of Indra. The gods, headed by Prajapati, said to one another (pointing with their hands to Indra) : “ This one is among the gods the most vigorous, most strong, most valiant, most perfect, who carries best out any work (to be done). Let us iostal him to the kingship over us).” They all consented to (515) perform just this ceremony (mahābhiṣeka) on Indra. They brought for him that throne-seat, which is called the Rik-formed. They made the Brihat and Rathantara verses its two forelegs, the Vairūpa and Vairāja verses its hind-legs, the Sakvara and Raivata (verses) its, top boards,&amp;rsquo;the Náudhasa and Kaleya its side-boards. The Rik verses were made the threads of the texture which went lengthwise, the Samans were the threads which went crossways, the Yajus verses the intervals in the texture. They made (the goddess of) Glory its covering, and (the goddess of) Fortune its pillow, Savitar and Brilaspati were holding its two fore legs, Váyu and Pūṣan the two hind-legs, Mitra and Varuṇa the two top-boards, the Aśvins the two side-boards.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH CHAPTER. (The Mahabhiseka Ceremony Performed on a King. What Rigis&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Performed it, and for what Kings they Performed it.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Consequences of the Malabluseka, The Oath which the King must&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;take Before the Priest Performs the Ceremony.) The priest who, with this knowledge (about the Mahābhiṣeka ceremony), wishes that a Kṣattriya should conquer in all the various ways of conquest, to subjugate all people, and that he should attain to leadership, precedence, and supremacy over all kings, and attain every where and at all times to universal sovereignty, enjoyment (of pleasures), independence, distinguished distinction as king, the fulfilment of the highest desires, the position of a king, of a great king, and supreme mastership, that he might cross (with his arms) the universe, and become the ruler of the whole earth during all his life, which may last for an infinitely long time, that he might be the sole king of the earth up to its (520) shores bordering on the ocean ; such a priest should inaugurate the Kṣattriya with Indra&amp;rsquo;s great inauguration ceremony. But, before doing so, the priest must make the king take the following oath : &amp;quot; What&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/08/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIFTH CHAPTER. (On the Office of the Purohitae, or House-priest. The Brahmanan Parimara, i. e., Dying Around the Brahma..)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;24 (The Necessity for a King to Appoint a House-priest. In what Way the King Keeps the Sacred Fires. How to Appease the Five&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Destructive Powers of Agni). Now, about the office of a Purohita (house-priest). The gods do not eat the food offered by a king who has no bouse-priest (Purohita). Thence the king even when (not) intending to bring a sacrifice, should appoint a Brahman to the office of house-priest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
