<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०७ on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०७ on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>००१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/001/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/001/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/001/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ अथ सप्तमं मण्डलम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथ सप्तमं मण्डलमारभ्यते । तस्मिन् मण्डले षडनुवाकाः । प्रथमेऽनुवाके सप्तदश सूक्तानि ।  तत्र ‘अग्नि नरः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चविंशत्यृचं प्रथमं सूक्तम् । अत्रेयमनुक्रमणिका&amp;mdash;&amp;rsquo; अग्निं पञ्चाधिका विराजोऽष्टादशाद्याः&amp;rsquo; इति । ‘ सप्तमं मण्डलं वसिष्ठोऽपश्यत् । इत्युक्तत्वात् मण्डलद्रष्टा वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । आदितोऽष्टादश विराजस्त्र्येकादशकाः शिष्टा अनादेशपरिभाषया त्रिष्टुभः । मण्डलादिपरिभाषया अग्निर्देवता । विश्वजितीदं सूक्तमाज्यशस्त्रम् । सूत्रितं च-’ विश्वजितोऽग्निं नर इत्याज्यम् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ७) इति । अत्रेश्चतुर्वीराख्ये चतूरात्रे&amp;rsquo; चतुर्थेऽहनीदमेव सूक्तमाज्यशस्त्रम्। सूत्र्यते हि- अग्निं नर इति चतुर्थे &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. १०. २ ) इति । व्यूळ्हे दशरात्रे चतुर्थेऽहनीदं सूक्तं जातवेदस्यनिविद्धानम्। सूत्रितं च-’ अग्निं नर इत्याग्निमारुतम् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ८) इति । महाव्रतेऽपीदमाज्यशस्त्रम् । तथैव पञ्चमारण्यके सूत्र्यते&amp;ndash;’ आज्यप्रउगे विश्वजितः &amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५.१.१ ) इति । अविवाक्येऽहनि प्रातरनुवाके ‘त्वमग्ने वसून्&amp;rsquo; इत्यादीनामनुष्टुभां स्थान आद्यस्तृचः प्रक्षेपणीयः । सूत्र्यते हि-’ दशमेऽहन्यनुष्टुभां स्थानेऽग्निं नरो दीधितिभिररण्योरिति तृचमाग्नेये क्रतौ &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८.१२ ) इति । आद्याः पडृचः तस्मिन्नेवाहनि आग्निमारुते शस्त्रे स्तोत्रियानुरूपार्थाः । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; अग्निं नरो दीधितिभिररण्योरिति स्तोत्रियानुरूपौ&amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ८.१२ ) इति । मण्डलादिहोमेऽप्येषा । आधाने तृतीयायामिष्टौ ‘प्रेद्धः&amp;rsquo; इति स्विष्टकृतोऽनुवाक्या । सूत्रितं च -’ प्रेद्धो अग्न इमो अग्न इति संयाज्ये&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. २.१) इति । एवमन्यत्रापि दीक्षणीयादिषु स्विष्टकृतोऽनुवाक्या । प्रायणीयेष्टौ ‘सेदग्निरग्नीन्&amp;rsquo; इत्यादिके द्वे स्विष्टकृतो याज्यानुवाक्ये । सूत्रितं च – &amp;rsquo; सेदग्निरग्नीँरत्यस्त्वन्यानिति द्वे संयाज्ये&amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ४.३ ) इति । आधाने तृतीयायामिष्टौ ‘इमो अग्ने&amp;rsquo; इति स्विष्टकृतो याज्या । सूत्रितं च- ‘इमो अग्न इति संयाज्ये&amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. २.१ ) इति । एवमन्यत्रापि दीक्षणीयादिष्वेषा सौविष्टकृती याज्या । प्रातरनुवाक आग्नेये क्रतौ त्रैष्टुभे छन्दस्याश्विनशस्त्रे च ‘त्वमग्ने सुहवः&amp;rsquo; इत्याद्याः पञ्चर्चः । सूत्रितं च-’ त्वमग्ने सुहवो रण्वसंदृक् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ४.१३ ) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/002/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/002/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ जुषस्व नः&amp;rsquo; इत्येकादशर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभम् । आप्रशब्दोक्तत्वादिदं तनूनपाद्रहितम् । समिद्धाद्या अग्निविशेषाः प्रत्यृचं देवता उक्ताः । तथा चानुक्रम्यते- जुषस्वैकादशाप्रम्  इति । पशाविष्टाविदमाप्रीसूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; जुषस्व नः समिधमिति वसिष्ठानाम् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ३. २) इति । पत्नीसंयाजे त्वष्ट्यागस्य याज्या त्वाष्ट्रे पशावपि पुरोडाशस्यानुवाक्येयमिति पूर्वमुक्तम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2 (518)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Āprı̄&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;11 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This Āprī hymn offers several original images and turns of phrase, even as it follows  the prescribed sequence of invocations. In verse 2cd the gods who sweeten the offer ings are probably the assembly of the deities and divine objects who are invoked in  the hymn. Two similes complicate the second half of verse 5. The priests open the  doors so that the chariot, probably the sacrifice itself, can pass into the realm of the  gods. In 5cd with their oblations of ghee the priests anoint the many doors that lead  to the gods. In pāda c the doors are compared to cows licking a calf. We have sug gested that the “divine chariot,” the sacrifice, corresponds to the calf and that the  ghee-offerings at the Prayājas, the “fore-offerings,” are the “licks.” It is not entirely  clear why the doors are compared to unmarried girls in pāda d. The ritual situation  to which the verse refers, however, is explained by I.124.8, which describes anointed  brides-to-be who about to choose a husband (vrā́) at the assemblies (sámana) that  include prospective grooms. The two similes are united by the representation of  the dúraḥ, which are grammatically feminine, as females: mothers and brides. And  finally, rather unusually, verse 7 identifies the two divine Hotars, who are not actu ally named, each as Agni Jātavedas. The phrasing suggests that this verse may be  a reversal of V.9.1–2. In V.9.1c the poet says mánye tvā jātávedasam “I think you884 VII.2&lt;br&gt;&#xA;[=Agni] to be Jātavedas,” and then in 2a, he calls Agni a Hotar. Alternatively, the  form jātávedasā could be an elliptical dual, as Geldner suggests, in which one of the  pair is Agni Jātavedas and the other the “inspired praise poet.”&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The conclusion of the hymn, verses 8–11, is identical to III.4.8–11, so either  the Viśvāmitra Āprī hymn has borrowed from this Vasiṣṭha hymn or vice versa.  Presumably the first part of the hymn was enough to make each of the two hymns  sufficiently unique to its gotra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/003/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/003/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;rsquo; अग्निं वो देवम् &amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाग्नेयम् । अत्रेयानुक्रमणिका’ अग्निं वो दश&amp;rsquo; इति । अग्निं वो देवम्&amp;rsquo; इत्येतदादीनि दश सूक्तानि तृतीयचतुर्थवर्जितानि प्रातरनुवाक आग्नेये क्रतौ त्रैष्टुभे  छन्दस्याश्विनशस्त्रे व विनियुक्तानि । सूत्रितं च- अग्निं वो देवमिति दशानां तृतीयचतुर्थे उद्धरेत् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ४.१३) इति । व्यूळ्हे दशरात्रेऽष्टमेऽहनीदं सूक्तमाज्यशस्त्रम् । सूत्र्यते हि &amp;ndash; द्वितीयस्याग्निं वो देवमित्याज्यम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८.१०) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/004/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/004/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र वः शुक्राय&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं चतुर्थं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाग्नेयम् । ‘प्र वः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोर्दशसूक्तमध्ये द्वितीयत्वेनोक्तः सूक्तविनियोगः । एकादशिन आग्नेये पशौ ‘ प्र वः शुक्राय&amp;rsquo; इत्येषा वपाया याज्या । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash;-’ प्र वः शुक्राय भानवे भरध्वं यथा विप्रस्य मनुषो हविर्भिः&amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ३.७) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4 (520)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;According to Geldner, this hymn expresses the wish for a son or for a replace ment for a lost son. This is a wish found already in VII.1, but it is even more  strongly articulated here. The best evidence for this interpretation is verses 7–8,  which describe the importance of a son of one’s own. Nonetheless, in our view,  the subject of this hymn is more likely Agni than a son, and its concern is with a  fire that has not come or is just coming to birth. The poet wants a fire of his own,  which will bring wealth to him and preserve his life. To be sure, the hymn does  contain an implicit analogy between Agni and a son, who likewise brings wealth  and preserves the family.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;One of the features of this hymn is the repetition of a word or of related words  in successive lines or verses: jagr̥bhré (3b) and gŕ̥bham (3c); uvóca (3c) and durókam (3d); agnír amŕ̥taḥ (4b), agnír amŕ̥tān (5b), and agnír amŕ̥tasya (6a); pári ṣadāma (6d)  and pariṣádyam (7a); and áraṇasya (7a) and áraṇaḥ (8a). Other repetitions occur at  a greater distance. Thus verse 8, the third from the last verse, has grábhāya (8a) and  ókaḥ (8c), echoing the repetitions within verse 3. This technique does not occur in  the first, introductory verse, nor in the last two verses, which are also VI.15.12 and  VII.3.10 respectively and which may have been borrowed from these hymns. These  verbal repetitions are a challenge to translate, particularly because in some cases the  poet uses the words in different senses. So, for example, amŕ̥ta refers to the “immor&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tal” gods in verse 5 but to “living” human beings in verse 6. In verse 6 pári √sad describes the sacrificers “sitting around” the fire, but in verse 7 it probably refers to  sequestering something or keeping it separate by drawing a notional circle around it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/005/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/005/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/005/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ प्राग्नये तवसे&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं पञ्चमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वैश्वानराग्निदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं &amp;ndash; प्राग्नये नव वैश्वानरीयं तु&amp;rsquo; इति । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;5 (521)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni Vaiśvānara&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn invokes Agni as both the fire on earth and the sun in heaven. More spe cifically, Agni is a tribal fire, which here represents an aggregation of clans in the  Pūru tribe (vs. 3). This hymn thus accords with VII.19.3, in which Indra also sup ports the Pūru tribe, but contrasts with VII.18.13, in which Indra supports Sudās,  the enemy of the Pūru. As Proferes (2007: 46–49) details, it is as a tribal fire and  as the sun that Agni is called Vaiśvānara, a name repeated in each of the first five  verses and then again in the last two (8–9).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins with a statement of Agni’s presence in heaven and on earth,  nurtured by both the gods and priests (vs. 1). In the second verse Agni is called  the master of both flowing and pooling waters, a theme echoed in verse 8, the  second to last verse, in which Agni is asked to send the “refreshing drink,” which  might be the rain for humans or the soma for the gods or both. Having descended to earth, Agni’s radiance extends to the Ārya clans (vs. 2cd). In verse 3 the  víśaḥ&amp;hellip; aśiknīḥ “dark clans” are Dasyus (vs. 6), but they are not dark because they  are “dark-skinned,” as the description is often interpreted, but rather because they  represent powers of darkness opposed to the Āryas (cf. Hock 1999). Note that  the brilliance of Agni in 3cd breaks apart the “dark clans” and, as light, disperses  darkness. Or likewise in verse 6 Agni drives away the Dasyus, providing a “broad  light” for Āryas. As fire and sun, Agni extends his light throughout the worlds  (vs. 4). In verse 5, the middle verse of the hymn, the poet concretizes Agni as the  present sacrificial fire, who guards and prospers the different communities and as  both the sacrificial fire and the sun, both of which appear in the early morning as  beacons of the day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/006/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र सम्राजः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं षष्ठं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षम् । अनुक्रम्यते च-’ प्र सम्राजः सप्त&amp;rsquo; । ‘वैश्वानरीयं तु &amp;rsquo; इत्युक्तत्वादस्यापि वैश्वानरोऽग्निर्देवता । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;6 (522)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni Vaiśvānara&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In its first verse this poem implicitly connects Agni with Varuṇa and Indra. In 1ab  Agni is called a “universal king and lord” to be honored “by the settlements.” This  description recalls Varuṇa and his rule over settled communities. Then in the second  hemistich Agni’s acts are explicitly compared to the heroic deeds of Indra during  war. The description of Agni as the “breaker”—if that is the meaning of dārú in  1d—is appropriate to him: in X.69.3d the poet asks of Agni sá vā́jaṃ darṣi “Break  out victory’s prize.” But the word also anticipates puraṃdará “breaker of strong&lt;br&gt;&#xA;holds” in 2c, here an epithet of Agni but normally one of Indra. In 2cd the two  gods, Indra and Varuṇa, are combined in Agni through the description of him as  puraṃdará and through reference to his vratá “commandment,” a term that is con ceptually and etymologically connected to Varuṇa. But then in verse 3 Agni takes  on the persona of Indra more exclusively as one who pursues the Paṇis, who are the  great enemies of Indra in his destruction of the Vala cave. The reference to Agni as  the one who brings the dawn in verses 4–5 is appropriate to the fire of the morning  sacrifice, but it also continues the reference to the Vala story, telling of the release  of the dawns. In verse 5cd Nahuṣ is the ancestor of the Nahuṣa, a tribe of whom  Agni takes possession. In I.31.11 Agni is the clanlord of the Nahuṣa, but it is still  not clear why they are mentioned here, although doing so does bring Agni’s action  down to earth and perhaps into the present. The last two verses give Agni posses&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sion of the whole earth, including the goods and peoples on it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/007/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र वो देवम्&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं सप्तमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाग्नेयम् । ‘प्र वो देवम्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोर्दशसूक्ते उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;7 (523)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poet invokes the powerful Agni—the god who acts with strength (sahasānám) in  the first verse and is summoned as the “son of strength” (sūno sahasaḥ) in the last.  Within this recursive frame the poet follows the descent of Agni from the heaven onto  the earth. In 1d Agni runs at “a measured pace” and is found “among the gods in his  own person,” that is, in the form of the burning sun. He is then invited to journey to  earth (vs. 2) and to the sacrificial place as a participant in the rite (vs. 3). Still, Agni  remains simultaneously earthly and heavenly. His “two mothers” or “mother and  father” in 3c are Earth and Heaven, but they can also be the two fire-churning sticks,  the aráṇī̆. In verse 4 Agni’s birth is set squarely on earth and at the sacrifice, where he  assumes his role as chief priest of the rite (vss. 4–5). Verse 6 presents an interesting  problem since it is not clear who is spoken about. In our view the subject is most likely  the gods, to whom the poet now returns at the end of the hymn, thus balancing the  reference to them in verses 1–2. But pādas a and cd can also describe the patrons of  the sacrifice and b can parenthetically refer to the priests, as Geldner suggests. This  ambiguity is likely intentional, allowing a double reference to gods and humans.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/008/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/008/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘इन्धे राजा&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चमष्टमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाग्नेयम् । इन्धे राजा&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोर्विनियोगः । आतिथ्यायां प्रप्रायमग्निः&amp;rsquo; इति स्विष्टकृतो याज्या। सूत्रितं च –‘प्रप्रायमग्निर्भरतस्य शृण्व इति संयाज्ये&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ४.५) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;8 (524)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Commenting on verse 4, Proferes (2007: 37) rightly says that this Agni, the fire of  the Bharatas, is linked to the military power of the tribe, and it is he, not the king  or the warriors, who is credited for the victory over the enemy tribe of the Pūrus.  There are hints of the extent of Agni’s power to repel the Pūrus in the repetition  of ví “afar” in verses 2, 3, and 4. Likewise, the poet describes how Agni, the son  of strength (vs. 7), becomes mighty (vs. 2) and makes his body strong (vs. 5). In an  interesting twist, Agni’s bodily strength, which is marked by his brightness, will  drive human bodily illness into darkness (vs. 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/009/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/009/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘अबोधि जारः&amp;rsquo; इति षड़ृचं नवमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाग्नेयम् । “अबोधि षट् &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोर्दशसूक्तमध्ये उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;9 (525)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The appearance of Agni as the fire of the morning sacrifice and also as the sun  marks the beginning of the sacrifice, and it is he who establishes the two signs of  the sacrifice: the oblations given to the gods and the wealth received in return by  humans (vs. 1). The exchange between sacrificers and gods is reasserted at the end  of the penultimate verse (vs. 5cd), which urges Agni to sacrifice to the gods in order  that they will benefit humans. The theme of exchange is continued in verse 2a, since894 VII.9&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni’s “strong resolve” is to sacrifice, and as a result of this resolve he opens the  pens of the Paṇis and, as in the Vala story, lets loose cattle, symbols of both wealth  and the dawns. In the latter part of this verse the function of Agni in promoting  the exchange between gods and sacrificers is suggested by word play that turns on  the ambiguity of arká, which can mean either “chant” or “flame,” and of the com&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pound purubhójas, either “bringing sustenance” or “consuming sustenance.” That  is, Agni purifies either the chant that creates food for humans or the flames that  consume it on behalf of the gods.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In 3ab, in a different kind of word play, Agni bears the names of three gods, all  of whom, like Agni, have roles in carrying out the ritual: Aditi is the embodiment of  the “Guiltlessness” of one who performs the rite correctly, Vivasvant is the first sac rificer (as Geldner notes), and Mitra is the deity of the sacrificial alliance between  gods and humans. The name Vivasvant may also carry its appellative significance  “shining forth,” which would also fit the fire. In 3cd Agni is brought into connection  with two groups of goddesses, who are complicit in the birth of Agni: the Dawns,  with whom he appears in the early morning, and the Waters, who give birth to Agni  and place him in the “fruitful” plants, from which the fire emerges. There is a final  word play in verse 6c, where puruṇīthā́&amp;hellip;jarasva can mean that, as a god, Agni  should awaken to the musical modes of the ritual chants or, as a priest, should sing  musical modes through the sounds of the fire. There is even battle imagery in the  latter part of the hymn: in verse 4 Agni enters the “melee” and in verse 5 with Agni’s  help Vasiṣṭha destroys the Jarūtha, probably a demonized enemy who is part of the  Vasiṣṭha family lore. In that context, puruṇīthā́ could also have a secondary refer ence to warriors’ strategems by which wealth is won.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/010/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘उषो न जारः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं दशमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाग्नेयम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्’ उषो न पञ्च&amp;rsquo; इति । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोरुक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;10 (526)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poet is particularly fond of alliteration and assonance, which he uses exten sively in the hymn. The first words of the first verse uṣó ná jāráḥ echo its last  uśatī́r ajīgaḥ, and throughout the verse the poet pairs initial sounds: pr̥thú pā́jaḥ,  dávidyutad dī́dyat, and bhāti bhāṣā́, in what may be a sonic representation of the  flickering fire repeatedly flaming. In verses 2 and 3 he strings sets of three repeti tions: dravád dūtó devayā́vā (2d) and susaṃdŕ̥śaṃ suprátīkaṃ sváñcam (3c). He then  returns to pairs in verse 4: rudráṃ rudrébhiḥ, ādityébhir áditim. These repetitions  abruptly stop at the last verse, which states matter-of-factly the principal theme of  the hymn first enunciated at verse 2: Agni brings offerings to the gods in heaven and  wealth to mortals on earth. There is a variation on this theme in verse 4, in which  Agni not only conveys oblations to the gods (as in vs. 3), but also conveys the gods  to earth at the sacrificial place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०११</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/011/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ महाँ असि&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चमेकादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाग्नेयम् । ‘महान्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोरुक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;11 (527)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The keywords in this hymn are ā́ “hither” and ihá “here.” The poet asks that Agni  come “hither” (vs. 1c) to sacrifice “here” (vss. 1d, 3c). And not only should Agni  come, but he should also bring the gods “hither” (vs. 5a) to enjoy the sacrifice  “here” (vs. 5b). The last pāda—excluding the Vasiṣṭha signature pāda—presents an  interesting twist, for the poet asks that this sacrifice, the sacrifice that is at this place  on earth, that is here where he has asked Agni to come and here where he is to bring  the gods, be placed “in heaven among the gods” (vs. 5c). At the end, therefore, what  is present and local should become celestial and divine.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 3 of this hymn presents an additional puzzle. What does it mean when  it says that good things become visible in Agni “three times at night”? Following  Sāyaṇa, Geldner argues that “night” here means the whole day, and therefore the  reference is to the three soma-pressings. Recognizing the difficulty of this interpre&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tation, Oldenberg wonders whether there might be a reference here to an Atirātra or  “overnight” rite. We agree and think that the reference here is to the rites that take  place at night. But what rites these are or why “good things” are visible in the fire  during them remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/012/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/012/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘अगन्म महा&amp;rsquo; इति तृचात्मकं द्वादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाग्नेयम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम् &amp;ndash; ’ अगन्म तृचम्&amp;rsquo; इति । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोरुक्तो विनियोगः । व्यूळ्हे दशरात्रे नवमेऽहनीदं सूक्तमाज्यशस्त्रम् । सूत्रितं च - तृतीयस्यागन्म महेत्याज्यम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ११) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;12 (528)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This brief hymn describes Agni’s appearance “in his own home” (vs. 1b) and “in the  household” (vs. 2b), but although he is a domestic fire, Agni also extends to heaven  and earth and the four directions (vs. 1cd). Agni’s principal function here is to pro tect the household against unnamed difficulties (vss. 2a, 2c) and accusations (vs. 2c).  It is because he protects the family that he is Varuṇa and Mitra (vs. 3a), since these  two gods guard the structure of the household and of the larger society.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/013/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्राग्नये&amp;rsquo; इति तृचं त्रयोदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वैश्वानराग्निदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं &amp;ndash; ’ प्राग्नये वैश्वानरीयम्&amp;rsquo; इति । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;13 (529)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni Vaiśvānara&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In each of the three verses of this hymn, the poet calls Agni vaíśvānara (vss. 1d, 2d,  3c), thereby identifying the emerging ritual fire with the rising sun. Because Agni is  the sun, he blazes everywhere, smashes enemies, fills heaven and earth with his light,  releases the gods from the curse (of darkness), looks upon all beings, and encom&lt;br&gt;&#xA;passes the earth. The poet brings to Agni his hymn as an offering in the hope that  with these powers Agni will bring success to the poet’s words.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/014/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘समिधा जातवेदसे&amp;rsquo; इति तृचं चतुर्दशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षमाग्नेयम् । आद्या बृहती द्वितीयातृतीये त्रिष्टुभौ । तथा चानुक्रम्यते - ‘समिधा बृहत्यादि&amp;rsquo; इति । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;14 (530)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3 verses: br̥hatī 1, triṣṭubh 2, 3&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn marks the raising of the sacrificial fire by placing kindling, by pouring  ghee, and by reciting praises and invocations, which verbal products, as much as  the wood and ghee, bring the fire to life. Noteworthy in this hymn is the repetition  of an emphatic vayám “we” at the beginning of each pāda in verse 2, continuing its  placement in 1d. The poet is drawing the god’s attention not only to the forms of  ritual service he is being offered, but also to the poet and his people as those offer&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ing that service.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/015/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ उपसद्याय&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चदशर्चं पञ्चदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं गायत्रमाग्नेयम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्&amp;ndash; ’ उपसद्याय पञ्चोना गायत्रम्&amp;rsquo; इति । प्रातरनुवाक आग्नेये क्रतौ गायत्रे छन्दस्याश्विनशस्त्रे चेदं सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च - उपसद्याय त्वमग्ने यज्ञानामिति तिस्र उत्तमा उद्धरेत्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ४.१३) इति ।&#xA;उपसदि पौर्वाह्णिक्याम् ‘उपसद्याय&amp;rsquo; इत्याद्यास्तिस्र ऋचः सामिधेन्यः। सूत्र्यते च -उपसद्याय मीळ्हुष इति तिस्र एकैकां त्रिरनवानम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ४. ८) इति । पवित्रेष्ट्याम् &amp;rsquo; अग्नी रक्षांसि&amp;rsquo; इत्येषा प्रथमाज्यभागानुवाक्या । सूत्रितं च&amp;ndash;’ पावकवन्तावाज्यभागावग्नी रक्षांसि सेधति&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. २.१२) इति । अन्वारम्भणीयायामग्नेर्भगिनो याज्या । सूत्रितं च- आ सवं सवितुर्यथा स नो राधांस्या भर&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. २. ८) इति । स्वस्त्ययन्यामिष्टौ ‘अग्ने रक्षा णः&amp;rsquo; इति प्रथमाज्यभागानुवाक्या । सूत्रितं च - ‘स्वस्त्ययन्यां रक्षितवन्तावग्ने रक्षा णो अंहसः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. २.१०) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/016/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;द्वितीयेऽनुवाके षोडश सूक्तानि । तत्र ‘त्वे ह यत्पितरः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चविंशत्यृचं प्रथमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमिन्द्रदेवताकम् । द्वाविंशादिभिश्चतसृभिः सुदासनाम्नो राज्ञो दानं स्तूयते । अतस्तास्तदेवताकाः । अनुक्रम्यते हि - त्वे ह यत्पञ्चाधिकैन्द्रं सुदासः पैजवनस्य चतस्रोऽन्त्याः दानस्तुतिः&amp;rsquo; इति । महाव्रत आदितः पञ्चदशर्चः शंसनीयाः। तथैव पञ्चमारण्यके सूत्रितं -’ त्वे ह यत्पितरश्चिन्न इन्द्रेति पञ्चदश&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५. २. २) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;16 (532)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;12 verses: br̥hatī alternating with satobr̥hatī, arranged in pragāthas&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn emphasizes the exchange mediated by Agni, who takes the oblations to  the gods (or brings the gods to the oblations) and who offers sustenance to the sac rificers (see esp. vs. 2cd). Because he thus nourishes both gods and humans, he is the  “child of nourishment” (vs. 1). The poet repeatedly mentions the patron or patrons  of the rite alongside the priests. Agni himself is not only the Hotar, who recites, and  the Potar, who purifies the soma, but also the householder, who is the patron of the  rite (vs. 5). In verse 6 the poet calls on Agni to sharpen not only the priests but also  the one who “praises well” and “is skillful,” a combination of the ability to recite  and the ability to perform the rites. The latter may be a priest, but it might be again  the householder, who is also a participant in the rite and who owns, in a sense, all of  the priestly functions. In verses 7–10 the poet asks Agni to bless generous patrons, who give cattle (vs. 7) and horses along with other gifts (vs. 10). In the final two  verses the poet addresses his fellow priests, urging them to prepare ample offerings  for the gods, but at the end he especially mentions the rewards of wealth and good  men for “the pious man,” who again is likely the householder.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/017/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;अग्ने भव सुषमिधा&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं सप्तदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षमग्निदेवताकम् । सप्तापि द्विपदास्त्रिष्टुभः । तथैवानुक्रम्यते&amp;ndash;&amp;lsquo;अग्ने भव सप्त द्वैपदं त्रैष्टुभम् &amp;rsquo; इति । अतिरात्रे षष्ठेऽहनि तृतीयसवने मैत्रावरुणशस्त्रे &amp;lsquo;अग्ने भव&amp;rsquo; इति तृचोऽनुरूपः । सूत्र्यते हि - &amp;lsquo;अग्ने त्वं नोऽअन्तमोऽग्ने भव सुषमिधा समिद्ध इति स्तोत्रियानुरूपौ&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. २) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;17 (533)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: dvipadā triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Quite reasonably, Oldenberg holds that this hymn, the last of the Agni hymns of  VII, is an addition to the original collection. It is a general description of the prepa rations for the sacrifice (vss. 1, 2), its performance (vss. 3, 4), and its rewards (vs.  5). The last two verses reaffirm the relationship of Agni to the gods (vs. 6) and to  mortals (vs. 7).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/018/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;द्वितीयेऽनुवाके षोडश सूक्तानि । तत्र ‘त्वे ह यत्पितरः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चविंशत्यृचं प्रथमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमिन्द्रदेवताकम् । द्वाविंशादिभिश्चतसृभिः सुदासनाम्नो राज्ञो दानं स्तूयते । अतस्तास्तदेवताकाः । अनुक्रम्यते हि - त्वे ह यत्पञ्चाधिकैन्द्रं सुदासः पैजवनस्य चतस्रोऽन्त्या दानस्तुतिः इति । महाव्रत आदितः पञ्चदशर्चः शंसनीयाः। तथैव पञ्चमारण्यके सूत्रितं - ’ त्वे ह यात्पितरश्चिन्न इन्द्रेति पञ्चदश&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५. २. २) इति ॥ ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;18 (534)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Battle of the Ten Kings: Indra (1–21), Sudās&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Paijavana’s Dānastuti (22–25)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;25 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This very famous hymn, the first in Vasiṣṭha’s Indra cycle, relates, if we can use so  positive a term, the so-called Battle of the Ten Kings, in which King Sudās and his  Bharata followers, with Indra on their side, defeat an alliance of ten kings, which includes their former allies, the Pūrus. The hymn has long been used as a major  source for the reconstruction of R̥gvedic history, perhaps somewhat too credu lously, as the description of the battle is anything but clear and is also clearly full  of puns, derisive word plays, phonological deformations of the names of oppo nents, and other poetic tricks, all couched in slangy language. Since the “historical”  dimension of the hymn has been fully treated elsewhere (see especially Schmidt  1980 and Witzel 1995a), we will not discuss it further here.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn falls into three parts. Verses 1–4 recall the aid that Indra has given us  in the past and ask for his help and gifts now. The poet names himself at the very  end of verse 4, which forms a clever ring with verse 1: the description of Indra in  1d, &amp;hellip; vásu&amp;hellip; vániṣṭhaḥ “best gainer of goods,” is condensed into the poet’s own  name in 4d, vás(u)(ván)iṣṭhaḥ → vásiṣṭhaḥ. The language and contents of these first  four verses are well-crafted but unremarkable.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The battle proper and its immediate aftermath occupy verses 5–21; the battle  itself takes place in and around the Paruṣṇī River (see esp. vss. 8–10), whose course  seems to have been diverted during the battle and in which a number of the com batants seem to have drowned. The account, especially the earlier verses, seems to  mirror the confusion and chaos of battle itself (reminiscent on a much smaller scale  of Tolstoy’s great accounts of the unintelligible disorder of battle in War and Peace,  or of Stephen Crane’s in The Red Badge of Courage). The confusion begins to sort  itself out as Indra’s role becomes more prominently featured. It is emphasized sev eral times that the forces of Sudās were outnumbered but that Indra was able to  marshal this overmastered force to defeat their foes (esp. vss. 14, 17). This section  ends with several verses celebrating the victory and Indra’s benevolence (20–21).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The final four verses (22–25) are a dānastuti, praising the extravagant gifts of  Sudās to the poet, ending (vs. 25) by commending Sudās to the protection of the  Maruts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/019/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘यस्तिग्मशृङ्गः&amp;rsquo; इत्येकादशर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं’ यस्तिग्मशृङ्ग एकादश&amp;rsquo; इति । आभिप्लविके पञ्चमेऽहन्येतन्निविद्धानम् । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash;‘कया शुभा यस्तिग्मशृङ्ग इति मध्यंदिनः &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ७ ) इति । विषुवति निष्केवल्यशस्त्रेऽप्येतत्सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च&amp;ndash;’ यस्तिग्मशृङ्गोऽभि त्यं मेषम् &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ६) इति । महाव्रते निष्केवल्येऽप्येतत् सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च-’ यस्तिग्मशृङ्गो वृषभो न भीम उग्रो जज्ञे वीर्याय स्वधावान्&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५. २. २ ) इति । आयुष्कामेष्ट्यां ‘मा ते अस्याम्&amp;rsquo; इतीन्द्रस्य त्रातुर्याज्या । सूत्रितं च – &amp;rsquo; मा ते अस्यां सहसावन्परिष्टौ पाहि नो अग्ने पायुभिः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. २. १०) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/020/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथ तृतीयोऽध्याय आरभ्यते । “उग्रो जज्ञे&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते- उग्रो दश&amp;rsquo; इति । आभिप्लविके चतुर्थेऽहनि निष्केवल्य एतत्सूक्तं निविद्धानम् । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; चतुर्थस्योग्रो जज्ञ इति निष्केवल्यम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ७ ) इति । महाव्रतेऽपि निष्केवल्य एतत्सूक्तम् । तथैव पञ्चमारण्यके सूत्रितम्- उग्रो जज्ञे वीर्याय स्वधावानुदु ब्रह्माण्यैरत श्रवस्या&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५. २. २.) इति । सौमिकचातुर्मास्येषु वैश्वदेवस्य स्थाने प्रथमं पृष्ठ्यमहः । तत्रापि निष्केवल्य एतत्सूक्तं निविद्धानम्। सूत्रितं च - ‘जनिष्ठा उग्र उग्रो जज्ञ इति मध्यंदिनः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ९:२) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/021/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘असावि देवम्&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं चतुर्थं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम् &amp;ndash; ‘असावि &amp;rsquo; इति । माध्यंदिनसवने मैत्रावरुणस्योन्नीयमानमिदं सूक्तम् । ‘असावि देवमिहोप यातेत्यनुसवनम् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ५.५) इति । इन्द्रस्य वृत्रघ्नः पशौ अभिक्रत्वा&amp;rsquo; इति वपाया अनुवाक्या । सूत्रितं च - ‘अभि क्रत्वेन्द्र भूरध ज्मंस्त्वं महाँ इन्द्र तुभ्यं ह क्षाः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ३.८) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;21 (537)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins with two verses establishing the sacrificial context, the second of  which describes the pressing stones as enthusiastic participants in the ritual. The  remaining verses celebrate Indra’s deeds and powers and beg him to display these  powers for our benefit. Verses 3 and 4 treat previous deeds, verses 6–7 primarily his  incomparable power.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The most striking verse is 5, the middle verse (vs. 10 being a refrain and thus  extra-hymnic). Here various threats to the “truth” of our people are rendered help less by our resistance and Indra’s power: threats internal to the community, namely  sorcerers and flatterers, and the “stranger” (an Ārya but an enemy), people who  deviate from our ways, and phallus-worshipers (presumably non-Āryas) outside it.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The final two verses before the refrain (8–9) recognize Indra’s help in the past  and request it for the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/022/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ पिबा सोममिन्द्र मन्दतु त्वा&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं पञ्चमं सूक्तम् । अनुक्रम्यते च &amp;ndash; पिब नव वैराजमृतेऽन्त्याम्&amp;rsquo; इति । वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । आदितोऽष्टौ विराजो नवमी त्रिष्ट्रप् । इन्द्रो देवता । दशरात्रे चतुर्थेऽहनि निष्केवल्यशस्त्रे ‘ पिबा सोममिन्द्र&amp;rsquo; इति षट् स्तोत्रियानुरूपौ । सूत्रितं च&amp;ndash; ’ वैराजं चेत्पृष्ठं पिबा सोममिन्द्र मन्दतु त्वेति षट् स्तोत्रियानुरूपौ&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ११) इति । महाव्रतेऽपि निष्केवल्य आद्याः षडृचः । सूत्रितं च&amp;ndash;’ पिबा सोममिन्द्र मन्दतु त्वेति षट्&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५. ३. १ ) इति । आद्या निष्केवल्यशस्त्रयाज्या । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; पिबा सोममिन्द्र मन्दतु त्वेति याज्या&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ५. १५) इति । चतुर्थेऽहनि माध्यंदिनसवने होत्रकशस्त्रेषु सप्त विराजस्त्रींस्तृचान् कृत्वैकैकस्तृचः शंसनीयः । तत्र  ‘न ते गिरः&amp;rsquo; इत्याद्याश्चतस्र ऋचः । सूत्रितं च -’ न ते गिरो अपि मृष्ये तुरस्य प्र वो महे महिवृधे भरध्वम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ११) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/023/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;उदु ब्रह्माणि&amp;rsquo; इति षड़ृचं षष्ठं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । अनुक्रम्यते च– ‘उदु षट्&amp;rsquo; इति । अग्निष्टोमे माध्यंदिने सवने ब्राह्मणाच्छंसिशस्त्र एतत्सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च - ‘उदु ब्रह्माण्यृजीषी वज्री वृषभस्तुराषाळिति याज्या &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ५. १६) इति । चातुर्विंशिकेऽहनि माध्यंदिनसवने ब्राह्मणाच्छंसिशस्त्र एतदहरहःशस्यसंज्ञकं सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च - ‘उदु ब्रह्माण्यभि तष्टेवेतीतरावहरहःशस्ये &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ४ ) इति । अहर्गणेषु द्वितीयादिष्वहःसु एतदेव सूक्तम्। महाव्रतेऽपि निष्केवल्य एतत्सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च- ‘उदु ब्रह्माण्यैरत श्रवस्या ते मह इन्द्रोत्युग्रेति पञ्च सूक्तानि (ऐ. आ. ५. २. २) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/024/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘योनिष्ट इन्द्र सदने अकारि &amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं सप्तमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । अनुक्रम्यते च-’ योनिः&amp;rsquo; इति । महाव्रते निष्केवल्य एतत्सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च - ’ योनिष्ट इन्द्र सदने अकारीत्येतस्य चतस्रः शस्त्वोत्तमामुपसंतत्योपोत्तमया परिदधाति&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५. ३. १) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;24 (540)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Entirely an invitation to the sacrifice, this hymn conforms to the “journey” model,  with repeated exhortations to Indra to “drive here,” declarations that the sacrifice  has been prepared, and, especially in the final verse (6), hopes for reciprocal benefits  given by a satisfied Indra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/025/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ ते मह इन्द्र&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचमष्टमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । ‘आ ते&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । महाव्रते निष्केवल्य इदमादीनि पञ्च सूक्तानि । सूत्रितं च-’ आ ते मह इन्द्रोत्युग्रेति पञ्च सूक्तानि (ऐ. आ. ५. २. २) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;25 (541)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;King Sudās, the leader in the Battle of the Ten Kings (VII.18), appears here in verse  3, and the context is once again that of war and hostility. In sometimes vivid lan guage we beg Indra to support our side in the conflict and to destroy our enemies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/026/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ न सोम इन्द्रम्&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं नवमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते&amp;ndash; ’ न सोमः पञ्च&amp;rsquo; इति । महाव्रत उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;26 (542)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This brief hymn displays several competing yet complementary types of structure.  On the one hand, the first two verses respond to each other and establish pressed  soma and hymns as the linked indispensible requisites of the sacrifice to Indra; the  doubly negative formulation of the first half of verse 1 is especially striking. The  last two verses (4–5) also respond to each other, each beginning with evā́ “in just  this way.” These two pairs of verses highlight the excluded verse 3, the middle verse,  as an omphalos, and this verse does contrast with the rest of the hymn in several  ways. It is the only place where Indra’s deeds are spoken of, and it also contains  in its second half a striking simile (the only simile describing Indra in the hymn),  in which the submission of fortresses to Indra is compared to the submission of  cowives to their common husband. Thus verse 3 is in a sense a miniature example of  proper praise-poetry, celebrating a god’s mythic exploits in artful language.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A different structural feature pairs verse 1 with the final verse 5, in opposition  to the three middle verses (2–4). In the first verse the speaker is “I”; in the last (vs.  5) it is Vasiṣṭha, who is doubtless identical with the “I” of verse&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/027/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/027/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/027/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘इन्द्रं नरः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं दशमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । ‘इन्द्रं नरः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । महाव्रते निष्केवल्य एतत्सूक्तमुक्तं तृतीयत्वेन । ऐन्द्रे पशौ वपापुरोडाशहविषामाद्यास्तिस्रः क्रमेणानुवाक्याः । सूत्रितं च– इन्द्रं नरो नेमधिता हवन्त इत्युरुं नो लोकमनु नेषि विद्वान्&amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ३. ७) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;27 (543)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is much preoccupied with receiving material goods from Indra. The  words “bounty,” “bounteous,” “largesse,” and so forth are prominent. What would  prompt his giving, namely our praise and sacrifice, is barely, but significantly, men tioned: the first verse opens with the martial context that is common throughout  these Indra hymns in the VIIth Maṇḍala, with men in battle position. In our inter pretation of pāda b, Indra is expected to harness the praise hymns directed to him  by the poets of our side “to be decisive”—that is, the hymns will ensure that Indra  will fight on our side and bring us victory. This concern to have Indra on our side in  battle is echoed in verse 4 with the “coincident call.” This call can refer both to war riors on opposing sides each calling Indra to fight on their own side, as in verse 1,  and also to rival sacrificers each calling Indra to come to their sacrifice, as we have  seen elsewhere in this Indra cycle.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Another important theme in the hymn is confinement, with subtle allusion to the  Vala myth. We ask for a share of the cattle enclosure in 1d and in 2d exhort Indra  to break apart the firmly closed fortresses and uncover what is enclosed there; the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/028/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/028/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/028/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ ब्रह्मा ण इन्द्र&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चमेकादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम्। ब्रह्मा णः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । महाव्रते निष्केवल्ये पञ्चमत्वेनास्य सूक्तस्य विनियोग उक्तः । अष्टमेऽहनि प्रउगशस्त्र आद्यस्तृच ऐन्द्रः ( आश्व. श्रौ. ८. १०)॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;28 (544)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Another hymn in this series concerned with competition between sacrificers. The  first verse exhorts Indra to heed only our call, though others are calling, too, and in  the second verse the phrase “penetrate through” seems to refer to Indra’s ability to  ignore the competitive calls in order to come to ours. The second half of verse 2 and  verse 3 then turn to Indra’s great deeds, but this section is connected to the first by a  word play. Although it cannot be rendered easily in English, both the “vie in invok&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ing” of verse 1 and the “penetrate through” in verse 2 contain the preverb ví “apart,  through,” which is in regular opposition to sám “together.” In verse 3 it is said that  Indra “united” the two world-halves, using a verb phrase including the preverb  sám (literally “lead together”). But the cosmogonic deed that is regularly credited  to Indra is rather the separation or pushing apart of the same two world-halves  (for a nearby example see VII.23.3); we contend that here this underlying formula is evoked by its opposite—the audience, familiar with the verbal formulae encap sulating Indra’s great deeds, would understand “lead together [sám]” as “lead apart [ví],” primed by the ví forms found earlier in the hymn. For another example of an  underlying formula appearing on the surface as its opposite, see Jamison (1982/83).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 4 is notable because of the intrusion of Varuṇa into this Indra hymn,  and Varuṇa in his role as observer and judge of the moral behavior of humans.  Varuṇa is the tutelary deity of Vasiṣṭha (see the remarkable series of Varuṇa hymns,  VII.86–89 below), but Varuṇa’s presence is otherwise not found, or expected, in  Indraic context. Since the last verse (5) is a refrain verse, in this Indra hymn Varuṇa  has the last word, as it were. For Mitra and Varuṇa’s parentage of Vasiṣṭha, see  VII.33.10–14.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/029/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/029/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/029/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अयं सोम इन्द्र&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं द्वादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । अयं सोमः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । व्यूळ्हे दशरात्रे नवमेऽहनि ‘अयं सोम इन्द्र&amp;rsquo; इति प्रउगशस्त्र ऐन्द्रस्तृचः । सूत्रितं च- अयं सोम इन्द्र तुभ्यं सुन्व आ तु प्र ब्रह्माणः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ११ ) इति । षोडशिशस्त्रे ‘ ब्रह्मन्वीर&amp;rsquo; इत्येषा त्रिष्टुप् । सूत्रितं च- ’ ब्रह्मन्वीर ब्रह्मकृतिं जुषाण इति त्रिष्टुप् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ६. २) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/030/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/030/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/030/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ आ नो देव&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं त्रयोदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रम् । ‘आ नो देव&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । प्रथमे छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्रे ‘आ नः&amp;rsquo; इत्ययमैन्द्रस्तृचः । सूत्र्यते हि-’ आ नो देव शवसा याहि शुष्मिन् प्र वो यज्ञेषु देवयन्तो अर्चन्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ९) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;30 (546)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Again this hymn expresses a martial and competitive spirit, especially in verse  2. Also, as in VII.28, another god is introduced into an Indra hymn, this time Agni  (vs. 3), rather than Varuṇa (VII.28.4). The combination of Agni and the dawns sug gests a dawn sacrifice, and the praise of patrons in verse 4 must refer to the distribu tion of the dakṣiṇā or priestly gift by patrons to priests and poets at that ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/031/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/031/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/031/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र व इन्द्राय&amp;rsquo; इति द्वादशर्चं चतुर्दशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं गायत्रमैन्द्रम् । दशम्याद्यास्तिस्रो विराजः शिष्टा गायत्र्यः । तथा चानुक्रान्तं - ’ प्र वो द्वादश गायत्रं त्रिविराळन्तम्&amp;rsquo; इति । सूक्तविनियोगो लैङ्गिकः । प्रथमे रात्रिपर्याये मैत्रावरुणशस्त्रे ‘प्र व इन्द्राय&amp;rsquo; इत्याद्यस्तृचः स्तोत्रियः । सूत्रितं च - ‘प्र व इन्द्राय मादनं प्र कृतान्यृजीषिणः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ६. ४) इति । अतिरात्रे प्रथमे पर्याये ब्राह्मणाच्छंसिशस्त्रे वयमिन्द्र वायवोऽभि&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुरूपस्तृचः । तथा च सूत्रितं - ’ वयमिन्द्र त्वायवोऽभि वार्त्रहत्यायेत्युत्तमामुद्धरेत्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ६. ४) इति । चतुर्थेऽहनि माध्यदिनसवने होत्रकशस्त्र आरम्भणीयाभ्य ऊर्ध्वं वैराज एकस्तृच आहवनीयः। तदर्थाः ‘प्र वो महे महिवृधे भरध्वम्&amp;rsquo; इत्याद्यास्तिस्रः । सूत्रितं च - &amp;rsquo; प्र वो महे महिवृधे भरध्वमिति चतस्रस्तिस्रश्च विराजः । (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ११) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/032/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/032/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/032/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘मो षु त्वा&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तविंशत्यृचं पञ्चदशं सूक्तम् । अत्रेयमनुक्रमणिका - मो षु सप्ताधिका प्रागाथं तृतीया द्विपदा सौदासैरग्नौ प्रक्षिप्यमाणः शक्तिरन्त्यं प्रगाथमालेभे सोऽर्धर्चं उक्तेऽदह्यत । तं पुत्रोक्तं वसिष्ठः समापयतेति शाट्यायनकं वसिष्ठस्यैव हतपुत्रस्यार्षमिति ताण्डकम्&amp;rsquo; इति । मण्डलद्रष्टा वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । इन्द्र क्रतुं नः&amp;rsquo; इति प्रगाथस्यार्धर्चस्य च वसिष्ठपुत्रः शक्तिर्वसिष्ठो वा । इन्द्रो देवता । अयुजो बृहत्यो युजः सतोबृहत्यः । तृतीया तु द्विपदा विराट्। महाव्रते निष्केवल्ये बार्हततृचाशीतावेतत्सूक्तम् । तत्र द्विपदाम् &amp;rsquo; अभि त्वा शूर&amp;rsquo; इत्येतं रथन्तरं प्रगाथं ‘नकिः सुदासः&amp;rsquo; इति प्रगाथं च वर्जयेत् । तथैव पञ्चमारण्यके सूत्रितं- मो षु त्वा वाघतश्चनेत्येतस्य द्विपदां चोद्धरति राथन्तरं च प्रगाथमथ हास्य नकिः सुदासो रथमित्येतं प्रगाथमुद्धृत्य त्वामिदा ह्यो नर इत्येतं प्रगाथं प्रत्यवदधाति&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५, २. ४ ) इति । चातुर्विशिकेऽहनि पञ्चमेऽहनि च निष्केवल्ये ‘मो षु त्वा वाघतः&amp;rsquo; इति प्रगाथः सद्विपदः । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; मो षु त्वा वाघतश्चनेति सद्विपद उपसमस्येद्द्विपदाम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ३) इति । चातुर्विंशिकेऽहनि मरुत्वतीये प्राकृतात् मरुत्वतीयात् प्रगाथादनन्तरं ‘ नकिः सुदासः&amp;rsquo; इति प्रगाथं शंसेत् । पृष्ठ्याभिप्लवषडहयोः तृतीये षष्ठेऽहनि चायं प्रगाथः । तथैव सूत्रितं &amp;ndash; नकिः सुदासो रथमिति मरुस्वतीया ऊर्ध्वं नित्यात्&amp;rsquo; इति । एवं स्थितान् प्रगाथान् पृष्ठ्याभिप्लवयोरन्वहं पुनःपुनरावर्तयेयुः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ३) इति । अग्निष्टोमे माध्यंदिनसवनेऽच्छावाकशस्त्रे ‘उदिन्न्वस्य रिच्यते &amp;rsquo; इति प्रगाथः। तथा च सूत्रितम्- उदिन्न्वस्य रिच्यते भूय इत्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ५. १६) इति । अग्निष्टोमे माध्यंदिनसवने मैत्रावरुणशस्त्रे ‘ कस्तमिन्द्र&amp;rsquo; इति प्रगाथः । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash; कस्तमिन्द्र त्वावसुं सद्यो ह जातः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ५. १६ ) इति । चातुर्विंशिकेऽहनि माध्यंदिनसवने मैत्रावरुणशस्त्रस्यायं प्रगाथः । अहर्गणेष्वपि द्वितीयादिष्वहःसु । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash; कस्तमिन्द्र त्वावसुं कन्नव्यो अतसीनाम् ( आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ४ ) इति । ‘ आरम्भणीयाः पर्यासान् कद्वतोऽहरहःशस्यानीति होत्रकाः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. १) इति । पृष्ठयषडहस्य तृतीयेऽहनि निष्केवल्ये वैरूपसामपक्षे ‘ यदिन्द्र यावतः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुरूपस्तृचः । सूत्रितं च -’ यदिन्द्र यावतस्त्वमिति प्रगाथौ स्तोत्रियानुरूपौ&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. १०) इति । अग्निष्टोमे चातुर्विंशिकेऽहनि माध्यंदिनसवनेऽच्छावाकशस्त्रे ‘तरणिरित्सिषासति&amp;rsquo; इति वैकल्पिकस्तृचः । सूत्रितं च तरोभिर्वो विदद्वसुं तरणिरित्सिषासति&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ४) इति । अग्निष्टोमे निष्केवल्यशस्त्रे रथन्तरसामपक्षे &amp;rsquo; अभि त्वा शूर&amp;rsquo; इति प्रगाथः स्तोत्रियः । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash; अभि त्वा शूर नोनुमोऽभि त्वा पूर्वपीतय इति प्रगाथौ स्तोत्रियानुरूपौ&amp;rsquo; (आश्व, श्रौ. ५. १५) इति । आश्विनशस्त्रेऽप्ययं प्रगाथः । तथैव सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; अभि त्वा शूर नोनुमो बहवः सूरचक्षस इति प्रगाथाः (आश्व. श्रौ. ६.५) इति। महाव्रते निष्केवल्ये दक्षिणपक्षेऽयं प्रगाथः । तथैव पञ्चमारण्यके सूत्रितम्-&amp;rsquo; अभि त्वा शूर नोनुमोऽभि त्वा पूर्वपीतय इति रथन्तरस्य स्तोत्रियानुरूपौ प्रगाथौ&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५. २. २) इति । आश्विनशस्त्रे ‘इन्द्र क्रतुं नः । इति प्रगाथः । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash; इन्द्र क्रतुं न आ भराभि त्वा शूर नोनुमः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ६. ५) इति । चातुर्विंशिकेऽहनि माध्यंदिनसवने ब्राह्मणाच्छंसिशस्त्रेऽयं वैकल्पिकः स्तोत्रियः प्रगाथः । सूत्रितं च - इन्द्र क्रतुं न आ भरेन्द्र ज्येष्ठं न आ भर&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ४) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/033/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/033/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/033/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘श्वित्यञ्चः &amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्दशर्चं षोडशं सूक्तम् । अत्रेयमनुक्रमणिका&amp;mdash; श्वित्यञ्चः षळूना संस्तवो वसिष्ठस्य सपुत्रस्येन्द्रेण वा संवादः&amp;rsquo; इति । आदितो नवानां वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । वसिष्ठपुत्राणां स्तूयमानत्वात्त एव देवता । “विद्युतो ज्योतिः&amp;rsquo; इत्यादिभिर्दशम्यादिभिः स्वपुत्रैर्वसिष्ठः स्तूयते । अतो वसिष्ठो देवता । त एव ऋषयः । ‘ या तेनोच्यते&amp;rsquo; इति न्यायात् । अनुक्तत्वात् त्रिष्टुप् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;33 (549)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasisṭha’s Sons (1–9); Vasis ̣ ṭha (10–14) ̣&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi (1–9), Vasiṣṭha’s sons (10–14)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;14 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This famous hymn, coming at the very end of the Vasiṣṭha Indra cycle, treats the  mystical birth of Vasiṣṭha and the accomplishments of Vasiṣṭha and his descen dants, particularly the feat of attracting Indra to the side of King Sudās and ensur ing Indra’s support in the Battle of the Ten Kings, the battle treated at length  in VII.18. The Anukramaṇī identifies the poet of verses 1–9 as Vasiṣṭha and the  “deity” as Vasiṣṭha’s sons, with the opposite identifications for verses 10–14, but this  does not seem the most perspicuous assignment of roles. Rather, it seems that the  hymn falls into three parts: 1–6, 7–9, 10–14, starting with a time close to the (semi mythical) present and moving backward to the deep mythical past.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first six verses celebrate the Vasiṣṭhas’ successful invitation of Indra to their  soma sacrifice and Indra’s subsequent aid to Sudās and the Tr̥tsus in the Ten Kings  battle. Indra himself appears to be the speaker in verses 1 and 4. The first two verses  depict one of the themes running through this set of Indra hymns: competing sacri&lt;br&gt;&#xA;fices. Here, Indra seems actually to rise from his seat at another sacrifice to go to the  Vasiṣṭhas in verse 1, with his journey described in verse 2. Verses 3–6 treat his aid to  Sudās in the Ten Kings battle, with all credit given to the Vasiṣṭhas’ poetic skill for  bringing this aid (vss. 3–5), and Indra himself declaring this in verse 4.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The next section begins with a trio of riddles based on the number three (vs.  7), with the last pāda of that verse asserting that it is exactly this knowledge that  the Vasiṣṭhas control—a nice meta-comment on what Vedic poets were supposed  to know. There is no consensus (modern or ancient) on the answers to these three  riddles. The three producers of semen may be the three soma-pressings, or heaven  (with its rain), soma, and man—and other answers have also been suggested. The  three Ārya “creatures” with light in front could be the three ritual fires, or the fire,  the sun, and dawn—and, again, there are other possible solutions. As for the three  “heats,” these could again be the ritual fires, or the sun, the fire, and the gharma924 VII.33&lt;br&gt;&#xA;drink, or some other triad. It is perhaps pleasing that the Vasiṣṭhas’ esoteric knowl edge has remained safe with them for over three millennia! This skill of theirs at  decoding secrets and putting them in proper verbal form is celebrated further in  verse 8 and the first half of verse 9.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The second half of verse 9 provides the transition to the last section, concern ing the birth of Vasiṣṭha. What the Vasiṣṭhas are weaving (a motif recurring almost  verbatim in vs. 12) is not entirely clear, but we are inclined to think it concerns the  institution and performance of the sacrifice. It is clear why they are approaching the  Apsarases (the heavenly “nymphs” of Vedic and later Indian culture): one of the  Apsarases’ number, Urvaśī, is their mother (see vss. 11–12), with Mitra and Varuṇa  as their father (see vss. 11, 13), in the first of their forefather Vasiṣṭha’s births. Both  births are referred to in verse 10, both that from Mitra and Varuṇa and that when  Agastya presented him to the clan. To say that the details of the births are murky  is an understatement, and we will not attempt here to interpret all the mysteries in  these verses. The last verse (14) is traditionally taken as Agastya’s words, introduc&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ing Vasiṣṭha to his adoptive clan, the Tr̥tsus, and outlining Vasiṣṭha’s ritual role.  The address to “you thrusters forth” (pratr̥daḥ) is most likely a pun on their name.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/034/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/034/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/034/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तृतीयेऽनुवाके द्वाविंशतिसूक्तानि । तत्र ‘प्र शुक्रा&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चविंशत्यृचं प्रथमं सूक्तम् । अत्रेयमनुक्रमणिका - प्र शुक्रा पञ्चाधिका वैश्वदेवं हाद्या एकविंशतिद्विपदा अब्जामहेरर्धर्च उत्तरोऽहिर्बुध्न्याय &amp;rsquo; इति । वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । आद्या एकविंशतिर्द्विपदा विंशत्यक्षरा विराजो द्वाविंशायाश्चतस्रस्त्रिष्टुभः । विश्वे देवा देवता । व्यूळ्हे दशरात्रे चतुर्थेऽहनि वैश्वदेवशस्त्र इदं सूक्तं वैश्वदेवनिविद्धानम् । सूत्रितं च - प्र शुक्रैत्विति वैश्वदेवम् &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८.८) इति । षोडशिनि ‘आ धूर्ष्वस्मा इति द्विपदा &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ६. २) इति । महाव्रतेऽप्येषा द्विपदा। तथैव पञ्चमारण्यके सूत्रितं - आ धूर्ष्वस्मा इत्येका सूददोहाः&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. आ. ५. २. २) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/035/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/035/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/035/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘शं न इन्द्राग्नी&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चदशर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तम् । अत्रेयमनुक्रमणिका- शं नः पञ्चोना शान्तिः &amp;rsquo; इति । वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । त्रिष्टुप् छन्दः । वैश्वदेवं ह &amp;rsquo; इत्युक्तत्वादिदमपि वैश्वदेवम् । महानाम्नीव्रत एतत् सूक्तं जप्यम् । तथा च सूत्रितं - भद्रं कर्णेभिः शृणुयाम देवाः शं न इन्द्राग्नी भवतामवोभिः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. १४) इति । एव&amp;hellip;.सु ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;35 (551)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;All Gods&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;15 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This fifteen-verse hymn is in competition for the most boring hymn in the R̥gveda  (a competition in which there are remarkably few entries). In the first thirteen  verses every pāda begins with the indeclinable word śám “luck, weal” in the  hardly varying formula “luck for us be X,” with X a god or gods, power, or  sacrificial element. There is generally a rationale for the groupings found in each&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/036/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/036/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/036/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथ पञ्चमाष्टके चतुर्थोऽध्याय आरभ्यते । तत्र षडनुवाकात्मकस्य वासिष्ठस्य सप्तमस्य मण्डलस्य तृतीयेऽनुवाके द्वाविंशतिसूक्तानि । तत्र ‘प्र ब्रह्म&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं पूर्ववद्वैश्वदेवम् । अनुक्रान्तं च&amp;mdash; प्र ब्रह्म नव &amp;rsquo; इति । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;36 (552)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;All Gods&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like many All God hymns, this one allots a verse each to a god or group of gods,  most named, some not named but obvious from their description, and a few  less transparently characterized. The verses whose divinities are clear are 1: Sun;  2: Mitra and Varuṇa; 5: Rudra, 6: Rivers, 7: Maruts (and their mother Pr̥śni?);  8:  Aramati, Pūṣan, and Bhaga; 9:  Maruts and Viṣṇu. For verse 3 some schol&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ars identify the Wind and Parjanya [Thunder] as the dedicands, but we assign  it instead to Soma; verse 4 may belong to both Indra and Aryaman, but we  consider aryamán here to be used as a descriptor of Indra, rather than as the  name of the third member of the Ādityan triad, since the other descriptors—&lt;br&gt;&#xA;strong resolution and confounding of the enemy’s battle fury—are characteristic  of Indra.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn can also be read as a chronological progress through a sacrifice. In  verse 1 the fire is kindled at dawn and ritual speech is uttered on the ritual ground.  The hymn is mentioned in verse 2, and the preparation of soma in verse 3. The  invitation to Indra to come to the sacrifice with his horses is given in verse 4, and  the actual sacrifice occurs in verse 5. Although the verse to the rivers (6) does not  appear to fit this pattern, it could refer to the waters used to swell the soma stalks&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/037/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/037/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/037/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ वो वाहिष्ठः &amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं चतुर्थं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वैश्वदेवम् । अनुक्रम्यते च - ‘आ वोऽष्टौ &amp;rsquo; इति । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;37 (553)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;All Gods&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Although this hymn is technically dedicated to the All Gods, it is only the R̥bhus  and Indra who feature in the hymn proper (R̥bhus esp. vss. 1–2, Indra vss. 3–7), with  Savitar addressed in the final verse (8). The association of Indra with the R̥bhus  identifies the ritual moment as the Third Pressing, which they share, and since  Savitar is often associated with the evening, his presence is also appropriate.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first four verses concern the sacrifice: the gods come, drink together, and  give gifts to the sacrificer and his patrons. In verse 4 Indra is sent home with a final  chorus. The next verses change the scene. In verses 5–6 Indra is praised for his help  in winning more territory for us, but he seems to be withholding the wealth we  expect. The most puzzling verse is 7, which has elicited various interpretations. In  our opinion, the “triple kin-bonds” refers to the three-generation model, in which a  man is situated conceptually between his father and his sons; this man is threatened  by dissolution and premature death, not only of himself but also of his sons, and he  approaches Indra for aid, since Indra himself successfully attains old age (an inter esting conceit for a “deathless” or “immortal” god). But this interpretation remains  uncertain and speculative. The first pāda of the final verse (8) forms a ring with the  first pāda of the hymn, and the topic returns to the gifts we expect and hope for.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/038/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/038/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/038/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘उदु ष्य देवः&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं पञ्चमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं सवितृदेवताकम् । सप्तम्यष्टम्यौ वाजिदेवताके। ‘भगमुग्रोऽवसे &amp;rsquo; इत्यर्धर्चो भगदेवत्यः सावित्रो वा । तथा चानुक्रमणिका - उदु ष्य सावित्रमन्त्ये वाजिन्यौ भगमिति भागो वार्धर्चः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;38 (554)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Savitar, except Savitar or Bhaga (6cd), Prizewinning  Horses (7–8)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Although the Anukramaṇī assigns most of this hymn to Savitar, with possibly a  half-verse to Bhaga and the final two verses to the Vājins (prizewinning horses), it  seems more likely to have been an All God hymn in original conception. It is found  in the middle of the All God hymns of the VIIth Maṇḍala in proper sequence as  to meter and number of verses, and, in addition to Savitar, mentions a number  of divinities, including several minor ones found also in the surrounding All God  hymns: see especially verse 5 with the Gift-Escorts (also VII.34.22, 23; 35.11; 40.6),  Ahi Budhnya (the Serpent of the Deep; also VII.34.17; 35.13), and the Shielding  Goddess(es); also VII.34.22; 40.6). The mysterious Ekadhenus (literally, “having  a single milk-cow”) are found only here. It is not unusual in an All God hymn for  a single god to predominate and others to be mentioned only in passing; compare  nearby VII.37 with its primary focus on Indra and the R̥bhus.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Savitar’s role is most prominent in the first two verses, where, as usual, he stands  up and raises his emblem, demonstrating his power to impel and compel. The group  of gods known as Vasus praises him in verse 3; Aditi and the Ādityas greet him in  verse 4; and, as already mentioned, several minor divinities are found in verse 5. As  often, the god Bhaga (“Fortune”) is invoked along with Savitar (vss. 1 and 6) as the  distributor of goods, which we seek. The last two verses (7–8) concern the “prize&lt;br&gt;&#xA;winners” (vājín). This word is frequently a descriptor of horses in competition, and  a number of scholars consider the reference here to be actual horses in the human  realm. However, the sacrificial context in these two verses is strong, and on the basis of phraseological parallels we consider the referents to be the Maruts (who are  called prizewinners in VII.36.7, while the phrase “let the Maruts of good chant be  luck for us” is found in VII.35.9).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/039/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/039/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/039/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ऊर्ध्वो अग्निः &amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं षष्ठं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वैश्वदेवम् । “ऊर्ध्वः सप्त वैश्वदेवं तु &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रमणिका । सूक्तविनियोगो लैङ्गिकः। द्वितीये छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्रे उर्ध्वो अग्निः&amp;rsquo; इति वैश्वदेवस्तृचः । सूत्रितं च - ‘ ऊर्ध्वो अग्निः सुमतिं वस्वो अश्रेदुत स्या नः सरस्वती जुषाणेति प्रउगम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. १०) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;39 (555)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;All Gods&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The organizing principle of this hymn is the ritual fire (Agni) and the dawn sacri fice over which he presides. In verse 1 the sacrifice is set in motion; the gods begin934 VII.39&lt;br&gt;&#xA;to assemble at dawn at the sacrificial ground (vss. 2–3), and Agni is exhorted to  perform the sacrifice (vs. 4) and to bring the various gods to it (vs. 5). The poet  declares his own contribution to the sacrifice and asks Agni for the appropriate  rewards (vs. 6). The final verse (7) summarizes what has gone before, in the name  of the Vasiṣṭhas.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 2b contains an impossible hapax, bī́riṭe, phonologically aberrant and mor phologically opaque. It is generally taken as “crowd, troop,” following Yāska, but,  as there is no particular etymological or contextual support for this, we have simply  declined to translate it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/040/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/040/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/040/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ओ श्रुष्टिः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं सप्तमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वैश्वदेवम्। ‘ओ श्रुष्टिः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;40 (556)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;All Gods&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The preoccupation of this hymn is the distribution of wealth, to be carried out in  orderly and fair fashion by a series of gods, starting in verse 1 with Savitar and  Bhaga (Fortune), whose involvement in the apportioning of treasures we met in  the nearby hymn VII.38. But a wide variety of gods are implicated in this giving,  as well as in providing other help (see vss. 3–4). There is little to attract particular  attention in this hymn, save for the sly admonition to Pūṣan not to be jealous of our  receiving gifts (vs. 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/041/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/041/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/041/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ प्रातरग्निम् &amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चमष्टमं सूक्तम् । अत्रानुक्रमणिका &amp;ndash; प्रातर्भागं जगत्याद्या लिङ्गोक्तदेवतान्त्योषस्या &amp;rsquo; इति । वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । आद्या जगती शिष्टास्त्रिष्टुभः। आद्याग्नीन्द्रादिदेवत्या द्वितीयाद्याः पञ्च भगदेवत्याः सप्तम्युषोदेवत्या । अत्र केचिदाहुः ‘निवेष्टुकामो रोगार्तो भगसूक्तं जपेत्सदा । निवेशं विशति क्षिप्रं रोगैश्च परिमुच्यते &amp;lsquo;( ऋग्वि. २.३०६) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;41 (557)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Bhaga, except Assorted Divinities (1) and Dawn (7)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh, except jagatī 1&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like the last hymn, this one is completely devoted to our acquisition of wealth by  distribution, but here the distribution is ascribed almost entirely to Bhaga, the god  of Fortune, whose name also means “portion.” The hymn begins (vs. 1) with a gen eral invocation of a range of gods in early morning, including Bhaga, but the next  five verses (2–5) call insistently on Bhaga, punning several times on his name. The  early-morning context of the hymn returns with the last two verses (6–7), concern ing the Dawns, who bring Bhaga with them (vs. 6). The final verse, which does not  mention Bhaga, is found also in a Dawn hymn later in the VIIth Maṇḍala (VII.80.3)  and is clearly extra-hymnic here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/042/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/042/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/042/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र ब्रह्माणः&amp;rsquo; इति षड़ृचं नवमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वैश्वदेवम् । अत्रानुक्रान्तं - ‘ प्र ब्रह्माणः षड्वैश्वदेवं तु &amp;rsquo; इति । सूक्तविनियोगो लैङ्गिकः । तृतीये छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्रे ‘प्र ब्रह्माणः  इति वैश्वदेवस्तृचः । सूत्रितं च &amp;mdash; प्र ब्रह्माणो अङ्गिरसो नक्षन्त सरस्वतीं देवयन्तो हवन्ते &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ११ ) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;42 (558)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;All Gods&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like VII.39, this hymn concerns the dawn soma sacrifice and especially Agni’s role  in it. The hymn begins with a verse expressing the readiness of all the ritual ele ments. Then Agni takes over and provides the impetus, hitching up his flames in  verse 2, and, as he gets larger, performing the sacrifice (vss. 3, 5). In verse 4 Agni  (identified as a guest, as often) is asked for the reward that is the expected return  for a successful sacrifice. The final verse (6) is a typical summary verse and names  Vasiṣṭha as the poet, as in another summary verse in this series (VII.39.7=40.7).  Although this is an All God hymn, the participation of named gods other than  Agni is limited to verse 5, where they are the simply the recipients of the sacrifice.  The mention of Aṅgirases in verse 1 is probably meant as a reference to the poet  and the other priests.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/043/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/043/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/043/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ प्र वो यज्ञेषु &amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं दशमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वैश्वदेवम्। ‘प्र वः पञ्च &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । सूक्तविनियोगो लैङ्गिकः । प्रथमे छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्रे ‘प्र वो यज्ञेषु &amp;rsquo; इति वैश्वदेवस्तृचः । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; ‘ प्र वो यज्ञेषु देवयन्तो अर्चन् प्र क्षोदसा धायसा सस्र एषेति प्रउगम् &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ९) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;43 (559)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;All Gods&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn has even less interest in individual gods than the most recent in this All  God series. Instead the sacrifice is again the focus: it is set in motion in verses 1–2,  with the priests exhorted to perform the ritual actions in the latter verse. The gods’  attendance is described in verses 3–4, and the poet’s relative indifference to their  individual identities is expressed in the phrase “however many you are” at the end  of verse 4. Appropriate to the ritual focus, Agni is the only god named (besides a  glancing reference to Heaven and Earth in vs. 1), and his actions and companion&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ship are crucial to our well-being.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/044/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/044/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/044/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘दधिक्रां वः &amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चमेकादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं दधिक्राख्यदेवताकम् । आद्या जगती सा तु दधिक्रादिलिङ्गोक्तदेवताका शिष्टाश्चतस्रस्त्रिष्टुभः । अनुक्रम्यते हि - दधिक्रां दाधिक्रं जगत्याद्या लिङ्गोक्तदेवता &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;44 (560)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dadhikrā, except Assorted Divinities (1)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh, except jagatī 1&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like VII.41, this hymn begins with a verse in jagatī calling on a number of gods,  especially those associated with the dawn ritual, and including the figure that will be the subject of most of the rest of the hymn, in this case the celebrated  racehorse Dadhikrā(van). (See IV.38–40 for other hymns devoted to Dadhikrā;  the last two [39—40] also show significant dawn associations.) Unlike VII.41,  however, where the god who is subject of the rest of the hymn, Bhaga, holds  the stage essentially alone after the first verse, Dadhikrā shares each of the  subsequent verses with a number of gods, again primarily characteristic of the  dawn ritual.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The most difficult verse is 3, not coincidentally the middle verse, whose third  pāda contains two color terms as addressees and a next-to-impossible hapax  (mām̐ścatóḥ), whose meaning is hotly disputed. Most commentators interpret  the color terms as referring to other horses. Our interpretation is quite different  and unavoidably speculative, but rather than introducing two otherwise unknown  horses, we identify the two addressees as gods associated with the ritual. In our view  the hapax refers to the two twilights (literally, “the time of the hiding of the moon,”  originally applied just to dawn), and the copper-colored one is the sun, whose color  is reddish at rising and setting, while the reddish-brown one is soma: the same color  term is used of soma a number of times.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Though it is not entirely clear why Dadhikrā is so strongly associated with the  dawn, it may be significant that the priestly gifts (dakṣiṇā) are distributed at the  dawn ritual and horses are among the most prized of these gifts. In most of this  hymn the equine aspects of Dadhikrā are not emphasized, except for vs. 4, unlike  the Dadhikrā hymns in Maṇḍala IV.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/045/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/045/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/045/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ देवो यातु&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं  द्वादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं सवितृदेवताकं त्रैष्टुभम्। &amp;lsquo;आ देवश्चतुष्कं सावित्रम्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । व्यूळ्हे दशरात्रे चतुर्थेऽहनि वैश्वदेशस्त्र इदं सावित्रनिविद्धानम्। सूत्र्यते हि - चतुर्थेऽहन्या देवो यातु &amp;ndash;&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ८)।&amp;hellip; इत्येषा वपानुवाक्या। सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash;&amp;rsquo; आ देवो यातु सविता सुरत्नः स घा नो देवः सविता सहावा &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ३. ७) इति। अश्वमेधेऽनुसवनं तिस्रः सावित्र्य इष्टयः । तत्र द्वितीयस्यामिष्टौ याज्येयम् । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; य इमा विश्वा जातान्या देवो यातु &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. १०. ६) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/046/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/046/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/046/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ इमा रुद्राय &amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं त्रयोदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं रुद्रदेवताकम् । अन्त्या त्रिष्टुप् शिष्टा जगत्यः । तथा चानुक्रमणिका - इमा रौद्रं त्रिष्टुबन्तम् &amp;rsquo; इति । शूलगवादिषु रौद्रयज्ञेष्वनेन सूक्तेनोदीची दिगुपस्थेया। सूत्र्यते हि - ‘ इमा रुद्राय स्थिरधन्वन इति सर्वरुद्रयज्ञेषु दिशामुपस्थानम् &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. गृ. ४. ९. २१ ) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;46 (562)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Rudra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: jagatī 1–3, triṣṭubh 4&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This brief hymn primarily begs Rudra to restrain his characteristic power to do  harm, though it also mentions in passing his healing and helpful gifts (vss. 3–4).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/047/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/047/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/047/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आपो यं वः&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं चतुर्दशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमब्देवताकम् । &amp;lsquo;आपो यमापम् &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तं च । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;47 (563)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Waters&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The waters are celebrated here primarily in their ritual employment, in the prepara tion of soma—though soma itself is not explicitly mentioned. These waters come to  be replaced by the rivers in the last two verses (3–4), but their physical characteris tics are not mentioned either. However, the final pāda before the refrain (4c) alludes  to the rivers’ making “wide space” for us, quite possibly an allusion to the enlarging  of the Ārya territory by crossing and conquering rivers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/048/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/048/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/048/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ ऋभुक्षणः&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं पञ्चदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमृभुदेवताकम् । अन्त्याया विकल्पेन विश्वे देवा देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तम् - ऋभुक्षण आर्भवमन्त्या वैश्वदेवी वा &amp;rsquo; इति । दशमेऽहनि वैश्वदेवशस्त्र आर्भवनिविद्धानम् । सूत्र्यते हि - ‘ ऋभुक्षण इत्यार्भवम् &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. १२) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;48 (564)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;R̥bhus&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The three R̥bhus are most commonly named R̥bhu, Vāja, and Vibhvan, and they  stand alongside Indra, who is sometimes called r̥bhukṣán “Master of the R̥bhus,”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/049/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/049/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/049/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘समुद्रज्येष्ठाः&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं षोडशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमब्देवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं &amp;ndash; समुद्रज्येष्ठा आपम् &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;49 (565)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Waters&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In contrast to VII.47, the waters in this hymn have more physical definition: in par ticular, verse 2 gives a notable typology of types of water: “heavenly waters” (rain), “those that flow” (rivers), “those found by digging” (well water), and “those that  arise by themselves” (springs)—all of which end by flowing into the sea. But the  purity and purifying power of flowing waters, noted in the first three verses, gives  them a moral as well as a physical quality, and in verse 3 the god Varuṇa in his role  as observer and judge of human actions is found among them. From passages like  this it is easy to see how Varuṇa came to be so closely associated with the waters, a  dominant characteristic of Varuṇa in later times. Verse 4 moves from the physical  and moral to the ritual realm, to the employment of water in the soma sacrifice, the  theme that prevailed in VII.47.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/050/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/050/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/050/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ मां मित्रावरुणा &amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं सप्तदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षम् । चतुर्थ्यतिजगती व्यूहेन शक्वरी वादितस्तिस्रो जगत्यः । प्रथमा मैत्रावरुणी द्वितीयाग्नेयी तृतीया वैश्वदेवी चतुर्थी गङ्गादिनदीदेवताका । तथा चानुक्रमणिका – &amp;rsquo; आ मां मैत्रावरुण्याग्नेयी वैश्वदेवी नदीस्तुतिर्जागतमन्त्यातिजगती शक्वरी वा &amp;rsquo; इति । अस्य सूक्तस्य प्रत्यृचं  विषादिहरणे विनियोगो लिङ्गादवगन्तव्यः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;50 (566)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Mitra and Varuṇa (1), Agni (2), the All Gods (3), the  Rivers (4)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: jagatī 1–3, atijagatī or śakvarī 4&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This is one of the relatively few healing hymns in the R̥gveda. The hymn is included  among those to the waters because of the last verse invoking the rivers for their  help. For a translation of the hymn and notes on the various lexical problems in it,  see Zysk (1985: 28 and 130–32).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The afflictions against which this hymn is recited center on the feet. The reference  to the “creeping thing” in the refrain of 1–3 led Velankar (1963) to propose that the  hymn is for treatment against different kinds of poison but especially against snake  venom. However, the symptoms and the causes of the foot problems, even though  they are too unclear to determine, appear to be varied. Zysk (p. 131) identifies the  “creeping thing” as the ajakāva (vs. 1), “an evil-looking, crawling animal&amp;hellip;which944 VII.51&lt;br&gt;&#xA;was known to have lived under the skin and to have formed a swelling or eruption”  (pp. 25–26). However, the ajakāva could also be referred to in 1b and therefore be  an ulcer or a swelling, if, as Renou (EVP XVI: 111) suggests, “the nesting thing”  is a skin lesion in contrast to a “swelling thing” on the skin. Likewise, we cannot  identify the vijāman joint, although it could be located in the foot, since the erup&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tion apparently spreads from it to the ankles and knees. And, as Zysk (pp. 131–32)  argues, the last verse probably refers to two kinds of female demons, the śipadā and  śimidā, who polluted waters and caused the foot problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/051/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/051/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/051/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ आदित्यानाम्&amp;rsquo; इति तृचमष्टादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमादित्यदेवताकम् । अनुक्रम्यते च - आदित्यानां तृचमादित्यं तु &amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः । आदित्यदेवताके पशौ आदित्यानामवसा &amp;rsquo; इति वपाया अनुवाक्या। सूत्रितं च - आदित्यानामवसा नूतनेनेमा गिर आदित्येभ्यः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ३.८) इति ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;आदित्यग्रहस्यैषानुवाक्या। सूत्रितं च - आदित्यानामवसा नूतनेन होता यक्षदादित्यान् &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ५. १७) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;51 (567)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ādityas&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is a general exhortation to the Ādityas to protect the sacrifice, keeping  its performance in “offenselessness” (adititvá), in accordance with their character as  sons of Aditi, the goddess who represents offenselessness or innocence. In the later  rite the offering of soma to Mitra and Varuṇa (as well as to the other dual divini&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ties) takes place in the morning and that to the Ādityas (as well as to other divine  collectives) in the evening. The gods in the last verse are worshiped at various times  in the sacrificial day, but there appears to be an emphasis on gods associated with  the evening rite: the Ādityas, All Gods, R̥bhus, and even the Aśvins, who are con&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nected with both the morning and the evening rituals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/052/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/052/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/052/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आदित्यासो अदितयः&amp;rsquo; इति तृचात्मकमेकोनविंशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमादित्यदेवताकम् ।  ‘ आदित्यासः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रमणिका । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;52 (568)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ādityas&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This short and probably late hymn has a number of unusual features. In verse 1 the  poet describes himself and his fellow sacrificers as áditi “offenseless,” and because  they are áditi they are also ādityá “Ādityas” or “sons of Aditi.” This is a surpris ing claim, and Geldner understandably softens it by turning the metaphor into a  simile. According to him, the poet asks that he and his people be offenseless like Ādityas. Were we to adopt Geldner’s approach, then in 1b we could supply a differ ent verb form and translate “there should be for us a fortress” (so Geldner) or “you  [=Ādityas] should be for us a fortress.” This solution is attractive since gods are  called fortresses in, for example, I.189.2 and VII.95.1. But there is no signal in the  text for the simile or for the ellipsis, and therefore, albeit with considerable hesita tion, we have translated the verse as if the speakers embody the “offenseless” gods.  That theme of offenselessness is continued in the next verse, in which the poet begs  that he and the sacrificers not be held responsible for the evil actions done by others.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In the last verse the poet speaks of the presence of the Aṅgirases in this sacrifice,  which suggests that the present priests now embody the legendary Aṅgiras priests,  a claim implicitly made elsewhere as well. The appeal to Savitar, who is associated  with the evening, and in verse 3d the reference to the All Gods, who in the later rite  receive offerings at the Third Pressing, place this hymn in that soma-pressing. The  identity of the “father” (vs. 3c) remains mysterious. Sāyaṇa identifies him as Varuṇa  since Varuṇa and Mitra are the fathers of Vasiṣṭha (cf. VII.33.11–13), but there is  little basis for associating Varuṇa here with either the Aṅgirases or the All Gods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/053/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/053/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/053/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र द्यावा यज्ञैः &amp;rsquo; इति तृचात्मकं विंशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं द्यावापृथिव्यम् । अनुक्रम्यते च &amp;mdash; प्र द्यावा द्यावापृथिव्यम्&amp;rsquo; इति । चतुर्थेऽहनि वैश्वदेवशस्त्र इदं द्यावापृथिव्यनिविद्धानम् । सूत्रितं च – &amp;rsquo; आ देवो यातु प्र द्यावेति वासिष्ठम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ८) इति । द्यावापृथिव्ये पशौ वपापुरोडाशयोः ‘प्र द्यावा &amp;rsquo; इति द्वे ऋचौ याज्ये। सूत्रितं च – प्र द्यावा यज्ञैः पृथिवी नमोभिरिति द्वे &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ३.८) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/054/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/054/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/054/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘वास्तोष्पते&amp;rsquo; इति तृचात्मकमेकविंशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वास्तोष्पत्यम् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते- ‘ वास्तोष्पते वास्तोष्पत्यम् &amp;rsquo; इति । स्मार्ते गृहनिर्माणे &amp;lsquo;वास्तोष्पते &amp;rsquo; इति चतसृभिः प्रत्यृचं जुहुयात् । सूत्रितं च - वास्तोष्पते प्रति जानीह्यस्मानिति चतसृभिः प्रत्यृचं हुत्वा &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. गृ. २. ९. ९ ) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;54 (570)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Lord of the Dwelling Place (Vāstospati) ̣&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This short hymn (but also see the first verse of the next one) is addressed to the  personified guardian spirit of the house and household and in later ritual is recited  for entry into a new house.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/055/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/055/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/055/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘अमीवहा&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं द्वाविंशं सूक्तम् । आद्या गायत्री पञ्चम्याद्याश्चतस्रोऽनुष्टुभो द्वितीयाद्यास्तिस्र उपरिष्टाद्बृहत्यः । ‘त्र्यष्टका चतुर्थद्वादशी बृहती&amp;rsquo; इति तल्लक्षणयोगात् । आद्या वास्तोष्पतिदेवताका शिष्टा ऐन्यःर्   । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्-&amp;lsquo;अमीवहाष्टौ वास्तोष्पत्याद्या गायत्री शेषास्त्र्युपरिष्टाद्बृहत्यादयोऽनुष्टुभः प्रस्वापिन्य उपनिषत् &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः । बृहद्देवतायां यदुक्तं  तदिह लिख्यते- वरुणस्य गृहान् रात्रौ वसिष्ठः स्वप्नमाचरन् । प्रविवेशाथ तं तत्र श्वा नदन्नभ्यवर्तत । क्रन्दन्तं सारमेयं स धावन्तं दष्टुमुद्यतम् ॥ यदर्जुनेति च द्वाभ्यां सान्त्वयित्वा ह्यसूषुपत् । एवं प्रस्वापयामास जनमन्यं च वारुणम्&amp;rsquo; (बृहद्दे. ६. ११-१३) इति । अत्र केचित् पुनरेवमाहुः-’ आसां प्रस्वापिनित्वं तु कथासु परिकल्प्यते । वसिष्ठस्तृषितोऽन्नार्थी त्रिरात्रालब्धभोजनः । चतुर्थरात्रौ चौर्यार्थं वारुणं गृहमेत्य तु । कोष्ठागारे प्रवेशाय पालकश्वादिसुप्तये । यदर्जुनेति सप्तर्चं ददर्श च जजाप च&amp;rsquo; (अनु. भा. ७. ५५) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/056/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/056/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/056/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथ चतुर्थेऽनुवाके पञ्चदश सूक्तानि । तत्र ‘ क ईं व्यक्ताः &amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चविंशत्यृचं प्रथमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं मरुद्देवताकम् । आद्या एकादश द्विपदा विंशत्यक्षरा विराजः शिष्टाश्चतुर्दश त्रिष्टुभः । तथा चानुकान्तं&amp;ndash; क ईं पञ्चाधिका मारुतं हाद्या एकादश द्विपदा &amp;rsquo; इति । दशरात्रे चतुर्थेऽहन्याग्निमारुते शस्त्र इदं मारुतनिविद्धानम् । सूत्र्यते हि &amp;ndash; वैश्वानरस्य सुमतौ क ईं व्यक्ता नरः &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ८) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;56 (572)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Maruts&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;25 verses: dvipadā virāj 1–11, triṣṭubh 12–25&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is structured like VII.34, an All God hymn, in that the first part is in the  short dvipadā meter and the second part in triṣṭubh, although the proportions of  verses in each meter are different. It also shares a final verse with VII.34, a generic  plea for the gods’ protection. But in content there is little in common between the  two hymns.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn begins with four verses about the birth and identity of the Maruts,  alluding both to their mysterious generation from Pr̥śni (see esp. vs. 4) and the para dox that they are both identical (“belonging to the same nest,” vs. 1) and separate  and rivalrous. This theme then disappears from the hymn, save for several refer ences to their plural “names” (vss. 10, 14; we of course know them only under one  name, “Maruts”). The rest of the dvipadā section (vss. 5–11) is essentially descrip tive, of their power, beauty, and accoutrements.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Although this celebration of the Maruts’ qualities continues in the triṣṭubh por tion, there is also a significant ritual component, initiated in the first half of verse  12. Subsequent verses make clear what ritual is involved: in verse 14 it is said that  they are worshiped at the beginning of the sacrifice, and they are invited to enjoy  the House-offering; in verse 16 they are called “playful.” In middle Vedic ritual  the third and last of the “Four-monthly” (Cāturmāsyāni) rituals is the Sākamedha, celebrated in the autumn. On the day before the Sākamedha day proper, the  Maruts receive two oblations—thus, they are worshiped at the beginning of the  sacrifice. Moreover, the second of these two oblations is the “House-offering”  (Gr̥hamedhīya). And on the next day there is an offering to the “playful Maruts,”  using the same word that describes their behavior in verse 16d. (For further refer&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ence to the Maruts at the Sākamedha in this Marut cycle, see VII.59.9–10. On the  ritual itself see, e.g., Hillebrandt 1897: 117–19; Keith 1925: 322–23.) As usual, offerings to the gods prompt us to ask for reciprocal benefits from the  gods, and these requests occupy much of the remaining verses (17–24), with the  final refrain verse (25) extending the requests to other gods as well. The last few  request verses specific to the Maruts (vss. 22–24) ask for their help in battles over  land and waters, alluding presumably to the Ārya expansion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/057/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/057/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/057/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ मध्वो वः &amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं मरुद्देवताकम्। &amp;rsquo; मध्वः सप्त &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । दशरात्रे षष्ठेऽहन्याग्निमारुत इदं मारुतनिविद्धानम्। सूत्रितं च - &amp;rsquo; मध्वो वो नाम स प्रत्नथेत्याग्निमारुतम् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ८.८) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;57 (573)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Maruts&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ritual offering to the Maruts is the subject of this whole hymn, although, unlike  the preceding hymn, no specific ritual is referred to. The hymn begins with an invita tion offered to the Maruts to the sacrificial “honey” (soma), an invitation phrased  in a way very close to the English idiom indicating potential possession “has their  name on it” (at least in our interpretation). They travel to the sacrifice and, having  received the guest reception, are asked to sit on the ritual grass, to receive the obla tion (vs. 2). The sacrifice is successfully concluded in verse 5, and their help and gifts  requested. The last two verses (6–7) seem to be a summary of the ritual process—in  6 they are urged to come in pursuit of oblations, in 7 to come in order to give help&lt;br&gt;&#xA;in return—the two verses being unified by the opening “when praised.” Verse 4 is somewhat odd in a Marut context. Although it is common to beg the  Maruts to keep their missile away from us (see, e.g., the preceding hymn, VII.56.9),  the reference to an “offense” committed by us humans is more appropriate to a  Varuṇa or Āditya context: see especially the use of the term in the Vasiṣṭha-Varuṇa  hymns later in this maṇḍala (VII.86.4, 87.7, 88.6), since the Maruts are not usually  associated with moral issues (though see vs. 5 in the next hymn, VII.58). Much  more typical is the lovely description of the glittering Maruts in verse 3.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/058/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/058/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/058/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ प्र साकमुक्षे &amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं तृतीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं मरुद्देवताकम् । अनुक्रान्तं च - ‘ प्र साकमुक्षे षट् &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;58 (574)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Maruts&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭub&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A description of the fearsome power of the Maruts, embodiments of the thun derstorm, begins the hymn (vss. 1–2), but the topic turns to their power to help  the poet and his patrons in verses 3–4, with the mythic model, their aid to Indra,  invoked briefly in verse 4. In verse 5 the potential anger of the Maruts is men tioned, and we seek to atone for whatever act occasioned it. Like the human  offense punished in verse 4 of the previous hymn, VII.57, this moral tone is  somewhat out of place in a Marut hymn. However, here the reference to the  Maruts’ father, Rudra the punisher and healer, provides a better context for this  scene of anger and atonement. The final verse (6) is a summary verse, referring  to the performance in the immediate past of the praise hymn that constitutes the  first five verses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/059/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/059/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/059/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘यं त्रायध्वे&amp;rsquo; इति द्वादशर्चं चतुर्थं सूक्तम् । अत्रेयमनुक्रमणिका - ‘यं त्रायध्वे द्वादश त्रिप्रगाथादि नवम्याद्यास्तिस्रो गायत्र्योऽन्त्यानुष्टुब्रौद्री मृत्युविमोचनी &amp;rsquo; इति । आद्यातृतीयापञ्चम्यो बृहत्यो द्वितीयाचतुर्थीषष्ठ्यः सतोबृहत्यः सप्तम्यष्टम्यावनुक्तत्वात् त्रिष्टुभौ नवमीदशम्येकादश्यो गायत्र्यः । द्वादश्यनुष्टुप् सा च रुद्रदेवताका । शिष्टा मारुत्यः । सूक्तविनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;59 (575)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Maruts (1–11), Rudra (12)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;12 verses: br̥hatī alternating with satobr̥hatī 1–6, arranged in pragāthas, triṣṭubh 7–8,  gāyatrī 9–11, anuṣṭubh 12&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As the variety of meters suggests, this is a composite hymn, with some of the sec tions clearly appended at the end of the Marut sequence. Its length confirms this  analysis, since the previous hymn contained only six verses.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first six verses consist of three pairs of pragāthas concerning the ritual ser vice offered first to a collection of gods (vs. 1, probably vs. 2) and then particularly  to the Maruts (vss. 3–6) and the benefits that accrue to the sacrificer. Vasiṣṭha names  himself in verse 3. This six-verse sequence conforms to the numerical pattern of the  Marut cycle and could have been original to it. The following two triṣṭubh verses  (7–8) continue the same theme, though more vividly. In particular, in verse 7 the  Maruts are compared to “dark-backed geese,” preening themselves in secret and  then flying here. This may be a reference to how quickly storms can seem to arise,  with thunderclouds fully developed (“preened in secret”).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The last four verses are clearly late additions. They make reference to the  Sākamedha rite encountered also in VII.56.14, the last of the Four-monthly rituals  described in middle Vedic texts. In verse 9 the Maruts are called “descendants of the  scorcher” (sā́ṃtapana), in verse 10 “sharers of the House-offering” (gŕ̥hamedha);  at the Sākamedha the Maruts as Sāṃtapana receive an offering at midday, and in954 VII.59&lt;br&gt;&#xA;the evening as Gr̥hamedha. The final verse (12), in a different meter, is dedicated  to “Tryambaka,” an epithet of Rudra. The Sākamedha ends with an oblation to  Rudra Tryambaka.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/060/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/060/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/060/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत्।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;व्याख्याय निगमाभिज्ञः पञ्चमस्य चतुर्थकम् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अध्यायं सायणाचार्यः पञ्चमं व्याकरोत्यथ ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तत्र ‘ यदद्य सूर्य &amp;rsquo; इति द्वादशर्चं पञ्चमं सूक्तम् । अत्रानुक्रमणिका – यदद्य मैत्रावरुणं तु वै सौर्याद्या &amp;rsquo; इति । मण्डलद्रष्टा वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । अनुक्तत्वात्त्रिष्टुप् छन्दः । ‘तु वै &amp;rsquo; इत्युक्तत्वादेतदादीनि सप्त सूक्तानि मित्रावरुणदेवत्यानि आद्या सूर्यदेवत्या । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;60 (576)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Mitra and Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;12 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The opening four verses describe the rising Sun, who watches over the good and  evil that people do. As such, he is the agent of Mitra, Varuṇa, and Aryaman,  since they are the gods whose central character is to govern the actions of mor tals. In verses 3–4 the poet blends the offerings that rise to the gods at dawn with  the antelopes of the Sun that carry him aloft. These antelopes are “rich in ghee”  (vs. 3), as the offerings would be. In verse 4 the “strengthening, honeyed ones”  are primarily the offerings given to Mitra and Varuṇa, but juxtaposed to the  Sun’s ascent and to the description of his antelopes, they also become reflections  of these antelopes, lifting the Sun to the heaven. In 4cd the Ādityas clear a path  for the Sun, and this image leads to the principal theme of the succeeding verses  and of the hymn itself—the ability of the Ādityas to lead even through difficult  circumstances. The Ādityas keep away those who oppose the truths they embody  (vs. 5), and they guide even those who may not understand their truths (vss. 6–7).  The “unwinking, perceptive ones” in 7a might be the gods themselves, although  they could also be the spies of Mitra and Varuṇa, who are described in similar  ways (cf. VII.61.3, 5) and who would be present both in heaven and on earth (cf.  VI.61.3).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;If there is benefit in following the Ādityas, there is also danger in not doing so.  The poet warns of the anger of the Ādityas (vs. 8), the hostility of Aryaman (vs.  9), the secret attack they can bring, and the hidden strength they possess (vs. 10).  All this leaves the poet and his people “trembling” (vs. 10) before them. The sense  of danger, either from those who do not follow the ways of the Ādityas or from  not following those ways, is strongly articulated in the second half of the hymn.  It is also here that the hymn designates Sudās, the king, as the special recipient of  the Ādityas’ protection and mercy (vss. 8, 9). This may point toward a time in  which the king and his people were trying to find and to establish a settlement  after the normal period of migration and battle, a time that might well be one of  particular peril.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/061/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/061/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/061/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“उद्वां चक्षुः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं षष्ठं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं मैत्रावरुणम्। &amp;lsquo;उद्वां सप्त &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रमणिका । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;61 (577)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Mitra and Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like the preceding hymn, with which it shares its final verse, this hymn begins with  a description of the rising Sun, who here is the eye of Mitra and Varuṇa, watch ing over the good and evils deeds of humans. In verse 2 the rising Sun parallels  the voice of the poet, who raises his hymn to Mitra and Varuṇa. And just as the  Sun fills the worlds with light, Mitra and Varuṇa penetrate all the worlds and even  go beyond them. Like kings who send their agents into the communities to note  what their subjects are doing and saying, Mitra and Varuṇa also have spies who are  everywhere (vs. 3).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The mention of these spies in verse 3 may help explain the most problematic  verse in the hymn, verse 5. There are several ways to construe the verse: ámūrā víśvā could be vocative and nominative dual respectively, describing Mitra and  Varuṇa as those who can never be fooled (so Geldner), but more likely they  describe the drúhaḥ “deceptions” in 5c. As Oldenberg notes, grammatically dis persing the phrase ámūrā víśvā(ḥ). . . imā́ḥ “all these who are never fooled” seems  forced. But the idea that Mitra and Varuṇa themselves deceive has understand ably given interpreters pause. Still, in X.109.4 Indra is said never to be deceived  but himself deceiving (√dabh) and in the previous hymn, in VII.60.9c, Aryaman  can bring “hostilities” against those who do not act rightly. The “deceptions”  of Mitra and Varuṇa are probably their hidden spies. These spies are actually  not seen and accordingly in this verse they are unidentified and hence verbally  hidden. The verse even works a deception of its own, describing the spies in the  feminine plural—spáśaḥ “spies” is masculine plural—and delaying the feminine  term that stands for them, drúhaḥ, until pāda c.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/062/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/062/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/062/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ उत्सूर्यः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं सप्तमं सूक्तम् । अत्रानुक्रमणिका &amp;ndash; उत्सूर्यः षळाद्यास्तिस्रः सौर्यः । इति । वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । त्रिष्टुप् छन्दः। आद्यास्तिस्रः सूर्यदेवत्याः शिष्टा मित्रावरुणदेवत्याः । सूक्तविनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;62 (578)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Sūrya (1–3), Mitra and Varuṇa (4–6)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As in the two previous hymns, the poet begins with the rising Sun, who shines down  upon all the Ārya tribes and fills the heaven with his light and therefore becomes  equal to heaven (vs. 1). The antelopes of the Sun carry him up, as do the praise  songs as they rise, and from heaven the Sun witnesses the deeds of humans and  attests to the Ādityas and Agni the innocence of the sacrificers (vs. 2). In verse 3 the  poet asks that Varuṇa, Mitra, and Agni bring them the highest arká. The primary  meaning of arká is “chant,” and therefore the first idea is that these gods will inspire  the chant of the sacrificers. But arká can carry a secondary meaning, “flame,” a  sense that is actualized here through the description of the gods as candrá “glitter ing” and by arcís “flame,” the latter etymologically related to arká in this meaning.  So like the Sun these gods will brighten themselves and also make bright the world  of the sacrificers.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 4 three gods—Heaven and Earth and Aditi, the mother of the Ādityas— are addressed in pāda a, but the remainder of ab refers only to two gods, Heaven  and Earth. The poet continues to address two gods in verse 5, revealing only in the  last pāda that the two gods are Mitra and Varuṇa. Finally, in the last verse the poet  matches the image of light spreading over earth and heaven that was introduced in  the first verse with the “wide space” across generations and the freedom of move&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ment that Mitra and Varuṇa will offer.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Although the poet does not continue the strategy through the whole hymn,  verses 1–2 have a striking number of sound repetitions. Thus 1d is krátvā kr̥táḥ súkr̥taḥ kartŕ̥bhir bhūt, 2b ebhí stómebhir etaśébhir évaiḥ, and 2d (á)nāgaso aryamṇé agnáye ca. In verse 2 the sound repetitions underscore the tie between the Sun’s ani mals and the praise songs and the bonds between Aryaman, Agni, and the innocent  sacrificers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/063/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/063/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/063/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘उद्वेति&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचमष्टमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभम्। आद्याश्चतस्रः पञ्चम्याः पूर्वार्धश्च सूर्यदेवत्या अवशिष्टास्त्रयोऽर्धर्चा मित्रावरुणदेवत्याः । तथा चानुकान्तम् - उद्वेतीति चार्धपञ्चमाः &amp;rsquo; इति । विनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;63 (579)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Sūrya (1–5ab), Mitra and Varuṇa (5cd–6)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Even more than the other hymns in the sequence VII.60–65, this hymn concen trates on the rising Sun. Here the Sun becomes the visible sign and the embodiment  of the Ādityas. He is the eye of Mitra and Varuṇa (vs. 1) and subhága “bringing  good fortune,” like Bhaga, the god Fortune (vs. 1). But the Sun is especially like the  god Savitar, the “Impeller.” He is prasavitár, who “impels forth” (vs. 2); he takes  the form of Savitar (vs. 3); and the people are impelled (prasūtá) by him (vs. 4).  The god Savitar especially drives living beings to their homes at night, so here the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/064/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/064/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/064/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘दिवि क्षयन्ता &amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं नवमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं मैत्रावरुणम्। &amp;lsquo;दिवि पञ्च&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रमणिका। तृतीये छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्र आद्यस्तृचो मैत्रावरुणस्य । सूत्रितं च - दिवि क्षयन्ता रजसः पृथिव्यामा विश्ववाराश्विना गतं नः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ११) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;64 (580)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Mitra and Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is a prayer to the Ādityas for rain, as the poet makes explicit in verse  2cd. Geldner rightly sees the likelihood of a double reading of verse 1. The “cloaks  of ghee” are butter offerings given to Mitra and Varuṇa, but at the same time they  are rain that the Ādityas send in response to these offerings. So also in verse 4, the  “ghee” that Mitra and Varuṇa should sprinkle on the composer of this hymn is  rain. As a result of the rain, the dwellings of the sacrificers will prosper (4cd, 5c).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As often, the middle verse of the hymn is more cryptic than the others. Mitra and  Varuṇa are addressed, as is the devó aryáḥ, translated here the “civilizing god” and  referring to Aryaman. The point of mentioning Aryaman in such an indirect way  is to create a verbal connection between the devó aryáḥ and the arí, the “stranger”  in pāda c. An arí is an outsider, but one who belongs to the Vedic peoples and fol&lt;br&gt;&#xA;lows the customs of the Āryas. The point is that such a stranger will recognize the  sacrificers as those who prosper because they follow the Ādityas and the ways of the  Āryas and will honor them as sudā́saḥ “good givers,” generous people. But Sudās  is also the Bharata king who figures very prominently in the Vasiṣṭha hymns, and,  inescapably, this designation must recall him. That is to say, even one who belongs  to another Vedic tribe will see that the sacrificers are “Sudāses” or like Sudās, the  great king, in their prosperity and generosity.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 4, the “chariot seat” is the seat of honor here at the sacrifice, which is  implicitly imagined as a chariot, as often elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/065/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/065/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/065/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ प्रति वां सूरे&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं दशमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं मैत्रावरुणम् ।  ‘ प्रति वाम् इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । द्वितीये छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्रेऽप्येष तृचः । सूत्रितं च- ‘ प्रति वां सूर उदिते सूक्तैर्धेनुः प्रत्नस्य&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. १०) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;65 (581)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Mitra and Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is similar in theme and phrasing to the preceding hymn, with which it  also shares the final verse. It too is fundamentally a prayer for rain to Mitra and  Varuṇa. There is no reference to Aryaman, although there is an indirect reference  to his function as god of customs in the poet’s description of Mitra and Varuṇa as  aryá “civilizing” (vs. 2a). Verse 4 most explicitly states the theme of the hymn. In  pāda a the poet offers the gods oblations, which include ghee and other ritual liba&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tions, and in b he asks for these in return, though in the form of rain. In c we read  váram “wish” twice, once in the phrase práti&amp;hellip; váram “at your wish,” referring to  the wish of the gods for oblations, and second in the phrase váram ā́&amp;hellip;pr̥ṇītám “fill  our wish” for rain. Thus in both ab and cd, the poet first refers to the desire of the  gods and then his own desire.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The translation below also takes víśva “everyone” twice in the translation of  verse 1, which, like the first verse of the preceding hymn, offers a possible double  reading. According to the translation below, in pāda d Mitra and Varuṇa move  “upon the course of everyone,” that is, they follow or accompany the actions of all  beings. But yā́man “course” can also mean “entreaty,” and if construed with ācít&lt;br&gt;&#xA;“attentive,” the line could also mean, “moving on the course of everyone, attentive  to the entreaty of everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/066/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/066/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/066/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र मित्रयोः&amp;rsquo; इत्येकोनविंशत्यृचमेकादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षम् । अत्रेयमनुक्रमणिका – प्र मित्रयोरेकोना गायत्रं दशम्याद्यास्त्रयः प्रगाथाः पुरउष्णिक् चतुर्थ्याद्या दशादित्यास्तिस्रः सौर्यः । इति । दशमी बृहत्येकादशी सतोबृहती द्वादशी बृहती त्रयोदशी सतोबृहती चतुर्दशी बृहती पञ्चदशी सतोबृहती षोडशी पुरउणिक् शिष्टा गायत्र्यः । चतुर्थ्याद्यास्त्रयोदश्यन्ता आदित्यदेवताः चतुर्दश्याद्यास्तिस्रः सूर्यदेवत्याः। आद्यन्त्यौ तृचौ पूर्ववन्मैत्रावरुणौ । अग्निष्टोमे माध्यंदिनसवने मैश्रावरुणशस्त्र आदितो नवर्चः शस्याः। प्र मित्रयोर्वरुणयोरिति नव&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ५. १०) इति सूत्रितत्वात् । पृष्ठ्याभिप्लवषडहयोः स्तोमवृद्धिनिमित्तमावापार्था आद्याः षडृचः । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; ‘ प्र मित्रयोर्वरुणयोरिति षट् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ५) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/067/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/067/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/067/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्रति वां रथम्&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं द्वादशं सूक्तम् । ‘प्रति वां दशाश्विनं तु तत्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रमणिका । ऋषिर्वसिष्ठः । छन्दस्त्रिष्टुप् । तुह्यादिपरिभाषयैतदादीनि अष्ट सूक्तान्यश्विदेवत्यानि। प्रातरनुवाक आश्विने क्रतौ त्रैष्टुभे छन्दस्येतदादिसूक्तसप्तकं द्वितीयवर्जं शंस्यम् । तथा च सूत्रं&amp;mdash; ‘प्रति वां रथमिति सप्तानां द्वितीयमुद्धरेत्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ४. १५) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;67 (583)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Aśvins&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The opening verses of this hymn describe the early morning advent of the Aśvins,  when the sacrificial fire is kindled and the dawn becomes visible (vs. 2). They also  present problems of translation and interpretation that turn on the identity of the  Aśvins’ chariot. Elsewhere the Aśvins’ chariot can be the sacrifice or the hymns of  the sacrifice that bring the Aśvins to the rite. Therefore, the chariot in verse 1a is  the vehicle bringing the Aśvins. In 1c “that which” the poet recites and “that which”  serves as a messenger to awaken the Aśvins is the praise song, now become the  Aśvins’ chariot carrying the Aśvins to the rite. In verse 4 there is no explicit men tion of the chariot, but there is a complex ellipsis in 4a, which lacks both subject  and verb. The gapped subject may be the chariot, but again the chariot as the hymn  that seeks the Aśvins.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn itself continues to be the focus of the poet in verses 5–6. In verse 5  he calls upon the Aśvins to advance his insight so that it will win gain for the sac rificers. While the poet previously mentioned the chariotry directly, here he refers  to the hymn using the language of competition and prizewinning appropriate for a  chariot. In verse 7 the poet also speaks of the “treasure,” the soma, which is offered  to the Aśvins along with his hymn, and he shifts attention from his “thought,” which  he offers to the Aśvins in the form of his hymn (vs. 1), to the Aśvins’ thought, which  he hopes will not be hostile to the sacrificers. In the final two verses the poet appeals  to the Aśvins to support his patrons, whose generosity and bounty he celebrates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/068/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/068/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/068/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ शुभा यातम्&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं त्रयोदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षमाश्विनम् । आदितः सप्त विराजोऽष्टमीनवम्यौ त्रिष्टुभौ । अनुक्रम्यते च&amp;mdash; आ शुभ्रा नव सप्ताद्या विराजः&amp;rsquo; इति । सूक्तविनियोगो लैङ्गिकः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;68 (584)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Aśvins&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: virāj 1–7, triṣṭubh 8–9&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In its first four verses the hymn opens with an invitation to the Aśvins to come to  the sacrifice in the early morning and to receive the soma offerings being made to  them. In verse 3 the Aśvins come with the daughter of the Sun, Sūryā, which marks  this as a morning hymn (cf. also vs. 9). In verse 4c the vípra “inspired poet” is likely  the reciter of the hymn, but in 4ab the pressing stone also sounds as it crushes the  soma stalks, and therefore it too could be the poet in the latter half of the verse.  The stone prepares the soma offerings, so the reference to the oblations in 4c would  also be appropriate to it.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Then in the second set of four verses (vss. 5–8) the poet briefly describes great  deeds of the Aśvins and four of the past figures whom they helped. In verses 6 and  8 the poet mentions the offerings of Cyavāna havirdā́ “the giver of offerings” and  their summons (hūyámāna) by Śayu, words that echo the present offerings (havís,  2b) and the calls to the Aśvins (hávana, 2c).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 5 alludes to the story of Atri, who was rescued from the heat of a pit oven  by the Aśvins and who received sustenance from them. That is to say, the Aśvins  rescued him with food and from becoming treated like food. In this verse the poet  refers to the “sustenance” (bhójana) and the “relief” (omán) Atri receives. Similarly,  in I.116.8 the Aśvins give Atri “nourishment together with solid food” (pitumátīm  ū́rjam) and in 118.7 they give “nourishment” and “relief” (ū́rjam omā́nam). Geldner  suggests that Atri receives from the Aśvins an elixir that restores him to life, but  these descriptions suggest more mundane gifts of food and drink that saved Atri  from starvation.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 7 Bhujyu’s evil-intentioned companions include his father, Tugra,  who left him behind (I.116.3, 119.8). But somehow the Aśvins changed Tugra’s  mind and rescued Bhujyu through Tugra, who, as the description yuvā́ku “seek ing you” implies, was a worshiper of the Aśvins (cf. I.117.14). In verse 8 the poet  refers to the Aśvins’ willingness to come to the rescue even of a “wolf,” of a bad  person, who is “starving” (jásamāna). This applies to Śayu, since he was once&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/069/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/069/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/069/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ वां रथः&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं चतुर्दशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाश्विनम् । अनुक्रम्यते च - ’आ वां रथोऽष्टौ &amp;rsquo; इति । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोर्विनियोग उक्तः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;69 (585)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Aśvins&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn is dominated by the chariot of the Aśvins and the theme of the journey  of the Aśvins. The poet opens with the chariot (rátha) and refers to it, often explic itly, in every verse. In verse 1 the poet describes their “golden chariot,” whose bril liance reflects the morning light that accompanies its advent. The final pāda of the  verse takes an interesting turn. The chariot is first called voḷhár “conveyor,” a term  that ordinarily refers to the chariot driver (as in I.144.3d, VI.64.3d, VII.2.35c) or  the horse that pulls a chariot (IX.81.2b, 96.15d, 112.4a). But here and in the simi lar pāda VII.71.4a, it describes the chariot itself, attributing agency to it. But then  the poet also calls—or appears to call—the chariot nŕ̥pati “lord of men,” which  should describe the Aśvins themselves, as it does in VII.71.4. Geldner suggests that  it could be a luptopamā, a comparison in which the particle of comparison has been  omitted: “(wie) ein Fürst.” Renou (EVP XVI: 48) describes the figure as a sort of  hypallage caused by the juxtaposition rátho nr̥patī in VII.71.4. Renou is likely right  that the pāda responds to VII.71.4, but it rather appears to be a semantic expansion  of the chariot so that it includes or rather becomes the horses that pull it and the  drivers who direct it. Also in verse 3 the chariot again takes the role of a groom,  “clasping the bride,” who is being carried on the chariot to her marriage. Behind  this semantic expansion of the chariot, if that is what is occurring, may be the  image of the Aśvins’ chariot as the sacrifice itself. Note that the chariot is described  as “having tracks of ghee” (vs. 1c) and “three chariot-boxes” (vs. 2b), corresponding  to the three soma-pressings. The chariot is not just the sacrifice, however. As usual,  it remains the chariot that brings the Aśvins to the sacrifice, as well as being the  sacrifice, at least in these opening verses.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The theme of the journey of the Aśvins is marked by verbal derivatives of √yā “journey,” which appear in every verse except verses 4 and 7. These two verses refer  to the great deeds of the Aśvins: how they brought the daughter of the Sun to her  marriage, how they rescued Atri from the heat of a pit oven, and how they saved  Bhujyu from the sea. The Aśvins’ chariot and thereby the theme of journeying are  involved in all of these rescues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/070/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/070/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/070/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ विश्ववारा&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं पञ्चदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाश्विनम् । अनुक्रम्यते च&amp;ndash; ’आ विश्ववारा सप्त&amp;rsquo; इति । प्रातरनुवाक आश्विनशस्त्रे च विनियोग उक्तः । आद्यस्तृचस्तृतीये छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्रे विनियुक्तः । विश्ववाराश्विना गतं नोऽयं सोम इन्द्र&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ११ ) इति सूत्रितत्वात् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;70 (586)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Aśvins&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In the last verse the poet calls the attention of the Aśvins to his hymn, calling it  “intricate” or “well-twisted” (suvr̥ktí). He is quite right: his hymn is complex, since  it presents metaphors of unclear reference and ellipses of uncertain interpretation.  Such intricacy is attractive to gods like the Aśvins, and the purpose of the poet is to  get the attention of the Aśvins by means of the hymn and to cause them to take notice  of the offerings and other elements of the sacrifice so that they will be present at it.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 1 the poet summons the Aśvins to take their place at the sacrifice, but  1cd, in which he describes the coming of the Aśvins, can be variously interpreted.  In 1c something “stood” when the Aśvins took their place. We have suggested that  this is the sacrificial fire kindled in the early morning, but other interpreters have  offered other reasonable possibilities: the hot milk offered to the Aśvins (Oldenberg,  Renou [EVP XVI: 49]) or the liquid offerings more generally (Geldner), the vessel for the hot milk (Oldenberg), the “good favor” mentioned in verse 2a (Renou), or  the place itself (Geldner, Velankar [1963]). Of these, the gharma or hot milk offer ing, which is mentioned in 2b, is the strongest possibility, and of course, the sup pression of the subject in 1cd might have allowed hearers to recall several or all of  these things that welcome the Aśvins.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 3 the poet shifts attention to the rewards that the Aśvins will bring. The  sacrificer hopes to find prosperity for the sacrificer from the rivers, plants, and clans,  among which the Aśvins find a place, over which they sit “at the peak of the moun tain”—in heaven perhaps? In verse 4a the “plants and the waters” recall the rivers,  plants, and clans of verse 3 and verbally connect the two verses, even though the  poet again shifts the theme back to the sacrifice being offered to the Aśvins. Here  the waters and plants represent sacrificial libations and offerings. In 4b it is not clear  what are the “harness cords” (yogyā́). They might be rites or offerings (especially  the hot milk offering), or hymns. That is, they are elements of the sacrifice of one  kind or another. Whatever these cords are, the image carries forward the descrip&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tion of the Aśvins in 2cd as “well-harnessed” horses and therefore should represent  what attaches the Aśvins to the sacrifice. In 4cd the Aśvins reward the present sacri ficers while keeping in mind the ancient ones. The present sacrifices are the equal to  the ones of the past and therefore deserve the reward of the Aśvins.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In the last verses the poet becomes more straightforward in calling the Aśvins’  attention to his hymn, his “formulations,” which he has sent out in search of them  (vs. 7), and to the sacrifice which stands ready for them (vs. 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/071/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/071/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/071/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;पञ्चमेऽनुवाके एकोनविंशतिसूक्तानि । तत्र ‘अप स्वसुः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं प्रथमं सूक्तं त्रैष्टुभमाश्विनम् । अनुक्रम्यते च -– अप स्वसुः षट्&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;71 (587)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Aśvins&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In its final verse this hymn repeats the last verse of the previous hymn, and as that  verse says, it too is an intricate one (suvr̥ktí). The first verse marks this as an early morning hymn. Since the ruddy light of early dawn is elsewhere associated with the  ruddy cattle, the poet echoes that connection by describing the horses and cattle  that the Aśvins bring. There is also a second possible reading: the two compounds  áśvāmaghā[ḥ] gómaghā[ḥ] “having bounties of horses, bounties of cattle” could  be nominative plurals as well as duals and be taken as proleptic adjectives modify ing the 1st-person “we.” This grammatical ambiguity can imply that the horses and&lt;br&gt;&#xA;cattle that the Aśvins bring will become the horses and cattle that we will have. In verses 1–2 the Aśvins are asked also for rescue from enemies, want, and dis ease. In verses 3–4 the poet then turns especially to the chariot of the Aśvins, and, as  often, the chariot is linked to the sacrifice itself. In 3c its horses are “in the harness of  truth,” that is, joined to the hymns and even to the rites, which may also be expres sions of truth. The chariot is also syū́magabhasti, an elusive hapax. Geldner among  others connects gábhasti “hands” to the rays of the sun, but there is no clear instance  of such a use elsewhere in the R̥gveda. We propose, therefore, that the hands, which  normally hold reins, have themselves become the reins (syū́man) of the chariot  because they are the hands of the priests, who control the ritual. In verse 4 the analy sis and reference of viśvápsnya, perhaps “containing all milk,” are obscure. Geldner  wonders whether the word might describe the praise hymn or Agni. The gharma  vessel suggested here is uncertain at best. Verse 5 then returns to the Aśvins’ ability  to save from danger by describing four great acts of rescue. The last, the rescue of  Jāhuṣa, is the least familiar and can be only tentatively reconstructed. The best sug gestion is that of Oldenberg, who says that by combining verse 5d and I.116.20cd we  can get the following: Jāhuṣa was trapped by his enemies is a wild, rocky area, but  the Aśvins brought him out and set him down on light, soft soil.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/072/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/072/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/072/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ गोमता&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाश्विनम्। अनुक्रम्यते च&amp;ndash; ’आ गोमता पञ्च&amp;rsquo; इति । विनियोगः प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोरुक्तः । आश्विने पशावाद्याश्चतस्रो याज्यानुवाक्याः। सूत्रितं च-– आ गोमता नासत्या रथेनेति चतस्रः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ३. ८) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;72 (588)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Aśvins&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn is marked by the repeated invitations to the Aśvins to “journey here”  (ā́&amp;hellip;yātam, vss. 1, 2, and 5), which create a ring of the hymn’s beginning and end.  The urgent pleas that the Aśvins come here to this place, to this sacrifice and not to  another, is reinforced by other words meaning “near” or “this way” (arvā́k, 2a) and  “here” (áchā, 3d). Only verse 4 counters by opening with ví, here translated “forth,”  but more exactly signifying “away, apart.” This verse shifts the attention to the  spreading light of dawn (pādas a, c), which is matched in pāda d by the spreading  light of the sacrificial fires and in b by the poetic formulations rising from the sing ers. The last verse joins the expansiveness of verse 4 to the invitation to the Aśvins  by describing the four directions in which the Aśvins are present and from which  they can come to the sacrifice at the center.974 VII.73&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The four directions and the implicit center in verse 4 are reflected in the “wealth  belonging to the five peoples” (vs. 5c), that is, the wealth belonging to all the Vedic  clans and tribes. This wish also suggests that this hymn is recited on behalf of  one who sees himself, his tribe, or his clan at the center of the Vedic peoples. The  Vasiṣṭha poet is not shy about pointing to his family’s connection to the center  either, since he speaks of the familial formulations that “awaken” in order to bring  the Aśvins (vs. 3ab).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/073/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/073/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/073/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘अतारिष्म &amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमाश्विनम् । अतारिष्म&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रमणिका। प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोरुक्तो विनियोगः ।।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;73 (589)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Aśvins&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This short hymn is a summons to the Aśvins at the break of dawn, “the further  shore of &amp;hellip;darkness.” In verse 2 the poet calls the Aśvins’ attention to Agni, the  sacrificial fire and the Hotar of the sacrifice, who has been installed and stands  ready to give the offerings to the Aśvins (2ab). All is ready for the Aśvins to con&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sume the soma and the other offerings presented to them (2cd). In verse 3a the poet  compares this sacrifice to a chariot speeding to the Aśvins. This image is answered  in verse 4ab, which looks forward to the arrival of the váhnī, the “two chariot horses.” The term can refer to the horses of the Aśvins, but it might also refer to  the Aśvins themselves as chariot-horses (cf. VIII.8.12). But in either case the idea is that the fully prepared sacrifice races to the Aśvins, and the Aśvins, with or as fully  equipped horses, race to the sacrifice. Again, in verse 4cd the poet draws attention  to the ritual preparations made for the Aśvins and begs the Aśvins not to ignore his  call and overlook his sacrifice. The last verse repeats the final verse of the preceding  hymn. Here it is not so closely tied to the themes of the hymn, but it appropriately  continues the plea to the Aśvins to travel from wherever they are to the sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/074/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/074/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/074/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘इमा उ वाम्&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं चतुर्थं सूक्तमाश्विनं वसिष्ठस्यार्षम् । आद्यातृतीयापञ्चम्यो बृहत्यः शिष्टाः सतोबृहत्यः । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्-’इमा उ वां षट् प्रागाथम् &amp;rsquo; इति । प्रातरनुवाक आश्विने क्रतौ बार्हते छन्दस्याश्विनशस्त्रे च सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash; इमा उ वामयं वाम् &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ४. १५) इति । दशरात्रे पञ्चमेऽहनि प्रउगशस्त्रे &amp;lsquo;इमा उ वाम्&amp;rsquo; इत्ययमाश्विनस्तृचः। सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash;’इमा उ वां दिविष्टयः पिबा सुतस्य रसिनः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. १२) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/075/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/075/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/075/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘व्युषा आवः&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं पञ्चमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षम् । अत्रानुक्रमणिका – व्युषा अष्टावुषस्यं तु वै &amp;rsquo; इति । तु वै इत्युक्तत्वात्तुह्यादिपरिभाषया इदमादीनि सप्त सूक्तान्युषोदेवत्यानि । प्रातरनुवाक उषस्ये क्रतौ त्रैष्टुभे छन्दस्याश्विनशस्त्रे चेदमादीनि षट् सूक्तानि । तथा च सूत्र्यते - &amp;rsquo; व्युषा आवो दिविजा इति षडिति त्रैष्टुभम् &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ४. १४) इति । ऋग्विधान आख्यातो विनियोगोऽत्र लिख्यते - &amp;lsquo;रात्र्या अपरकाले य उत्थाय प्रयतः शुचिः । व्युषा इत्युपतिष्ठेत षड्भिः सूक्तैः कृताञ्जलिः ॥ प्राप्नुयात् स हिरण्यानि नानारूपं धनं बहु । गा अश्वान् पुरुषान् धान्यं स्त्रियो वासांस्यजाविकम् &amp;rsquo; (ऋग्वि. २. ३१७-१८) इति ।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/076/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/076/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/076/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;rsquo; उदु ज्योतिः &amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं षष्ठं सूक्तं त्रैष्टुभमुषस्यम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम् - &amp;rsquo; उदु सप्त इति । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोरुक्तो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;76 (592)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dawn&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A tightly structured hymn: the verbally responsive verses 3–4 are set within an inner  ring (vss. 2, 5) with exact repetition in their final pādas (ámardhanto vásubhiḥ&amp;hellip;). This&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;structure is reinforced by tense usage: the verbs in verses 1–2 are all augmented aor ists referring to the immediate past of today’s dawn; those in verses 5–7 are present  indicatives and imperatives, stating general truths about the behavior of the dawns  and the singers; while those in verses 3–4 are augmented imperfects (with one per&lt;br&gt;&#xA;fect) referring to the distant past, which gave rise to the present situation. This structure defines verses 3–4 as an omphalos, and indeed these verses show  clear omphalos features. Verse 3 contains the most intricate syntax in the hymn,  while verse 4 concerns the Father’s finding of “the hidden light” in the Vala cave,  the primeval model for each new dawn. Verses 3 and 4 are in reverse chronologi cal order: the Fathers find the hidden light of Dawn in verse 4, and verse 3 then  describes the subsequent time with the periodic return of the Dawn, eagerly pro ceeding to the sacrifice as if to a lover, not moving slowly and reluctantly like a  maiden leaving an assignation.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The exact repetition in the inner ring mentioned above is not a static feature. It  participates in what we have termed “poetic repair” (Jamison 2006) and therefore  provides forward movement by setting up a puzzle that is resolved later in the hymn.  The adjective ámardhantaḥ “not negligent” modifies “paths” in verse 2. The com&lt;br&gt;&#xA;bination seems discordant, although the hearer can construct a meaningful read ing: paths that are not negligent are those, properly maintained and “set in order,”  that lead one where they are supposed to go. The application of “not negligent” to  the priests in verse 5 is far easier to interpret: not negligent priests are those who  properly perform the sacrifice every morning and therefore do not transgress the  gods’ commandments that regulate the proper functioning of the cosmos, since  by ritual logic the sacrifice causes the new day to dawn. The phrase in verse 5 thus  “repairs” the more jarring one in verse 2, but the jarring phrase in verse 2 also  forced the hearers to formulate a more complex conception.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As so often, consideration of poetic structure gives depth to the apparently  conventional expressions and images in this hymn, which recur in so many other  descriptions of Dawn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/077/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/077/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/077/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ उपो रुरुचे &amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं सप्तमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षमुषस्यम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम् - उपो रुरुचे षट् &amp;rsquo; इति । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोरुक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;77 (593)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dawn&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Renou (EVP III: 95) calls this hymn a “pièce banale,” a designation that seems  hardly fair. Although it lacks the intricate patterning of the immediately pre ceding hymn, its simpler structure gives it a forward-moving urgency encoded  in its deployment of verb forms. The first half of the hymn (vss. 1–3) opens  with a perfect (ruruce “she has shone”) but thereafter consists entirely of aug mented aorists (like vss. 1–2 of VII.76), with aroci of 2d almost forming a  ring with the opening perfect form, built to the same root (√ruc). There is an  abrupt change of verbal mood in verse 4, with a cascade of imperatives in the  next two verses (4–5). The grammatical person also changes: the constant 3rd  person of verses 1–3 is succeeded by 2nd person in the rest of the hymn. Thus  the first half of the hymn describes the immediate arrival of Dawn, and in  the second the poet addresses a series of eager commands to Dawn, who has  just appeared in front of him. Two features tie the hymn together grammati cally: (1) the abundance of present participles modifying Dawn in both halves,  though more common in the first; and (2) the constant use of Dawn as subject.  Except for 1c and the first half of the final verse (6ab) Dawn is always the  grammatical subject. A glance at other Dawn hymns in this series shows that  this uniformity is unusual.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;No doubt Renou’s remark concerned the “content” of the hymn, and it is cer tainly true that there are no remarkable images or elaborate conceits. However, the&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/078/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/078/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/078/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;प्रति केतवः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चमष्टमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमुषस्यम् । ‘प्रति पञ्च&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रमणिका। उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;78 (594)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dawn&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is characterized by two “signature words”: práti “in response to / oppo site” (found in every verse but 4)  and the present participle vibhā́tī “radiating  widely” (vss. 3–5), words regularly found in other Dawn hymns. In fact, there is,  until near the end, little novel about this hymn. The most noticeable feature until  the end is that the middle verse (3) refers to the dawns in the plural, though they&lt;br&gt;&#xA;seem to be immediately present, while the other verses have singular Dawn. But the most noteworthy aspect of the hymn is the striking hapax verb that opens  the last half verse (5c): tilvilāyádhvam. This is a transparent denominative built to  the adjective tílvila (V.62.7), but this only displaces the problem, as the meaning  and derivation of this adjective are not at all clear, and its rhyming reduplicative formation (til-vil) deviates markedly from normal Vedic word formation patterns.  The adjective is generally taken to mean “fruitful’ or the like and may be connected  with the word tilá “sesame.” If so, the creation and abundant scattering of seed may  be the intended meaning here, though this is only a guess. The English idiom used  to translate this obscure word is meant to convey its special status in the diction of  this otherwise unremarkable hymn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/079/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/079/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/079/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘व्युषा आवः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं नवमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षमुषस्यं त्रैष्टुभम् । “व्युषाः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रमणिका । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोरुक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;79 (595)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dawn&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This little hymn is dense with phonetic figures and puns, and like the preceding  hymn has signature words—in this case the preverb ví “apart, widely” and the pho nologically similar verbal roots vas “dawn” and vR̥(var) “(un)cover.”&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like many Dawn hymns, this one gives the opening of the Vala cave and the  release of the cows imprisoned therein as the mythic model for each new dawn (see  esp. vs. 4). Dawn’s association with the distribution of goods is also emphasized in  the last three verses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/080/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/080/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/080/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्रति स्तोमेभिः&amp;rsquo; इति तृचात्मकं दशमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमुषस्यम् । ‘प्रति तृचम् इत्यनुक्रमणिका । प्रातरनुवाकाश्विनशस्त्रयोरुक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;80 (596)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dawn&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This very brief hymn, a mere three verses, sketches the main outlines of Dawn’s  activities, though it has no space to elaborate: her connection with poets and the  morning ritual, her task of revealing the visible world and banishing darkness, and  her connection with the distribution of goods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/081/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/081/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/081/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशायनमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथ षष्ठो व्याख्यायते । सप्तमे मण्डले पञ्चमेऽनुवाके दश सूक्तानि व्याकृतानि।  ‘ प्रत्यु अदर्शि&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचमेकादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षमुषस्यम् । प्रथमाद्या अयुजो बृहत्यो द्वितीयाद्या युजः सतोबृहत्यः । तथा चानुक्रान्तं&amp;mdash;- ‘ प्रत्यु षट् प्रागाथम्&amp;rsquo; इति । प्रातरनुवाक उषस्ये क्रतौ बार्हते छन्दस्याश्विनशस्त्रे चेदं सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash; प्रत्यु अदर्शि सह वामेनेति बार्हतम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ४. १४) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/082/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/082/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/082/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘इन्द्रावरुणा&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं द्वादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं जागतम् । इदमादीनि चत्वारि सूक्तानीन्द्रावरुणदेवतानि । तथा चानुक्रान्तम् - ‘इन्द्रावरुणा, दशैन्द्रावरुणं ह जागतं तु&amp;rsquo; इति । तृतीये सवन उक्थ्ये प्रशास्तुः शस्त्र एतत्सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च -&amp;rsquo; इन्द्रावरुणा युवमा वां राजानौ&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ६. १) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;82 (598)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra and Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is structured into two sections, with the second embedded in the first.  The first is an invocation to Indra and Varuṇa to come to the rite and consists of  verses 1 and 7–10. The second section and the heart of the hymn are verses 2–6,  which describe the two sides of kingship that the two gods represent.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra represents the king ruling during times of migration and conflict; Varuṇa  represents the king ruling during times of settlement, ideally times of peace. In the984 VII.82&lt;br&gt;&#xA;political structure of the Vedic period, different men may have been kings during  these two times or, as we believe more likely, the same king may have exercised these  complementary functions at different times of the year.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 2 the poet calls one of the gods samrā́j “sovereign king” and the other  svarā́j “independent king.” While both terms can be used of both Indra and Varuṇa  (cf. Schlerath 1960:  132–35), samrā́j is used especially frequently of Varuṇa and  the Ādityas (cf. I.25.10; V.63.3, 85.1; VIII.25.7–8, 29.9, 42.1; X.63.5) and svarā́j frequently of Indra (cf. I.61.9; III.45.5; VIII.12.14, 46.28, 61.2, 69.17, 93.11).  Therefore, despite Schlerath’s doubts, the “sovereign king” here is likely Varuṇa  and the “independent king” Indra. Further, at least in this verse, the contrasting  titles likely reflect the distribution of kingly functions between the two gods. Since  the samrā́j governed the peoples and their divisions, he might be connected with  times of settlement. Since the svarā́j was independent of other authority, he might  be associated with times of conflict between separate clans, peoples, and rulers.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;However the relation between svarā́j and samrā́j is to be understood, the poet  insists on the necessity of both kinds of king and both sides of kingship. Indeed,  after contrasting the two gods in verse 2ab, the poet emphasizes their similarity  (2cd) and their united action in ordering the world (3ab). In verse 3cd the actions of  the ritual are blended with the gods’ cosmic functions. The two gods share Soma— here both the ritual drink and the god—who inspires their action and who therefore  metonymically possesses the transforming power, the “cunning” (māyā́), by which  they made the waters swell. The image of swelling waters is then metaphorically  carried over to the hymns, which should likewise swell.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 4 the poet returns to the two periods associated with the two sides of king ship: in 4a the poet and his people are moving in chariots at the time of conflict and  migration; in 4b they are seated at the beginning of the period of settlement. But here,  unlike verse 2ab, the poet does not explicitly distinguish between the two gods. Both  gods are summoned at both times. In verse 5cd, however, he reintroduces their oppo sition by connecting Varuṇa with settlement and Indra with movement. This alterna tion between conjunctions and disjunctions underscores the mutual dependence of  the different sides of kingship and the poet’s insistence that both gods are great.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 6 continues the contrast between Indra and Varuṇa in a fashion similar to  verse 2, although the actions of the gods in 6cd are not entirely clear. Assuming that  6c refers to the action of Indra and possibly to the destruction of Vr̥tra and similar  “obstacles,” then 6d describes the action of Varuṇa. As Renou (EVP VII: 83) notes,  the verb prá √vR̥in 6d is rare, but appears to mean “ward off” the attack of an enemy  (cf. IX.21.2). Unlike the aggressive action of Indra in 6c, the action of Varuṇa is  thus defensive. Perhaps he protects the individual settlements during times of peace  from incursions from enemies who might threaten them. The two gods thus have  complementary functions in their different contexts and the similarity between  them is reflected in the singular ójas “power” (6b) that both possess.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 1 the poet is especially aware that his is not the most elaborate sacrifice  offered, but he asks the gods to ignore what he sees as the overly showy rites of his competitors and to come to his rite. While it may be plainer than other rites, it does  not have the evil intent behind it that those rites have. Returning to this theme in  the latter part of the hymn, verses 7–10, the poet pleads for the attention of Indra  and Varuṇa. In verse 9 he recalls the competition for the gods’ favor and again asks  the gods to hear his words, for his sacrifice will please the gods more than the words  and rites of others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/083/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/083/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/083/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘युवा नरा&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं त्रयोदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं जागतमैन्द्रावरुणम् । ‘युवां नरा&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । आभिप्लविकेषूक्थ्येषु स्तोमवृद्धौ प्रशास्तुरिदं सूक्तमावापार्थम् । सूत्रितं च &amp;mdash; युवां नरा पुनीषे वाम् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ९) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;83 (599)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra and Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn looks back at the Battle of the Ten Kings described in VII.18, in which  the Bharata king Sudās with the help of the Vasiṣṭhas triumphed over an alliance  of ten rulers. This battle was a key moment in Vasiṣṭha history, and the poet recalls  this historic victory in order to extend it into the present. Now warriors allied with  the Vasiṣṭhas are going forth in their quest for cattle (vs. 1). Looking on Indra and  Varuṇa, who are present at the sacrifice, with their minds if not with their eyes and  thinking of their close association with the two gods, the poet and his allies call  upon the gods to help them. The cry to help Sudās in 1d replicates the call to which  the gods responded before and sets the stage for the poet’s recollection of the Ten  Kings’ battle.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 3 the poet re-enters the earlier battle and speaks as if he were part of it  or speaks in the voice of those who were. In the person of the earlier Vasiṣṭha, he  calls for help in the midst of the turmoil of battle. Then in verse 4ab he remembers  that the gods did help Sudās, and in 4cd the poet returns to his present, calling on  Indra and Varuṇa to hear him. Like the earlier Vasiṣṭha, the poet and his people  confront enemies on every side (vs. 5ab), and therefore he calls upon Indra and  Varuṇa to help at the critical time as they did before (5cd). The poet knows that  others summon the gods as well (vs. 6ab), but in verses 6cd–8 he recalls that the  gods chose to help Sudās and Vasiṣṭha and not the other kings and priests. In the  end the sacrifices of these others were inadequate, and in the end the gods were  present at the sacrifice of Vasiṣṭha (vss. 7–8). In verse 9 the poet distinguishes Indra  and Varuṇa for the first and only time in this hymn. While the two gods may have  different functions, both their divine functions apply to the poet’s present situation.  Indra can bring victory to the poet and his people and Varuṇa can defend them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/084/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/084/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/084/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ आ वाम्&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं चतुर्दशं सूक्तं वासिष्ठं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रावरुणम् । अनुक्रान्तं च &amp;mdash;  ‘आ वां पञ्च&amp;rsquo; इति । उक्थ्ये तृतीयसवने मैत्रावरुणशस्त्र इदं सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च - ‘ आ वां राजानाविन्द्रावरुणा मधुमत्तमस्येति याज्या &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ६. १) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;84 (600)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra and Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The theme of rapid and forward movement dominates this hymn. This movement  is marked by the repetition of prá “forth” or “forward” in verses 1c, 3d, 4c, and 5b  and by verbal forms such as invati “speeds” in 2a and -jūtaḥ “hastened” in 3c. The  various kinds of movement involve the proffering of hymns and oblations and the  answering progress of the sacrificers by means of the wealth and offspring they  receive from the gods. There is also movement implied in the “speed” of the rule of  Indra and Varuṇa (2a), which extends high and wide. In verse 2, verbally enclosed  within this description of the extent of their rule (2a, 2d), are the “bonds” of the  two gods (2b) and the anger of Varuṇa (2c), which show the menacing power of the  gods to enforce their rule.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Another characteristic of this hymn is verbal sleight of hand in verses 1 and 4. In  verse 1 the “ghee-rich one” (ghr̥tā́cī) would normally described the sacrificial ladle,  but, as Renou (EVP VII: 85) notes, it can also characterize the dhī́, the “insight”  embodied in the hymn (I.2.7) or the “songs” (gíraḥ, VII.5.5). Because this “ghee-rich  one” is held in the arms of the priests, hearers would think first of the ladle. But  in 1d the “ghee-rich one” goes “by itself” and “in its varying appearance.” These  descriptions would fit the hymn, which flies to the gods with its varied sounds and  words. The final line, therefore, creates for hearers an unexpected redefinition of the  “ghee-rich one” and produces a double image of it as both ladle and hymn. As such,  the “ghee-rich one” represents the “oblations and reverence” offered to the gods in 1b.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Neither the translation nor the interpretation of verse 4cd is secure. The rela tive clause in 4c surely describes Varuṇa, but śū́ra “champion” in 4d is more  likely a description of Indra. So the normal relation between relative and main  clauses suggests that the subject in 4d is Varuṇa (as Sāyaṇa understands it to be),  but the content of 4d suggests that it is Indra. Moreover, there is a word play  between minā́ti “confounds,” which ends 4c, and ámitā “immeasurable,” which  opens 4d. They are not from the same root, although they sound as though they  could be. The words thus create a verbal icon of simultaneous similarity and dif ference. These ambiguities accord with the representation of Varuṇa and Indra  as embodying different sides of kingship, which are nonetheless complementary  and necessary to one other. As we read the lines, therefore, the two gods are  separately characterized, but their separation is undermined by formal features  that efface it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/085/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/085/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/085/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ पुनीषे वाम्&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं पञ्चदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रावरुणम् । पुनीषे&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । आभिप्लविकेषूक्थ्येषु तृतीयसवने स्तोमवृद्धौ प्रशास्तुरिदमावापार्थम् । सूत्रितं च &amp;mdash;  ‘ युवां नरा पुनीषे वाम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ९) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;85 (601)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra and Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poet announces his hymn in the first verse, implicitly comparing it to Agni,  the sacrificial fire. Agni has a “face of ghee,” that is, he is both bright like ghee and  receives oblations of ghee (cf. I.143.7, III.1.18, V.11.1, X.21.7). This prepares for  verse 4, in which the poet asks that Agni be the Hotar of this rite, who will bring  the oblations to Indra and Varuṇa. The last verse is also found as VII.84.5 but is less  thematically connected to this hymn than it is to the previous hymn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/086/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/086/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/086/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;rsquo; धीरा त्वस्य &amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं षोडशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वरुणदेवत्यम्। तथा चानुक्रान्तं- &amp;rsquo; धीराष्टौ वारुणं ह &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;86 (602)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn and the following three hymns (VII.87–89) are justly famous because  they have an unusually intimate tone and because the poet Vasiṣṭha as a literary  creation of the poem emerges as a distinct personality. Jamison (2007:  91–118)  offers a detailed study of the hymns in this group and of the creation of the poet’s  personality. Like the other hymns in this small collection, this poem centers on just  two figures, the poet—Vasiṣṭha according to tradition—and the god Varuṇa, and  Vasiṣṭha speaks personally, even confessionally with Varuṇa. Apparently Vasiṣṭha  has been suffering from some kind of affliction, which, he has been told, is the pun ishment of King Varuṇa for an offense. He begs Varuṇa to accept his offerings and  repentance, to forgive his transgressions, which he says were not intentional (vs. 6),  and to restore him to prosperity and health.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The relationship between Vasiṣṭha and Varuṇa constantly shifts as the hymn  unfolds. The literary strategy of the poem most clearly appears in its use of pro nouns and other markers of person, as Jamison (2007: 96–100) shows in her analysis.  Use of the 3rd person distances the speaker and the object, while addressing another  as “you” is a token of closeness and presence to one another. The poet deploys these  pronouns first to distance Vasiṣṭha and Varuṇa, then to bring them close, and finally  to separate them once again. So in verse 1 Vasiṣṭha is absent because there is no  reference to the speaker, and Varuṇa is distanced by the 3rd singular pronoun asya.  His absence is mitigated only by fact that unaccented asya should be anaphoric and  therefore might point to the previous presence of the god. Otherwise, the relation&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ship between Vasiṣṭha and Varuṇa is completely broken. In verse 2 Vasiṣṭha is present  (1st sg. in each of the four lines), and Varuṇa remains distanced. In verse 3 Vasiṣṭha  is present once again (1st sg.) and Varuṇa is partly present: he is addressed in the  vocative but he is also mentioned in the 3rd person. In verse 4 both Vasiṣṭha (1st sg.)  and Varuṇa (2nd sg.) are present. Then there begins a retreat from their full presence  to one another. In verse 5 Vasiṣṭha is less present (the 1st pl. generalizes rather than  personalizes the speaker) and Varuṇa is present (through the vocative address and  2nd sg. imperative). This verse reverses 3, in which Vasiṣṭha was fully present but  Varuṇa partly present. In verse 6 Vasiṣṭha is distanced (note especially svá “one’s  own,” not “my own”), and Varuṇa is present (through the vocative address). Again this verse reverses 2, in which Vasiṣṭha was present and Varuṇa was distanced. In  verse 7 Vasiṣṭha is present (1st sg.), but Varuṇa is distanced (3rd sg.). This partially  reverses 1 insofar as Vasiṣṭha was absent there but is present here. Varuṇa remains  distanced in both verses 1 and 7. The last verse (8), is a concluding, extra-hymnic  verse, a coda that stands outside the main structure of the hymn.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This analysis also shows the omphalos structure of the hymn. Verse 1 corresponds  to 7, verse 2 to 6, verse 3 to 5, and verse 4 is the center. It is the thematic heart of the  hymn because it is in this verse that the poet and the god are both present and pres ent to one another. It also signifies the determination of Vasiṣṭha, who anticipates  the resolution of his conflict with Varuṇa. Varuṇa will—perhaps even in the sense of  “must”—proclaim what Vasiṣṭha has done, and Vasiṣṭha promises to make amends  to the god to receive the god’s forgiveness. Although the hymn moves away from this  encounter between Vasiṣṭha and Varuṇa, the last verse suggests that the problem has  been resolved. Varuṇa has returned to the distance, but he and Vasiṣṭha now mutually  support one another. Varuṇa has enlightened Vasiṣṭha (vs. 7c), and Vasiṣṭha ritually  serves the god to his greater “wealth,” his power and glory (7d).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 2b the meaning of váruṇe “within Varuṇa” may play on the possible ety mological relation of váruṇa and vratá “commandment.” That is, “within Varuṇa”  has the sense of “under, or in conformity with, the commandment of Varuṇa.”  The poet wants to be no longer at odds with Varuṇa. At the same time the hope  for closeness to the god or even for envelopment by the god, which is suggested in  the phrase, looks forward to the increasing intimacy of Vasiṣṭha and Varuṇa. The  state is both parallel to and contrasts with the situation in verse 6c where the elder  is “within the misdeed of the younger.”&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In verse 4d, we read áva&amp;hellip;īyām, from ava + √yā “make recompense,” instead of  the transmitted but metrically faulty áva&amp;hellip;iyām.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/087/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/087/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/087/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘रदत्पथः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं सप्तदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वारुणम् । अनुक्रान्तं च – रदत्सप्त &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;87 (603)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;On this hymn, see the introduction to the previous hymn and especially Jamison  (2007: 101–3).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The name of Varuṇa occurs in each verse of the hymn, and in verse 4 Varuṇa  himself speaks. Like the previous one, therefore, this hymn has an omphalos  structure, organized around the central verse 4 and the words of the god himself.  In hymns organized around a central verse, that verse is often the key to under&lt;br&gt;&#xA;standing a hymn or the dramatic climax of the hymn, as it is, for example, in the  previous hymn. But sometimes, as here, it is the most enigmatic verse of all. In 4a,  as implied in the translation below, does Varuṇa know that the poet is wise and  therefore will understand his cryptic words? Or does médhira “wise” anticipate  the wisdom that the poet will receive from Varuṇa’s words? In that case, we might  rather say that Varuṇa spoke “to me (to make me) wise”? As Jamison (2007: 102– 3) argues, the ambiguous placement of ná in 4c allows it to be taken either as a  particle of comparison (“like”) or as a negation (“not”). As a result the pāda  can mean either “he will speak (their names) like secrets,” that is, he will speak  the names but he will do so only in a cryptic manner, or “he will not speak their  secret (names),” that is, he will keep the secrets hidden. But most of all, there are  the obscure words of the god in 4b: “The inviolable cow bears three times seven names.” As often, the “cow” in this verse is speech (e.g., Thompson 1995: 20),  and it is speech, or more specifically this hymn, that carries within it twenty-one  “names.” These names may be similar to the three times seven “tracks” (padā́) in  I.72.6, although these tracks too are also “secret” (gúhyāni) and therefore their  reference unclear.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;There is one possible clue to the twenty-one names in the following verse. Verse  5 mentions three heavens and three earths “arranged in six” or “arranged in sixes.”  That is, “six” could refer to the three heavens and three earths, and, if so, we should  translate, “Three heavens are hidden within him, and below are three earths, form&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ing an arrangement of six.” On the other hand, if ṣáḍvidhānāḥ refers only to the  three earths and if each of the three earths is arranged in six, then we would have  eighteen earths and three heavens, which gives twenty-one, the number of “names.”  In that case, the “names” might be tokens of the extent of Varuṇa’s rule.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Returning again to verse 4, its last mystery is the “later generation” in 4d,  which may refer not to a future generation of human beings but to humans as the  “generation” of beings later than the gods. If so, then Varuṇa strives to instruct  humans despite their limited capacities, perhaps well illustrated in our attempts to  understand him.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;While verse 4 is the most enigmatic in the hymn, it is not the only mysterious  one. We have already touched on the riddle of three heavens and three earths of  verse 5ab. In verse 6a Varuṇa is like the sky, which drops to the horizon at the far  distance where there is the river that surrounds the earth. Because he is like the sky  that drops toward this river, he is called a wild animal (6b) that comes down to the  water to drink and he is like the “bright drop,” which, as Geldner points out, might  be the setting moon or sun or even the soma as it sinks into the waters with which  it is mixed. In 6c Varuṇa is “of deep recitation.” The primary sense is probably that  Varuṇa speaks profound words, but the compound is ambiguous and could also  mean that Varuṇa inspires or receives profound praise-recitations. Verse 7 connects  this hymn to the previous hymn and provides a persuasive reason to link the two  hymns, as Jamison (2007: 103) has noted. In VII.86.2 the poet asks, “When shall  I be within Varuṇa?” Here in verse 7 the poet gives an answer: when we are free of  offense, then “we would be within Varuṇa.” That is, we would be in conformity with  the vratā́ny áditeḥ “the commandments of Aditi,” the goddess representing offense lessness, whose commandments are mentioned in 7c.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/088/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/088/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/088/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र शुन्ध्युवम्&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चमष्टादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वारुणम् । ‘प्र शुन्ध्युवम्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;88 (604)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This intricate and justly admired hymn has been widely anthologized and stud ied. See especially the treatment of the hymn in Jamison (2007: 103–8) and Lüders  (1951: 315–21). It is closely related to the two preceding hymns and likewise con cerns the relationship between Vasiṣṭha and Varuṇa, delineating it in perhaps the  most intimate fashion of any of these hymns.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha speaks for himself in these verses, even though he begins in verse 1 by  addressing himself in the vocative. Once again, the theme of the poem is the distance  between Vasiṣṭha and Varuṇa that has been created by something that Vasiṣṭha has  done. That Vasiṣṭha addresses himself in the 2nd person perhaps suggests not only  his distance from the god but even, as a result, from himself. The meaning of this  becomes clearer as the poem develops. In verse 2 Vasiṣṭha approaches the ritual fire  during the night and in the face of fire sees the face of Varuṇa. This results in a  vision of Vasiṣṭha and Varuṇa sailing together (vs. 3). Their goal is Varuṇa’s “swing,”  which, as in VII.87.5, is probably the sun, which Vasiṣṭha hopes will dispel the dark ness that surrounds him and his relationship with Varuṇa. This vision takes Vasiṣṭha  back to the time when he and Varuṇa were close (vs. 4), when Varuṇa made Vasiṣṭha  a seer (ŕ̥ṣi) and praise singer (stotár). The light imagery is most intense in this verse, for the day Vasiṣṭha became a seer and praise singer was the “brightest day of days.”  This memory of a time of perfect harmony between Vasiṣṭha and Varuṇa is the dra matic and emotional climax of the hymn and not surprisingly occupies the central&lt;br&gt;&#xA;verse of the hymn, which like the two previous hymns has an omphalos structure. In verse 5 Vasiṣṭha returns from his vision and memory of better times to the  unhappy present, in which he is no longer in the household of Varuṇa. But in verse  6 he continues to hope that, despite what he has done, the god will not hold his  offenses against him, and will again offer him the protection that he once enjoyed  within the house of Varuṇa. The poet keeps these offenses distant from himself by  talking about the offender in the 3rd person (in 6ab), but then he refers to those  who bear the guilt of those offenses in the 1st person (in 6c). Finally, in verse 7 the  poet more confidently looks to Varuṇa’s forgiveness: he “will release his fetter” of  punishment “from us.” As Jamison (2007: 107) has pointed out, both pādas a and  c have present participles for which there is no grammatically appropriate noun.  Logically they should describe “us”—and that logic is reflected in the translation— but the absence of an explicit reference to us generalizes that happy result and the  possibility of reconciliation with the god.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/089/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/089/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/089/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;मो षु वरुण&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चमेकोनविंशं सूक्तं वारुणम् । अन्त्या जगती शिष्टाश्चतस्रो गायत्र्यः । तथा चानुक्रान्तं &amp;ndash; मो षु पञ्च गायत्रं जगत्यन्तम् &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;89 (605)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Varuṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: gāyatrī 1–4, jagatī 5&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As Oldenberg remarks, although this hymn does not break the sequence of verse  numbers and meter, it appears to be an addition to this Varuṇa collection. It is in  another meter, and Vasiṣṭha does not appear by name within it. Moreover, while  the other three hymns of this collection refer to Vasiṣṭha’s unhappy state, this hymn  more explicitly concerns an illness afflicting the speaker. It is an illness so serious  that it could bring the speaker to the mr̥nmáyaṃ gr̥hám “house of clay” (vs. 1), the  earth, in which the dead are buried.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;According to both indigenous commentators and contemporary schol ars, the illness especially associated with Varuṇa is dropsy, on which see Zysk  (1985: 59–61). The reference in verse 2 to the speaker as “inflated like a water-skin”  could point to dropsy, as could prasphuránn iva, here translated “seeming to  kick,” if it is interpreted as stumbling or as describing the water-skin as quiver ing. But the evidence is not very firm.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The last verse, which is in a different meter, brings the hymn closer to the preced ing three hymns, since it lays the blame for the speaker’s condition on a violation of  the commandments of Varuṇa, his dhármā “ordinances.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/090/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/090/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/090/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;षष्ठेऽनुवाके पञ्चदश सूक्तानि । तत्र ‘प्र वीरया&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं प्रथमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वायव्यम्। यासु पञ्चम्याद्यासु द्विवचनमस्ति ता ऐन्द्रवायव्यः । तथा चानुक्रान्तं - प्र वीरया सप्त वायव्यं ह्यैन्द्र्यश्च या द्विवदुक्ताः&amp;rsquo; इति ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तृतीये छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्रे ‘प्र वीरया&amp;rsquo; इति वायव्यस्तृचः । सूत्रितं च - प्र वीरया शुचयो दद्रिरे वां ते सत्येन मनसा दीध्यानाः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ११) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;90 (606)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vāyu (1–4), Indra and Vāyu (5–7)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The split dedication to Vāyu, then Indra and Vāyu reflects the ritual fact noted  often elsewhere, that the first offerings of soma at the Morning Pressing are made  to Vāyu alone and then to Indra and Vāyu jointly. This ritual purpose is announced  quite clearly in the first verse, and, as often in Vāyu hymns, the invitation is followed  by the god’s journey to the sacrifice. As often also in Vāyu hymns the poet makes  productive use of the ambiguity between Vāyu’s “teams,” his wind-horses (see vs.  3), and ours, the poetic thought we deploy, and in verse 5 the priests and poets actu&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ally become the horses that pull the chariot of the two gods.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As befits the early morning setting of the ritual, Dawn is prominent in the hymn  (vss. 3–4), with the latter verse alluding obliquely to the Vala myth associated with  the primal dawn. The distribution of gifts and goods appropriate to the early morn ing ritual is also prominent. In the early verses 2 and 3 there is promise of benefits  for the sacrificer from the gods, a promise that in the last two verses (6–7) is actually  fulfilled by the gifts made by the human patrons of the sacrifice. Indeed the patrons  seem to be partly assimilated to the gods: they have the power to confer not only  goods but sunlight itself (see vs. 6), and they share with the gods the repeated par ticiple īśāná “having dominion over,” said of Vāyu in verse 2, of Indra and Vāyu in  verse 5, and of the patrons in verse 6.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/091/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/091/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/091/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘कुविदङ्ग&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वायव्यम्। ‘कुविदङ्ग&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः । वायव्ये पशौ ‘कुविदङ्ग&amp;rsquo; इति वपाया याज्या । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; ‘ कुविदङ्ग नमसा ये वृधास ईशानाय प्रहुतिं यस्त आनट्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ३. ८) इति&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;91 (607)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vāyu (1, 3), Indra and Vāyu (2, 4–7)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The last half of this hymn (vss. 4cd through 7, the last verse being repeated from  VII.90.7) is a straightforward invitation to Indra and Vāyu to journey to the sacri fice, bringing goods to distribute, and to drink the soma. The first half of the hymn  is both more miscellaneous and more obscurely phrased. True, verse 2 also issues  the invitation to the two gods, but it is sandwiched between two verses with which it  seems to have little in common.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 1 is variously interpreted, with its parts variously arranged in translation.  In our interpretation it contains speculation about the prior existence of the gods  and the beginning of ritual activity: the gods who now derive their strength from  men’s sacrifices must have existed before the sacrifice began, the proof being that  these gods created the dawn and the sun for both Vāyu, a god of the midspace, and  for Manu, the first man and first sacrificer, under trying conditions. (A somewhat  similar situation is depicted in VI.49.13, where Viṣṇu measures out the realms for  “hard-pressed Manu,” another cosmogonic deed.) The creation of dawn would in  turn allow the ritual process, the ritual day, to begin—and begin it does with the  offering to Vāyu. Verse 3 is clearly a depiction of the sacrifice, but the referents of the  various phrases are not entirely certain. Although most scholars consider Vāyu the  subject of the first half-verse, on the basis of shared vocabulary we instead consider  it a disguised reference to the soma and its usual accompaniment, cow’s milk. The  soma drops then offer themselves to Vāyu. The first half of verse 4 complements the  concerns in verse 1: in the first verse the time before the creation of the sacrifice by  the gods is the subject of speculation; in 4ab the unbounded continuance of the sac rifice is envisioned, for as long as men have the power to perform it. With these ends  of the sacrifice demarcated, the offering to Indra and Vāyu in the here-and-now can  proceed, and the simple invitation of the rest of the hymn is issued to them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/092/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/092/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/092/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ वायो&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वायव्यम् । अनुक्रान्तं च &amp;mdash; ‘ आ वायो पञ्च &amp;rsquo; इति । शुनासीरीये पर्वणि वायोर्नियुत्वतो यागस्य ‘आ वायो &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुवाक्या । सूत्रितं च &amp;mdash; आ वायो भूष शुचिपा उप नः प्र याभिर्यासि दाश्वांसमच्छ &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. २.२० ) इति । नियुत्वद्वायुदेवताके पशावेषैव वपाया अनुवाक्या ( आश्व. श्रौ. ३. ८)। प्रथमे छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्रे वायव्यतृचस्यैषैवाद्या । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; समुद्रादूर्मिरित्याज्यमा वायो भूष शुचिपाः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८.९) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/093/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/093/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/093/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;शुचिं नु &amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं चतुर्थं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्राग्नम् । अनुक्रम्यते हि - शुचिं न्वष्टावैन्द्राग्नं तु &amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः । ऐन्द्राग्नस्य पशोर्वपायाः ‘ शुचिम् &amp;rsquo; इत्येषा याज्या। सूत्रितं च - शुचिं नु स्तोमं नवजातमद्य गीभिर्विप्रः प्रमतिमिच्छमानः &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ३. ७) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;93 (609)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra and Agni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first six verses of this hymn, though they contain numerous examples of dual  address of and reference to Indra and Agni together, are strongly skewed toward  Indra. The two gods are called “smiters of Vr̥tra” (vss. 1, 4) and “possessors of  good maces” (Indra’s weapon; vs. 4); they “smite” (Indra’s activity) the enemy (vs.  5) and “drive” to the sacrifice (vs. 6; since Agni is kindled on the ritual ground, he  has no need to drive to it). Moreover the theme is the winning of prizes (vā́ja) and  their distribution, and the besting of opponents: this agonistic cast is more typical  of Indra than of Agni. The last two verses (7–8) are addressed to Agni only, in his  familiar ritual role, mediating between the sacrificer and the gods, including Indra.  But even in these verses Agni’s own character is overlaid with that of other gods: for  instance, in verse 7 he seems to be assimilated to Varuṇa and the other Ādityas in  forgiving offenses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/094/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/094/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/094/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘इयं वाम् &amp;rsquo; इति द्वादशर्चं पञ्चमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षमैन्द्राग्नम् । द्वादश्यनुष्टुप् शिष्टा गायत्र्यः । तथा चानुकान्तम् - इयं वां द्वादश गायत्रमन्त्यानुष्टुप् &amp;rsquo; इति । ज्योतिष्टोमे प्रातःसवनेऽच्छावाकशस्त्र आदितो नवर्चः शस्यन्ते । सूत्र्यते हि &amp;ndash; इयं वामस्य मन्मन इति नव &amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ५.१०) इति । आभिप्लविकेषूक्थ्येषु स्तोमेषु वृद्धावच्छावाकस्य प्रातःसवन इदं सूक्तमावापार्थमुत्तमावर्जम् । सूत्रितं च &amp;ndash; ‘इयं वामस्य मन्मन इत्येकादश&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ५) इति । चातुर्विंशिकेऽहनि प्रातःसवने तस्यैवाद्यस्तृचः । सूत्रितं च  &amp;ndash; इयं वामस्य मन्मन इन्द्राग्नी युवामिमे&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. २ ) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/095/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/095/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/095/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र क्षोदसा&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं षष्ठं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं सरस्वतीदेवताकम् । तृतीया तु सरस्वद्देवताका । अनुक्रम्यते च -– प्र क्षोदसा षट् सारस्वतं तु तृतीया सरस्वते&amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः । प्रथमे छन्दोमे प्रउगशस्त्रे ‘प्र क्षोदसा धायसा सस्र एषेति प्रउगम्&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ८. ९) इति । सारस्वते पशौ ‘प्र क्षोदसा&amp;rsquo; इति वपाया याज्या। सूत्रितं च- प्र क्षोदसा धायसा सस्र एषा पावीरवी कन्या चित्रायुः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ३. ७) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/096/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/096/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/096/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘बृहदु गायिषे &amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं सप्तमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षम् । आद्या बृहती द्वितीया सतोबृहती तृतीया प्रस्तारपङ्क्तिः शिष्टास्तिस्रो गायत्र्यः । आद्यस्तृचः सरस्वतीदेवताकोऽन्त्यश्च सरस्वद्देवताकः । तथा चानुक्रान्तं&amp;ndash; बृहदु प्रगाथः प्रस्तारपङ्क्तिः परास्तिस्रो गायत्र्यः सरस्वते &amp;rsquo; इति । पञ्चमेऽहनि प्रउगशस्त्र आद्यः प्रगाथः सारस्वतस्तृचः । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash; बृहदु गायिष&amp;rsquo; इति बार्हतं प्रउगं प्रगाथानेके । ( आश्व. श्रौ. ७. १२ ) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;96 (612)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Sarasvatı (1–3), Sarasvant (4–6) ̄&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: br̥hatī 1, satobr̥hatī 2, prastārapaṅkti 3, as extended pragātha; gāyatrī 4–6,  as trcḁ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is not metrically unified (see Oldenberg 1888: 200). The first three verses,  dedicated to Sarasvatī, consist of a pragātha (vss. 1–2) of the usual type (br̥hatī alter nating with satobr̥hatī), extended with a third verse in prastārapaṅkti (12 12 8 8). The1004 VII.96&lt;br&gt;&#xA;other three verses form a conventional tr̥ca, dedicated to Sarasvant, whose charac ter seems little different from his better-known counterpart Sarasvatī. It is perhaps  the identity of the “bachelors” in verse 4 that suggests that prayer to a male divinity  would be appropriate. But the attribution of a “swelling breast” to this same male  in verse 6 is distinctly odd; a nourishing, wealth-giving breast (using the same word  stána) for suckling is attributed in I.164.49 to Sarasvatī, a more suitable figure by  her gender.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The phrase “both stalks” (ubhé . . . ándhasī) in verse 2 has occasioned much  discussion, and in recent years some political and military conclusions have  been drawn from one quite speculative interpretation of it—conclusions not  justified by the evidence, in our opinion. Although most interpreters take the  “two stalks” as referring to two different beverages, one of which is soma (the  usual referent of singular ándhas is the soma stalk), either soma and surā or  soma and milk, some, following Grassmann, interpret the word as referring  metaphorically to the two banks of the river. From this interpretation it is  inferred that the Pūrus crossed the Sarasvatī and conquered the territory on the  other side—a conclusive leap based on a shaky interpretation of this word. By  contrast, we interpret the term on the basis of the twinned hymn VII.95, whose  corresponding verse 2 states that Sarasvatī “milked out ghee and milk,” a liquid  pairing that may well be referred to by the dual in verse 2 of this immediately  following hymn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/097/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/097/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/097/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘यज्ञे दिवः&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चमष्टमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभम् । प्रथमैन्द्री तृतीयानवम्योरिन्द्राब्रह्मणस्पती देवता दशम्या इन्द्राबृहस्पती शिष्टानां तु बृहस्पतिः । तथा चानुक्रान्तं - यज्ञे दशैन्द्र्यादि बार्हस्पत्यमन्त्यैन्द्री च तृतीयानवम्यावैन्द्राब्राह्मणस्पत्ये&amp;rsquo; इति। आभिप्लविकेषूक्थ्येषु तृतीयसवने स्तोमवृद्धौ ब्राह्मणाच्छंसिन इदमुत्तरं च सूक्तमावापार्थम् । सूत्रितं च–“यज्ञे दिवः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ७. ९) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;97 (613)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra (1), Br̥haspati (2, 4–8), Indra and&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Brahmaṇaspati (3, 9), Indra and Br̥haspati (10)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;According to the Anukramaṇī (whose identifications are reproduced here in the  heading) there is a wide array of divine dedicands for the individual verses of this  hymn: Indra alone, Br̥haspati alone, Indra and Br̥haspati, and Indra and the more  transparently named Brahmaṇaspati (“Lord of the Sacred Formulation”). The  hymn is more carefully structured than the random listing would suggest, however.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;First, as has often been discussed above, Hanns-Peter Schmidt (1968) has shown  that Br̥haspati was originally an epithet of Indra in his priestly role and only gradu ally split off into a separate god. As in IV.50 this divine history is recapitulated in  part in the progress of this hymn, though in a different way from the earlier hymn.  For most of the hymn only one of the divine figures is on stage at a time: verse  1 has Indra, verse 2 Br̥haspati, and Br̥haspati holds sway in verses 4–8. Even in  verse 3, supposedly dedicated to both Indra and Brahmaṇaspati, the two are not  depicted together, and in fact the phraseology seems designed to identify Indra as  Brahmaṇaspati: the two-word phrase bráhmaṇas pátim “lord of the sacred formula&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tion” in pāda b is, it seems, paraphrased with the defining relative clause of d, refer ring to Indra: yó bráhmaṇaḥ &amp;hellip;rā́jā “who is king of the sacred formulation,” with  “king” substituting for “lord,” thus superimposing the one on the other. What we  are claiming here, then, is that in verses 1–8 the divine names Indra and Br̥haspati/ Brahmaṇaspati refer to a single divine figure, Indra.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;But when the transparent designation Brahmaṇaspati recurs in verse 9, it is  immediately preceded by the dual pronoun vām “you two”; there must therefore  now be two divine addressees, and the split between Indra and his epithet has been  effected. The last two verses (9–10) call upon them both, using dual verbs, pro&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nouns, and vocatives quite insistently. It is because we consider bráhmaṇas páti- an  epithet in verse 3 and a divine name in verse 9 that we have translated them differ ently in the two verses. Notice also that Brahmaṇaspati, as opposed to Br̥haspati, is&lt;br&gt;&#xA;only found in verses also containing the noun bráhman “sacred formulation.” But the hymn has another divine presence, not named but clearly there, who  complicates the identity problem even more. The entire hymn is set on the ritual  ground; this scene is set at the very beginning, in verse 1, starting with the word  yajñé “at the sacrifice” and continuing with a clear depiction of the locus of ritual  offerings, where men and gods (including Indra) meet. But, in the middle verses  mentioning only Br̥haspati (4–8), that god is described in ways extremely suggestive  of Agni, the ritual fire: he sits on the womb (vs. 4); he is both bright and roaring (vs.  5), bright, golden, and good to enter (vs. 7), and most clearly, in the image of verse  6 he is dark below but possessed of horses like ruddy clouds. All of this phraseol ogy has clear counterparts in descriptions of Agni. Thus, the divine figure Indra/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/098/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/098/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/098/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘अध्वर्यवः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं नवमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभमैन्द्रं सप्तम्यैन्द्राबार्हस्पत्या । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्- अध्वर्यवः सप्तोक्तदेवतान्त्या&amp;rsquo; इति । पूर्वसूक्तेन सहोक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;98 (614)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Indra (1–6), Indra and Br̥haspati (7)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This is really an Indra hymn; the final verse dedicated to Indra and Br̥haspati (vs.  7) is simply repeated from the previous hymn (VII.97.10). The theme of the rest of  the hymn is Indra’s close affinity with and unslakable desire for soma. Not only is  it the regular ritual offering that he seeks daily (vss. 1–2), but it belonged to him  from birth (vs. 3) and became his special substance after his first victories (vs. 5).  The deeds and power of Indra are also celebrated. Intriguingly, his mother first  proclaims his greatness (vs. 3): the mention of Indra’s mother, especially in connec&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tion with soma, always tantalizingly alludes to apparently fraught family dynamics  associated with Indra’s birth (see III.48 and IV.18). Verse 5, near the end of the  hymn, repeats the proclamation of his deeds, using the formula sometimes found  and expected at the beginning of a hymn (see, e.g., I.32.1, I.154.1), though not rare  later in the unfolding of the poem.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poet, of course, wishes to profit from the battle-might soma inspires in  Indra (vs. 4) and receive some of the spoils of his victories (vs. 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/099/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/099/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/099/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘परो मात्रया &amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं दशमं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभम्। &amp;lsquo;उरुं यज्ञाय &amp;rsquo; इत्याद्यास्तिस्र ऐन्द्रावैष्णव्यः शिष्टाः केवलविष्णुदेवताकाः। तथा चानुक्रान्तं &amp;ndash; परो वैष्णवं तूरुमित्यैन्द्र्यश्च तिस्रः &amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः । विष्णुदेवताके पशौ ‘परो मात्रया&amp;rsquo; इति पुरोडाशस्य याज्या । सूत्रितं च - परो मात्रया तन्वा वृधानेरावती धेनुमती हि भूतम्&amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ३. ८) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;99 (615)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Viṣṇu (1–3, 7), Indra and Viṣṇu (4–6)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As has been discussed previously, Viṣṇu, one of the great gods of classical Hinduism,  is a marginal figure in the R̥gveda, generally associated with Indra. Viṣṇu’s primary  mythic exploit in Vedic is the “three strides” he made across the cosmos, measuring  out, enlarging, and mapping the cosmic spaces. In middle Vedic literature and later,  Viṣṇu takes the form of a dwarf when making these vast strides, but there is no trace  of this notion in the R̥gveda.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first three verses of this hymn are addressed solely to Viṣṇu and allude to his  establishment and fixation of the cosmic spaces, though without directly mention ing his three strides. The first verse does sketch (in the second half) the three sepa rate realms with which Viṣṇu is associated, an indirect reference to the three strides;  but in verses 2 and 3 the action that creates the spaces is “propping,” an action  more characteristic of Indra. However, in verse 3 Viṣṇu fastens the earth down  with “loom pegs,” a homely device in a way. The word (mayū́kha) is found only one  other time in the R̥gveda, in verse 2 of the late hymn X.130, where the creation of  the sacrifice is likened to weaving. This verse is also noteworthy for Viṣṇu’s direct  address to Heaven and Earth as he props them apart.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The second three verses (4–6) are dedicated to Indra and Viṣṇu together, and  though heroic deeds are attributed to both of them, the deeds themselves are ones  assigned only to Indra elsewhere (e.g., the destruction of Śambara and of Varcin in  vs. 5). It is not unusual in hymns addressed to dual divinities for the more dynamic  mythology of one to be credited to both.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The final verse is dedicated to Viṣṇu alone (Śipiviṣṭa being an enigmatic epithet  of Viṣṇu found in the R̥gveda only in this and the following hymn), though the sen timents of the verse are conventional. For further on the epithet, see the next hymn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१००</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/100/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/100/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/100/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘नू मर्तः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चमेकादशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं वैष्णवम् । &amp;lsquo;नू मर्तः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्थ्ये अच्छावाकशस्त्र इदं शंसनीयम् । सूत्रितं च - ‘ ऋतुर्जनित्री नू मर्तो भवा मित्रः &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ६. १) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;100 (616)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Viṣṇu&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins conventionally enough, with a mortal offering sacrifice to the god  (vs. 1) and a request for gifts in return (vs. 2). Viṣṇu’s three strides are the subject  of the following two, responsive verses (3–4). Verse 3d also introduces the theme  of Viṣṇu’s name, which is the subject of the last two real verses of the hymn (5–6,  since vs. 7 is merely a repetition of the final verse of VII.99). The enigmatic epithet  śipiviṣṭá found in the last verse of the last hymn (VII.99.7) is, as it were, interrogated  in these verses. In verse 6 the poet, who boasts that he knows the hidden patterns,  sets out to proclaim the god’s name, while addressing him as Śipiviṣṭa, and then  asks in the next verse whether the god’s own proclamation of himself as Śipiviṣṭa  was meant to be ignored or passed over. The poet then mysteriously alludes to two  different forms of the god, which may (or may not) correspond to two different  names. The hymn does not resolve these questions, perhaps leaving the shadowy  figure of Viṣṇu to be fully developed in the ensuing centuries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/101/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/101/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/101/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्थ निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथ सप्तमो व्याख्यायते । सप्तममण्डलस्य षष्ठेऽनुवाक एकादश सूक्तानि व्याख्यातानि ।  ‘ तिस्रो वाचः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं द्वादशं सूक्तम् । अत्रानुक्रम्यते &amp;ndash; ‘ तिस्रः षट् पार्जन्यं तु &amp;rsquo; इति । एते कुमार आग्नेयोऽपश्थद्वसिष्ठ एव वा &amp;rsquo; इति वक्ष्यमाणत्वादग्निपुत्रः कुमार ऋषिर्वसिष्ठो वा । अनुक्तत्वात् त्रिष्टुप् । इदमुत्तरं च पर्जन्यदेवत्यम् । अत्र शौनकः &amp;ndash; आस्यदघ्नं विगाह्यापः प्राङ्मुखः प्रयतः शुचिः । सूक्ताभ्यां तिस्र आदिभ्यामुपतिष्ठेत भास्करम् ॥ अनश्नतैतज्जप्तव्यं वृष्टिकामेन यत्नतः । पञ्चरात्रेऽप्यतिक्रान्ते महतीं वृष्टिमाप्नुयात् ॥&amp;rsquo; (ऋग्वि. २. ३२६-२७) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/102/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/102/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/102/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘पर्जन्याय&amp;rsquo; इति तृचं त्रयोदशं सूक्तं गायत्रम् । पूर्ववदृषिदेवते । तथा चानुक्रान्तं - पर्जन्याय तृचं गायत्रम्&amp;rsquo; इति । वैश्वानरपार्जन्यायामन्वारम्भणीयायां पार्जन्यस्य चरोः ‘ पर्जन्याय &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुवाक्या । सूत्र्यते हि - ‘ पर्जन्याय प्र गायत प्र वाता वान्ति पतयन्ति विद्युतः &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. २. १५) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;102 (618)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Parjanya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kumāra Āgneya or Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As simple and straightforward an address to Parjanya as the preceding hymn was  cryptic and complex.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/103/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/103/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/103/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;rsquo; संवत्सरम् &amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं चतुर्दशं सूक्त वसिष्ठस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभम् । आद्या त्वनुष्टुप् । मण्डूका देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- संवत्सरं दश पर्जन्यस्तुतिः संहृष्टान्मण्डूकांस्तुष्टावाद्यानुष्टुप् &amp;rsquo; इति । वृष्टिकामेनैतत्सूक्तं जप्यम् ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;103 (619)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Frogs&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: triṣṭubh, except anuṣṭubh 1&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A rain charm, which cleverly matches accurate description of frogs noisily emerging  from estivation and mating at the beginning of the rainy season with the behavior  of priests at a particular ritual, the Pravargya (see esp. vss. 7–9). Although there  has been much debate about whether this hymn satirizes priests by comparing them  to frogs or instead is to be taken with deadly seriousness, the truth no doubt lies  somewhere in between. The poet obviously took great delight in his skill at match&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ing frog behavior with ritual behavior and is unlikely to have been unaware of the  potentially comic aspects of the comparison; however, the explosive fertility of the  frogs provides a model for similar increase in the human sphere, and therefore the  comparison has a serious purpose.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Attention to modern studies of animal behavior allows us to see just how  much careful observation of frogs lies behind the depiction of the frogs here, and  understanding anuran mating habits deepens our understanding of the poem. (See  Jamison 1993.) For example, the frog lying “like a dried-out leather bag” is a coun&lt;br&gt;&#xA;terintuitively accurate representation of a frog in estivation: some really do go dor mant and dry up during the dry season, and “adding water” plumps them up and  revives them. Once revived, the chorus of frogs begins, the purpose of which is to  draw female frogs to the males, who are vocalizing, for mating. This antiphonal  chorus is described in verses 2–6. Since the calls of different species are quite dis tinctive (as sketched in vs. 6), the different cries serve to attract conspecific females  to the appropriate male. The actual mating posture of frogs is described in verse  4: it involves the male approaching the female from behind and grasping her firmly  for as long as it takes—which for some species can be quite awhile (days or weeks).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Another important aspect of the hymn is its comparison of the frog chorus to  a pedagogical situation (see esp. vss. 3, 5), in which the father/teacher speaks and  the pupils exactly repeat his utterance. This is the clearest and earliest depiction of  pedagogy in ancient India and is an example of how our knowledge of everyday  life at that time must be obliquely won. The most famous word in this hymn is  found in verse 3, the phonologically aberrant akhkhala (underlying the so-called  cvi-formation, akhkhalī-[kŕ̥tya]). On the one hand, it would take a very austere  interpreter, and a killjoy, not to recognize this as an onomatopoetic imitation of a  froggy sound; on the other hand, in the inspired analysis of Paul Thieme (1954),  this is, in Middle Indic guise, a representation of the word akṣara “syllable.” What  the frog pupils are doing is “making syllables,” that is, repeating the utterance of  the teacher verbatim, as sound, not meaning. This is a pedagogical technique that  endures to this day in traditional Vedic learning. It is also telling that the word  akhkhala is in Middle Indic form, as the everyday language of the R̥gvedic poets,  and especially of their wives and children, had most likely already undergone many of the phonological and morphological changes characteristic of Middle Indic, but  only found in preserved texts from a much later period. Instruction of the young,  as well as most ordinary conversation, was no doubt carried out in this language  rather than in the high Vedic Sanskrit of the hymns.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As for the ritual application, the Pravargya rite occurs after a year-long con secration, like that referred to in verse 1 and brought to an end in verses 7–9. The  most salient feature of the Pravargya is the offering of the gharma drink, referred to  specifically in verses 8–9, the heated milk-offering that boils until it overflows. The  last, and most important, implicit comparison between frogs and priests turns on  this ritual offering: the prodigious discharge of eggs after anuran mating, especially  by many pairs simultaneously, must have reminded the poet of the frothy bubbling  overflow of the boiling milk. And since the thousands of eggs released are a tan gible sign of fertility and increase, the frogs are seen as assuring increase for us as  well, in the final verse (10), culminating in the “Pressing of Thousands.”&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Oldenberg suggests that that this hymn was added at this point in the Maṇḍala,  just after the two Parjanya hymns (VII.101–2), because of the presence of Parjanya  in the first verse. It is certainly appropriate for the rainy season.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/104/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/07/104/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/07/104/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘इन्द्रासोमा&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चविंशत्यृचं पञ्चदशं सूक्तं वसिष्ठस्यार्षम् । आद्याः षट् जगत्यः सप्तमी जगती त्रिष्टुब्वाष्टादश्येकविंशीत्रयोविंश्यो जगत्योऽन्त्या प्रति चक्ष्व&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुष्टुप् शिष्टाश्चतुर्दश त्रिष्टुभः । नवमीद्वादशीत्रयोदश्यः सोमदेवत्या एकादशी देवदेवत्याष्टमीषोडश्याविन्द्रदेवताके सप्तदशी ग्रावदेवत्याष्टादशी मरुद्देवताका दशमीचतुर्दश्यावग्निदेवताके ‘प्र वर्तय&amp;rsquo; इत्याद्याः पञ्चर्च इन्द्रदेवताकाः । ‘मा नो रक्ष&amp;rsquo; इति त्रयोविंश्याः पूर्वोऽर्धर्चो वसिष्ठस्य प्रार्थनापरः । अतस्तद्देवताकः । उत्तरोऽर्धर्चः पृथिव्यन्तरिक्षदेवत्यः । शिष्टानां रक्षोहणाविन्द्रासोमौ देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्’ &amp;ndash; इन्द्रासोमा पञ्चाधिकैन्द्रासोमं राक्षोघ्नं शापाभिशापप्रायं षट् सप्त वाद्या जगत्य एकविंशीत्रयोविंश्यौ चाष्टादशी मारुती च दशमीचतुर्दश्यावाग्नेय्यौ दैव्येकादश्यन्त्यानुष्टुन्नवमी द्वादशी त्रयोदशी सौम्यः सप्तदशी ग्राव्ण्यष्टमीषोळश्यावैन्द्र्यौ प्र वर्तयेति पञ्चैन्द्र्यो मा नो रक्ष इत्यृषेरात्मन आशीरुत्तरोऽर्धर्चः पृथिव्यन्तरिक्षदेवतः&amp;rsquo; इति । अत्र बृहद्देवतायामनुक्रम्यते- संवत्सरं तु मण्डूकानैन्द्रासोमं परं तु यत् ॥ ऋषिर्ददर्श रक्षोघ्नं पुत्रशोकपरिप्लुतः । हते पुत्रशते क्रुद्धः सौदासैर्दुःखितस्तदा ॥ (बृहद्दे. ६. २७-२८) इति । अतो रक्षोनिबर्हणार्थमेतत्सूक्तं जप्यम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
