<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST CHAPTER (ADHYAYA).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The Dikṣaniya Iṣti, with the Initiatory Rites.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Agni, among the gods, has the lowest, Viṣnu the highest, place; between them stand all the other deities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sā yana, whom M. Muller follows in his translation of the first six chapters of the first book, as given in his “History of Ancient Sanskrit Literature&amp;quot; (pages 390-405), explains the words avama and parama by * first&amp;quot; and &amp;ldquo;last.&amp;rdquo; To prove this meaping to be the true one, Sāyana adduces the mantra (1.4. Asyal. Sr. S. 4, 2), agmir mulcham prathamo devatanim samgatánam uttamo Viṣnur asït, i.e., Agui was the first of the deities assembled, (and) Viṣnu the last. In the Kauṣitaki-Brāhmanam (7, 1) Agni is called avarárdhya (instead of avama), and Viṣgu parárdhya (instead of parana), n.e., belonging to the lower and higher halves (or forming the lower and higher halves). That the meaning &amp;ldquo;first” cannot be reasonably given to the word avama, one nay learn from some passages of the Rigveda Samhita, where avana and purama are pot applied to denote rank and dignity, but only to mark place and locality. See Rigveda 1, 108, 9, 10 : avarasyám prithiūyám, madhyamasyan, para musyam uta, i.e., in he lowest place, the middle (place), and the highest (place). Agni, the fire, has, among she gods, the lowest place ; for he resides with man on the earth; while the other gods are either in the air, or in the sky. Viṣnu occupies, of all gods, the highest place ; for he represents (in the Rigveda) the sun in its daily and yearly course. In its daily course it reaches the highest point in the sky, when passing the zenith on he horizon; thence Visiu is called the &amp;quot; highest&amp;rdquo; of the gods. Sāyana understands I first&amp;quot; and &amp;quot; last&amp;quot; in reference to the respective order of deities in the twelve iturgies (sastra) of the Soma day at the Agnistoma sacrifice. For, says be “The Irst of these liturgies, the so-called Ajya-Sastra (see 2, 31), belongs to Agni, and in he last out of the twelve, in the so-called Agnamaruta sastra (see 3, 92-38), there is ne verse addressed to Viṣnu. But this argument, advanced by Sayaga, proves Jothing for his opinion that &amp;quot; Agni is the first, and Viṣnu [2] the last deity;&amp;quot; for hese twelve liturgies belong to the fifth day of the Agnistoma sacrifice, whilst the Sikṣanīya-isti, in connection with which ceremony the Brahmanam makes the remark(kapala). They offer it (the rice-cake) really to all the deities of this (Isti, without foregoing any one.&amp;quot; For Agni is all the deities, and Viṣnuis all the deities. For these two (divine) bodies, Agni and Viṣnu, are the two ends 5 of the sacrifice. Thus when they portion out the Agni-Vişṇu rice-cake, they indeed make at the end &amp;amp; (after the ceremony is over) prosper? (all) the gods of this (ceremony).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND CHAPTER.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Práyaniya Iṣti.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Práyaniya iṣti has its name &amp;ldquo;práyanīya&amp;rsquo;l from the fact that hy its means the sacrificers approach heaven (from pra-yā, going forward). The práyaniya [16]ceremony is the air inhaled (prāna), whereas the uda yaniya, i e, concluding ceremony (of the whole sacrifice) is the air exhaled. The Hotar (who is required at both ceremonies) is the common hold of both the airs (samāna). Both the air inhaled and exhaled are held together (in the same body). (The performance of both ceremonies, the prayanīya and udayanīya are intended) for making the vital airs, and for obtaining a discriminating knowledge of their several parts (prana, udang, &amp;amp;c.)?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD CHAPTER. The Buying and Bringing of the Soma. The Producing of Tire&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;by Friction. The Atithyā Tşti.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The gods bought the king Soma in the eastern direction. Thence he is (generally) bought in the eastern direction. They bought him from the thirteenth month. Thence the thirteenth month is found unfit (for any religious work to be done in it); a seller of the Soma is (likewise) found un fit (for intercourse). For such a man is a defaulter. (When the Soma, after having been bought, was brought to men (the sacrificers), his powers and his faculty of making the senses sharp moved from their place and scattered everywhere. They tried to collect and keep them [27] together with one verse. But they failed. They (tried to keep them together; with two, then with three, then with four, then with five, then with six, then&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 Diso is to be taken as an ablative depending on the verb vyudasidan, literally, they were upset (and scattered) everywhere. The preposition ut in this verb mainly requires the ablative.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH CHAPTER (The Pravargya Ceremony.&amp;quot;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The sacrifice went away from the gods (saying), I shall not be your food. The gods said : do not go; thou alone shalt be our food. The gods then killed [42] it. When it had been taken asunder&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;13 In the last pada of the first mantra there occur the words agnim atithim janānám, and also in the last pada of the second the words daivyo atithin, the heavenly guest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIFTH CHAPTER. (The Ceremonies of carrying the Fire, Soma, and the Offerings from their Places in the Prachina-vansa to the Uttara Vedi.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The king Soma lived among the Gandharvas. The Gods and Kiṣis deliberated; as to how the king might be induced to return to them. Vāch (the goddess of speech) said, the Gandharvas lust after women. I (there fore) shall transform myself into a woman, and then you sell me to them (in exchange for Soma).&amp;rsquo; The gods answered: “No! how may we live without thee? She said, sell me unto them; if you should want me, I shall return to you.&amp;quot; Thus they did. In the disguise of a big naked wo man she was sold (by the gods to the Gandharvas) in exchange for Soma. In imitation (of this precedent) they drive away an immaculate cow of one year&amp;rsquo;s age, being the price at which they purchase the king Soma. She (this cow) may, however, be rebought ; for Vāch (whom this cow, for which the Soma is bought, represents) returned to the gods. Thence the mantras (after Soma has been bought) are to be repeated with a low voice. After Soma has been bought, Vāch is with the Gandharvas; but she retuns as soon as the ceremony of the Agnipranayana is performed.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;*These words follow the mantra mentioned above : ansur amśuste, &amp;amp;c. (Taitt. Samh. 1, 2, 11, 1.; but the text differs a little from that in our Brahmanam).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
