<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/01/</guid>
      <description>FIRST CHAPTER (ADHYAYA).
(The Dikṣaniya Iṣti, with the Initiatory Rites.)
Agni, among the gods, has the lowest, Viṣnu the highest, place; between them stand all the other deities.
Sā yana, whom M. Muller follows in his translation of the first six chapters of the first book, as given in his “History of Ancient Sanskrit Literature&amp;quot; (pages 390-405), explains the words avama and parama by * first&amp;quot; and &amp;ldquo;last.&amp;rdquo; To prove this meaping to be the true one, Sāyana adduces the mantra (1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/02/</guid>
      <description>SECOND CHAPTER.
Práyaniya Iṣti.
The Práyaniya iṣti has its name &amp;ldquo;práyanīya&amp;rsquo;l from the fact that hy its means the sacrificers approach heaven (from pra-yā, going forward). The práyaniya [16]ceremony is the air inhaled (prāna), whereas the uda yaniya, i e, concluding ceremony (of the whole sacrifice) is the air exhaled. The Hotar (who is required at both ceremonies) is the common hold of both the airs (samāna). Both the air inhaled and exhaled are held together (in the same body).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/03/</guid>
      <description>THIRD CHAPTER. The Buying and Bringing of the Soma. The Producing of Tire
by Friction. The Atithyā Tşti.
The gods bought the king Soma in the eastern direction. Thence he is (generally) bought in the eastern direction. They bought him from the thirteenth month. Thence the thirteenth month is found unfit (for any religious work to be done in it); a seller of the Soma is (likewise) found un fit (for intercourse).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/04/</guid>
      <description>FOURTH CHAPTER (The Pravargya Ceremony.&amp;quot;)
The sacrifice went away from the gods (saying), I shall not be your food. The gods said : do not go; thou alone shalt be our food. The gods then killed [42] it. When it had been taken asunder 13 In the last pada of the first mantra there occur the words agnim atithim janānám, and also in the last pada of the second the words daivyo atithin, the heavenly guest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/01/05/</guid>
      <description>FIFTH CHAPTER. (The Ceremonies of carrying the Fire, Soma, and the Offerings from their Places in the Prachina-vansa to the Uttara Vedi.)
The king Soma lived among the Gandharvas. The Gods and Kiṣis deliberated; as to how the king might be induced to return to them. Vāch (the goddess of speech) said, the Gandharvas lust after women. I (there fore) shall transform myself into a woman, and then you sell me to them (in exchange for Soma).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
