<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/01/</guid>
      <description>FIRST CHAPTER. [158 ) (The Pra-uga Sastra. Pagatkāra, The Nivids.)
(The Pra-uga Śastra.) !
(The deities of the Pra-uga Śastra.) The Pra-uga Sastra is the recitation appropriate to the Soma offer 1 The Pra-aga sastra is the most peculiar of all the recitations by the Hotar on the day of the Soma feast; for it comprises a larger number of deities, divided into regular sections, than any other one, and has neither a proper Nivid, nor Pragathas, nor Dhāyyās, nor Soktas, as we constantly ind at the Sastras of the midday and evening libations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/02/</guid>
      <description>SECOND CHAPTER. [177] (The Murutvatiya and Niṣkevalya Sastrus.)
12
(On the Ahava and Pratigara.) They (the theologians) say: the subjects of the gods are to be pro cured. (To achieve this end) one netre is to be put in another metre. (This is done when) the Hotar calls (the Adhvaryu) by sorn sávon, &amp;quot; Let us both repeat, yes !&amp;quot; which (formula) consists of thee syllables. At the morning libation, the Adhvaryu responds (prati-grihnáti) (to this formula of three syllables) with one consisting of five: samsamo daivớn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/03/</guid>
      <description>THIRD CHAPTER. (The Abstraction of soina. Origin of the Three Libations. Evening Libation. The Vaišvadeva and Agnimāruta Sastras.)
(Story of the Metres which were despitched by the Gods to fetch the Sona from heaven. Jagati and Tristubh unsuccessful. Origin of Dikga, Tapas, and Dakṣind). The king Soma lived once) in the other world (in heaven). The Gods and Risis deliberated : how might the king Soma (be induced) to come to us?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/04/</guid>
      <description>FOURTH CHAPTER. (On the Origin, Meaning, and Universal Nature of the Agnistoma as the model for other Sacrifices. On the Chatuṣtoma and Jyotiṣtoma.)
(On the Origin of the name &amp;quot; Ágnistoma,&amp;quot; and its Meaning.) The Devas went to war with the Asuras, in order to defeat them. Agni was not willing to follow them. The Devas then said to him, &amp;quot; Go thou also, for thou art one of us.&amp;quot; He said, &amp;quot; I shall not go, unless a ceremony of praise is performed for me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
