<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST CHAPTER. [158 ) (The Pra-uga Sastra. Pagatkāra, The Nivids.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The Pra-uga Śastra.) !&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The deities of the Pra-uga Śastra.) The Pra-uga Sastra is the recitation appropriate to the Soma offer 1 The Pra-aga sastra is the most peculiar of all the recitations by the Hotar on the day of the Soma feast; for it comprises a larger number of deities, divided into regular sections, than any other one, and has neither a proper Nivid, nor Pragathas, nor Dhāyyās, nor Soktas, as we constantly ind at the Sastras of the midday and evening libations. It consists only of the verses in seven sections, mentioned in the Rigveda Sambitá (1,2-3). Each section is preceded by a so-called Paroruk, along with the Ah&amp;amp;va. Before the Puroruk of the first section there are, besides, the Himkára and the three great words required. I here write these introductory words in the same order in which they are repeated by the Hotri-priests up to the present day: f yzia: Free sta preiz NETETT AS : AT THEET 4** Ifrat Farf: Ferarata a t (see 1, 2,1-3) i.e. May Vāyu who walks frst, be the enjoyer of the sacrificer, come with his mind to the sacrifice; (may he come) the happy with his happy crowd! Om! Come, 0 Vayı, &amp;amp;o.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND CHAPTER. [177] (The Murutvatiya and Niṣkevalya Sastrus.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(On the Ahava and Pratigara.) They (the theologians) say: the subjects of the gods are to be pro cured. (To achieve this end) one netre is to be put in another metre. (This is done when) the Hotar calls (the Adhvaryu) by sorn sávon, &amp;quot; Let us both repeat, yes !&amp;quot; which (formula) consists of thee syllables. At the morning libation, the Adhvaryu responds (prati-grihnáti) (to this formula of three syllables) with one consisting of five: samsamo daivớn. This makes eight on the whole. The Gāyatri has eight syllables (i, e, each of its three padas). Thus these two (formulas) make the Gāyatri at the com mencement of the recitation at the morning libation. After the Hotar has finished his recitation, he uses this (formula of) four syllables : ultham [178] vdchi, i.e., the recitation has been read, to which the Adhvaryu&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD CHAPTER. (The Abstraction of soina. Origin of the Three Libations. Evening Libation. The Vaišvadeva and Agnimāruta Sastras.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Story of the Metres which were despitched by the Gods to fetch the Sona from heaven. Jagati and Tristubh unsuccessful. Origin of Dikga, Tapas, and Dakṣind).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The king Soma lived once) in the other world (in heaven). The Gods and Risis deliberated : how might the king Soma (be induced) to come to us? They said, “Ye metres must bring back to us this king Soma.&amp;quot; They consented. They transformed themselves into birds. That they transformed themselves into birds (suparna), and flew up, is called [202] by the knowers of stories sauparnam (1.c, this very story is called so). &amp;ldquo;The inetres went to fetch the king Soma. They consisted (at that time) of four syllables only; for (at that time) there were only such metres as consisted of four syllables. The Jagati, with her four syllables, flew first up. In flying up, she became tired, after having completed only half the way. She lost three syllables, and being reduced to one syllable, she took (from heaven) with her (only) the Dikṣā and Tapas,&amp;rsquo; and flew back (to the earth). Ile who has cattle is possessed of Dīkṣā and pos sessed of Tapas. For cattle belong to Jagati. Jagati took them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/03/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH CHAPTER. (On the Origin, Meaning, and Universal Nature of the Agnistoma as the model for other Sacrifices. On the Chatuṣtoma and Jyotiṣtoma.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;89&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(On the Origin of the name &amp;quot; Ágnistoma,&amp;quot; and its Meaning.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Devas went to war with the Asuras, in order to defeat them. Agni was not willing to follow them. The Devas then said to him, &amp;quot; Go thou also, for thou art one of us.&amp;quot; He said, &amp;quot; I shall not go, unless a ceremony of praise is performed for me. Do ye that now.” So they did. They all rose up (from their places), turned towards Agni, and performed the ceremony of praising him. After having been praised, he followed them. He having assumed the shape of three rows, attacked in three battle lines the Asuras, in order to defeat them. The three rows were made only of the metres (Gayatri, Triṣtubh, Jagati). The three battle lines are only the three libations. He defeated them beyond expectation. Thence the Devas put down the Asuras. The enemy, the incarnate sin (pāpman), the adversary of him who has such a knowledge, perishes by himself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
