<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 THE MOTHER OF THE VEDAS on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/2_THE_MOTHER_OF_THE_VEDAS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 THE MOTHER OF THE VEDAS on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/2_THE_MOTHER_OF_THE_VEDAS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>6 Personification, Divinization,</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/2_THE_MOTHER_OF_THE_VEDAS/6_Personification_Divinization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/2_THE_MOTHER_OF_THE_VEDAS/6_Personification_Divinization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Part I has shown that the status of the Gāyatrī-Mantra in Early Hinduism continued to increase after it had been made the primary initiation mantra. But while the religious manuals produced in that period reflect this increase in status in a number of ritual developments, they nowhere personify the mantra, even when attributing divinity to it. The most straightforward explanation for this is that the GM was not (yet) consistently considered a full-fledged deity, at least not by the practitioners and codifiers of the “orthoprax” ritualistic religion. In this chapter, however, we will see that the idea of a mantra goddess had already had precursors in this period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Identification with Sāvitrī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/2_THE_MOTHER_OF_THE_VEDAS/7_Identification_with_sAvitrI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/2_THE_MOTHER_OF_THE_VEDAS/7_Identification_with_sAvitrI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 6 focused on the deification of the Gāyatrī-Mantra itself, considering its association or even identification with other deities (the deified gāyatrī  meter; Sarasvatī) only insofar as they were relevant to this process. In this chapter, the approach differs in that it hones in on one specific deity that, I argue, had a vital impact on the deification of the GM. The origins of this deity extend far back to a time long before the Indo-Aryans immigrated to South Asia in the second millennium bce. In various forms and under various names, it had already existed for thousands of years prior to the GM’s elevation to divine status. By the time it first came into contact with the GM, it was called Sāvitrī, just like the mantra itself. This chapter is devoted to retracing the history and prehistory of this goddess, and to showing how she became entangled with the foremost sāvitrī.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>8 The Mantra Goddess</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/2_THE_MOTHER_OF_THE_VEDAS/8_The_Mantra_Goddess/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/haas_gAyatrI/2_THE_MOTHER_OF_THE_VEDAS/8_The_Mantra_Goddess/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the previous two chapters I have attempted to show how the Gāyatrī-Mantra became a goddess. In doing so, I adopted a diachronic perspective, focusing on the developments that took place between one stage and the next. This approach shed light on the processes involved in the mantra’s deification. The result of these processes, however – the deity itself – has so far been largely left aside.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lacuna will be partially closed in the present chapter, whose primary aim is to outline a portrait of the mantra goddess as she appears in the Sanskrit literature that was composed in the period of Classical Hinduism (c. 350–550 ce) and in the first centuries of the “Tantric Age” (sixth century ce+).⁹⁷⁵ To round off the portrait, I will also address conceptions of the goddess that likely originated in the final third of the first millennium ce (and continued to be elaborated throughout the second).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
