<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;06 R̥gvedic People and Society on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/06_Rgvedic_People_and_Society/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;06 R̥gvedic People and Society on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/06_Rgvedic_People_and_Society/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A R̥gveda as History</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/06_Rgvedic_People_and_Society/A_Rgveda_as_History/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/06_Rgvedic_People_and_Society/A_Rgveda_as_History/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A number of scholars have treated the question of the historical background of the  R̥gveda and to what extent we can extract historical information from the names  of kings and peoples, the events they are depicted as participating in, and the place54 The Rigveda names where these events are depicted as occurring or where the kings and their  retinues are depicted as living. We do not intend to enter into these issues and will  simply make global reference to the many works of Michael Witzel (e.g., Witzel  1995a, 1995b), who has been especially active in discussing these questions in recent  decades.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B Āryas, DĀsas, and Dasyus</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/06_Rgvedic_People_and_Society/B_Aryas_DAsas_and_Dasyus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/06_Rgvedic_People_and_Society/B_Aryas_DAsas_and_Dasyus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The people of the R̥gveda refer to themselves as Āryas, which probably meant the  “civilized” ones or something similar. Under this term they define their own group  as the people who sacrifice to the gods, who adhere to Vedic customs, who speak  Indo-Aryan languages, and who in other ways identify themselves with Vedic culture. They also refer to themselves as mā́nuṣa and mānavá, the “sons of Manu” or  the “peoples of Manu,” for the legendary Manu (mánu simply means “man”) was  the one who first instituted the sacrifice and was therefore the founder of Vedic  religious culture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C Social and Political Organization</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/06_Rgvedic_People_and_Society/C_Social_and_Political_Organization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/06_Rgvedic_People_and_Society/C_Social_and_Political_Organization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The R̥gveda is the product of an elite segment of society, and it no doubt reflects  only a small part of even elite religious life.+++(4)+++ For example, the life-cycle rituals that  are so important in the late Vedic period, chronicled in the gr̥hya sūtras, are only  tangentially treated in the R̥gveda, and we get only glimpses of the dharmic prescriptions that later ordered daily life, as preserved in the dharma sūtras of the  late Vedic period and the dharma śāstras that followed them. The religious beliefs  and practices of the non-elite are completely absent from the text, except perhaps  in obscure and slighting references to practices that do not conform to R̥gvedic  standards.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
