<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;07 Language and Poetics on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;07 Language and Poetics on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Grammatical Structure and Language Use</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/A_Grammatical_Structure_and_Language_Use/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/A_Grammatical_Structure_and_Language_Use/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sanskrit is an inflectional language with an especially rich morphology, and most of  the grammatical information that is carried in English by word order and by separate  elements such as prepositions and auxiliary verbs is coded in Sanskrit on the word  itself. R̥gvedic poets glory in their grammar and are skillful in exploiting not only the  many distinctions it provides but also grammatical ambiguities and neutralizations  of grammatical distinctions. Moreover, since basic information, such as the identity  of the grammatical subject and object, is coded on the word, the poet is free to use  word order for rhetorical purposes, placing particularly significant words in emphatic  positions such as initial in the verse line. When possible, we have tried to reproduce  these effects, but all too often, given the very different structure of English, the result  of a well-intentioned effort to follow the Sanskrit word order is at best awkward and  artificial, and at worst unintelligible. This is discussed further in section VIII below.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B Hymn Types and Structuring Devices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/B_Hymn_Types_and_Structuring_Devices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/B_Hymn_Types_and_Structuring_Devices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is no single, universally applicable template to which all, or even most,  R̥gvedic hymns conform. At best we can state the uselessly vague obvious: most hymns praise a god or gods, often with reference to their attributes and deeds, and  explicitly or implicitly request goods and services from the divinities in return for  this praise. This exchange is often effected during the sacrifice at which we hope they  are present, either because they are part of the sacrificial paraphernalia (like Agni  and Soma) or have come as invited guests.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C Imagery, Metaphors, and Similes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/C_Imagery_Metaphors_and_Similes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/C_Imagery_Metaphors_and_Similes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The R̥gveda is rich in imagery: the procedures of sacrifice, the exploits of the gods,  the activities of men, and the elements and functioning of the cosmos are constantly presented in images of something else, images based on similarity and parallelism.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;similie&#34;&gt;Similie&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the formal level by far the most common way of expressing these images  is in a simile—the most common poetic device in the R̥gveda, as it is in Classical  Sanskrit poetry. Although to Indologists the dominance of the simile may seem too  predictable to be worth noting, in fact this is one of the features of R̥gvedic style  that looks forward to the classical era, and seems to represent something of a break  from the stylistic parameters of the poetic tradition from which R̥gvedic practice  emerged. The Avesta contains very few similes—none in the Old Avestan Gāthās  to which the R̥gveda is otherwise so akin—and the so-called “Homeric simile” of  ancient Greek epic, with its elaborately imagined world expressed in verb phrases,  is structurally very different from the Sanskrit simile.+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D Riddles</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/D_Riddles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/D_Riddles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Much of the R̥gveda is enigmatic, not only because of our distance from the time  of its creation, but also because the poets meant it to be enigmatic. They valued  knowledge, especially the knowledge of the hidden connections (the bandhus discussed above) between the visible world, the divine world, and the realm of ritual.+++(5)+++  They embedded that knowledge in hymns that were stylistically tight and elliptical,  expressively oblique, and lexically resonant. As a result, many hymns of the R̥gveda  can appear to us as riddles. However, there are also hymns purposefully composed  to cloak their subjects or to withhold them until late in the hymn.+++(5)+++ In the later Veda  the ability to solve the riddles they pose became a formalized demonstration of the  knowledge of the priests taking part in the sacrifice. In the R̥gveda the riddle hymns  challenged the interpretive ability of their hearers and demonstrated the cleverness  of their poets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E Metrics</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/E_Metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/07_Language_and_Poetics/E_Metrics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The most conspicuous and ubiquitous formal feature of the R̥gveda is meter. The  hymns are composed in a variety of meters, but all of the meters are syllable-counting and quantitative. That is, they consist of lines containing a fixed number of syllables,  arranged in patterns of “heavy” and “light” syllables (the “quantity” referred to by  the term “quantitative”). Heavy syllables contain a long vowel (a class that includes  e and o) or diphthong or a short vowel followed by two consonants (which need not  belong to the same word) and are symbolized in Western analysis by a macron (¯).  Light syllables contain a short vowel followed by, at most, a single consonant and  are symbolized by a breve (˘). (Aspirated consonants [those written with two roman  letters, the second of which is h, e.g., th] count as single consonants.) The final syllable of a line is metrically indifferent and symbolized by x. The distinction between  heavy and light metrical syllables simply formally enshrines patterns inherent in  the language itself, where various linguistic processes are sensitive to distinction  in syllable weight and the difference between short and long vowels is lexically and  morphologically crucial.+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
