<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०९ on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०९ on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>००१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/001/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/001/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/001/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ऋग्वेदसंहिता&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;श्रीमत्सायणाचार्यविरचितभाष्यसमेता&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ अथ नवमं मण्डलम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;नवमे मण्डले सप्तानुवाकाः । तत्र प्रथमेऽनुवाके चतुर्विंशतिसंख्याकानि सूक्तानि । तत्र ‘ स्वादिष्ठया&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं प्रथमं सूक्तम् । अत्रानुक्रम्यते&amp;mdash; स्वादिष्ठया दश मधुच्छन्दाः&amp;rsquo; इति । वैश्वामित्रो मधुच्छन्दा ऋषिः । प्राग्वत्सप्रीयपरिभाषया गायत्री छन्दः । ‘ नवमं मण्डलं पावमानं सौम्यम्&amp;rsquo; (अनु.) इति वचनात् पवमानगुणविशिष्टः सोमो देवता । ग्रावस्तोत्रेऽर्बुदसूक्तस्य प्रागुत्तमाया इदमादिकं सर्वं पावमानं विकल्पेनावपनीयम् । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash;’ प्रैते वदन्त्वित्यर्बुदं प्रागुत्तमाया आ व ऋञ्जसे   प्र वो ग्रावाण इति सूक्तयोरन्तरोपरिष्टात्पुरस्ताद्वा पावमानीरोप्य यथार्थमा वा ग्रहग्रहणात् &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ५, १२) इति । उपाकर्मणि मण्डलादिग्रहण आद्या! सूत्रं पूर्वमेवोदाहृतम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/002/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/002/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘पवस्व &amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तं काण्वस्य मेधातिथेरार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- पवस्व मेधातिथि:&amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2 (714)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Medhātithi Kāṇva&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Medhātithi Kāṇva is the named poet of several hymns in the first half of Maṇḍala  VIII (2–3, 32), with its predominantly Kāṇva authorship—but more to the point  also of the second division of Maṇḍala I (I.12–23). So, just as the first hymn of IX  is ascribed to the poet of the first hymns of Maṇḍala I, the second hymn of IX is  said to have been composed by the poet of the second collection in I.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins with the signature command “purify yourself” (pávasva), and  the first word of the second pāda belongs to the same root: pavítram, the “means  of purifying,” that is, the filter. The first verses in general follow the steps in the  preparation of soma after the pressing proper: the filtering of the pressed soma  (vs. 1), into a vessel (vs. 2) with water (vss. 3–4), followed by the mixing with milk  (vs. 4). This process is summarized in grandiose and cosmic terms in the following  two verses (5–6), with the verbal accompaniment, the hymns and prayers, intro&lt;br&gt;&#xA;duced in verses 7–8. Verse 9 echoes the earlier part of the hymn, particularly verse  3, and the poet ends (vs. 10) with a description of all of Soma’s winnings, which  can be interpreted as a covert request for Soma to provide us with these items.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;There is nothing particularly noteworthy or out of the ordinary in this hymn,  which could be taken as a prototypical Soma hymn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/003/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/003/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘एष देवः&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तमाजीगर्तेः शुनःशेपस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । अनुक्रान्तं च - एषः शुनःशेपः&amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3 (715)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Śunaḥśepa Ājiīgarti&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Following the pattern set by IX.1–2, the Anukramaṇī gives as the poet of  this hymn the author of the third collection of hymns in Maṇḍala I  (24–30),  Śunaḥśepa Ājīgarti, also the protagonist of the famous Aitareya Brāhmaṇa story  of father/son sacrifice (AiB VII.13–18), related during the Rājasūya, the Royal  Consecration.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn is verbally unified by the “this (one)” (eṣá), which begins every verse.  It is thematically unified by its focus on only one step of the preparation, the filter ing through sheep’s wool that is the self-purification proper. A form of the verb  “purify oneself” appears in seven of the ten verses (and “filter” derived from the  same root in an eighth; only vss. 1 and 6 lack such a form). The poet provides vari ety with a range of images, from the bird of verse 1 to the chariot rider in verse 5,  and as is common he conflates, and equates, the ritual and cosmic spheres. So, for  example, the filter across which the soma moves is both a tangle of wool (vs. 2) and  the vast spaces of heaven and the atmosphere (vs. 7).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/004/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/004/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘सना च&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं चतुर्थं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसकुलस्य हिरण्यस्तूपस्थार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । अनुक्रान्तं च- सन हिरण्यस्तूपः &amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4 (716)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Hiraṇyastūpa Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Once again, the poet of this fourth hymn in the Soma Maṇḍala is also the author  of the fourth collection of hymns in Maṇḍala I (I.31–35), as well as another Soma  hymn, IX.69.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The thematic constriction of the soma hymns is even narrower than usual in this  hymn. A third of each verse is occupied by the self-contained refrain (pāda c: áthā no vásyasas kr̥dhi “then make us better off”), and many of the verses consist of  short imperative clauses. There are local repetitions as well: the initial “win!” (sánā)  of verses 1–3, the repeated pāda about resolve and help in verses 5b–6a, and the  initial “rush” (abhy àrṣa) of verses 7–8. Only two verses (6, 9) lack an imperative,  and the former contains an optative in similar usage.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;These conscious formal limits of the hymn are obviously its point: content is  secondary. One might note, however, that the sun’s light is especially desired (vss.  2, 5, 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/005/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/005/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/005/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘समिद्धः&amp;rsquo; इत्येकादशर्चं पञ्चमं सूक्तं काश्यपस्यासितस्य देवलस्य वार्षम् । अष्टम्याद्याश्चतस्रोऽनुष्टुभः शिष्टाः सप्त गायत्र्यः । नराशंसवर्जिताः समिदादयः क्रमेण प्रत्यृचं देवताः । तथा चानुक्रान्तं - समिद्ध एकादश काश्यपोऽसितो देवलो वा विंशतिः सूक्तान्याद्यमाप्रियश्चतुरनुष्टुबन्तम् इति । काश्यपस्य पावमानमिदमाप्रीसूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च- समिद्धो अद्येति सर्वेषां यथर्षि वा  (आश्व. श्रौ. ३. २) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;5 (717)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Āprı̄&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;11 verses: gāyatrī 1–7, anuṣṭubh 8–11&lt;br&gt;&#xA;An interesting hybrid: the poet has taken the strict patterning of the Āprī hymns of  the animal sacrifice, in which each verse contains a key word or phrase (italicized  in translation) and the verses appear in the same order, and adapted it to the Soma  Pavamāna genre. The same key words are found in the same order, but they are  no longer directly addressed to or descriptive of a series of different divinities and  divinized ritual elements. Instead Soma is sometimes identified with the divinity&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/006/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘मन्द्रया&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं षष्ठं सूक्तं काश्यपस्यासितस्य देवलस्य वार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;6 (718)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma’s journey—to the gods, to Indra, and to us, as well as to the state of exhila ration and to material rewards—is the primary subject of this hymn. In the last two verses (8–9) Soma’s association with poetry and with the exercise of poetic  skill is mentioned. The last statement, that Soma takes to himself hymns, though  they are hidden, is not entirely clear, but it may refer to his ability to stimulate  poetic inspiration, and to cause poets to create new hymns from deep within  themselves.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Noteworthy is also the pun in verse 2, where the drop (índu) is urged to flow as  “Indra.” The phonological similarity between these two words is often exploited  elsewhere, indeed in the immediately preceding hymn (IX.5.9).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/007/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘असृग्रम्&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं सप्तमं सूक्तम् । &amp;rsquo; असृग्रम्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । असितो देवलो वर्षिः ।। तौ च कश्यपगोत्रजौ&amp;rsquo; । गायत्रं छन्दः । सोमः पवमानो देवता । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;7 (719)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The word “soma” does not appear at all in this hymn, and the epithet “self-purify ing” (pávamāna) only once, in verse 5 (a finite verb form from the same root is found  in vs. 8). Verses 1 and 8 have a similar structure, especially in their final pādas, and&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/008/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/008/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘एते सोमाः&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चमष्टमं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । अनुक्रान्तं च &amp;ndash; एते सोमाः &amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तः सूक्तविनियोगः । ग्रावस्तोत्रे गाणगारिमतेनाभिरूपकरणे सोमे मृज्यमाने &amp;rsquo; मृजन्ति त्वा  इत्येषा । सूत्रितं च- अथापरमभिरूपं कुर्यादिति गाणगारिरा प्यायस्व समेतु त इति तिस्रो मृजन्ति त्वा दश क्षिपः&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ५.१२ ) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;8 (719)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Although this hymn is, of course, dedicated to self-purifying Soma, the process is  repeatedly described in the passive (“being purified,” vss. 2, 3, 6) rather than in the  usual reflexive construction. However, this grammatical peculiarity does not seem  to deprive Soma of agency: he (or his juices) are urged to increase Indra’s power (vs. 1), provide us with power (vss. 2, 8), cause Indra to be generous to us (vs. 3) and  provide us with mortal patrons as well (vs. 7), remove hostilities (vs. 7), and cause  the rain to fall (vs. 8), among other things.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The middle verses (4–6) concern the preparation of soma; as usual, the materials  used in the preparation are animatized (vss. 5–6): the “ewes” are the fleece filter, the  “cows” and “cattle” the milk-mixture.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first three verses reunite the group of gods to whom Soma went in the previ ous hymn (IX.7.7): Vāyu and the Aśvins (vs. 2) and Indra (vss. 1, 3), the principal  deities of the Morning Pressing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>००९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/009/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/009/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘परि प्रिया&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं नवमं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । परि प्रिया&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्तो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;9 (721)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Unlike the relatively straightforward preceding hymns, this one is full of puz zles and ambiguities, with the implements and process of soma purification  compared to cosmic entities and actions. Some of the puzzles are illuminated  by the next hymn, IX.10, which is in some ways a more straightforward twin  to this one. This one also appears to be an omphalos hymn, with an inner ring1244 IX.9&lt;br&gt;&#xA;defined by numerological repetition in verses 4 and 6, around the omphalos  verse 5.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;On the ritual level, the soma is pressed between or in his two granddaughters  (vs. 1): most likely the hands of the priest, on the basis of IX.10.2; after his journey  (vss. 1–2), accompanied by hymns he is united with the waters (vss. 4–5), who make  him their eye. He is called upon to give aid to the ritual and to the hymn (vss. 7–8).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This synopsis leaves a number of questions unanswered. Who, for example, are  his two mothers in verse 3? Are they the same as his two female kinsmen in verse  1? Since R̥gvedic poets delight in paradoxical kinship relationships, this is certainly  possible. If so, they could be both the ritual implement (hands) and Heaven and  Earth, and in this latter cosmic manifestation their son Soma, who makes them  shine in verse 3, could be identified with the sun—an identification that is supported  by the “single eye” of verse 4. Again under a cosmic interpretation the rivers of  verse 4 can be not only the waters with which soma mixes in his ritual preparation,  but also the heavenly streams (and indeed real rivers).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The referents in the middle verses 4–6 are especially floating and uncertain: both  the insights and the rivers of verse 4 are feminine in gender. The agent of verse 5  (the omphalos verse) is feminine plural, and so could be either insights or rivers or  both, and “the great” is also left unspecified. In verse 6 we encounter “the seven”  again, which can either be the seven insights of verse 4 (which we also met in the  preceding hymn, IX.8.4) or the rivers, since the canonical number of rivers is seven.  This series of puzzles is capped by the final pāda of verse 6, with the impossible  word krívi, which seems here to refer to Soma. The goddesses whom he satisfies  could, again, be either the rivers or the insights (or perhaps even just goddesses).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The final three verses (7–9), with their requests, cause little difficulty, by contrast. Although the mysteries of the hymn remain largely unsolved, we can note a the matic strain that provides some unity: the issue of light and darkness. The Soma/&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Sun of verse 3 lights up his mothers; he may also be the Sun in verse 4. In verse 7  we call upon Soma to help us combat darkness and in verse 8 to light up the lights.  The last word of the hymn (vs. 9) is “sun” (svàḥ). It seems that in this hymn Soma  is both identified with the Sun and seen as a force that can win and keep the light  that Vedic people so craved and worried about. This focus on the sun is also found  in the next hymn, IX.10.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/010/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ प्र स्वानासः&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं दशमं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘प्र स्वानासः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;10 (722)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn, which shares a number of themes with IX.9, begins with three verses  heavy with similes, quickly sketching the pressing, filtering, and mixing of the soma  juices. After a verse (4)  with no poetic figuration, the second part of the hymn  switches to metaphor, and especially to metaphors of and identifications with the  sun, as in IX.9. The spreading of the soma juices across the sheep’s fleece is likened  to suns and their rays (vs. 5). The “lone one” in verse 7 is probably both the soma  crossing the filter and the sun crossing heaven. Soma’s eye is first tied to the sun (vs.  8), and then the sun implicitly becomes his eye (vs. 9). In addition, the “portion” of  Vivasvant (“the one shining forth”) and of Dawn in verse 5 probably refers to the  radiance of these divinities, obtained by the soma juices, which are then transformed  into suns.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Other metaphors involve the poets and sacrificers: the doors of poetry (vs. 6), the  seven siblings of the priests (vs. 7), who are no doubt the seven inspired thoughts of  previous hymns (IX.9.4, 6; IX.8.4). This latter metaphor of kinship then provides  our own kinship relationship to Soma himself (vs. 8). One image remains somewhat  obscure: in verse 9 the “track of heaven” is said to have been placed in hiding by the  Adhvaryus. This must be a specific ritual reference, with the track of heaven being  likened to Soma’s own tracks—perhaps when Soma disappears into the fleece when  the Adhvaryu priests are first pressing him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०११</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/011/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ उपास्मै &amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चमेकादशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् ।  उपास्मै  इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्तः सूक्तविनियोगः । अभिष्टवे घर्मदुघावत्सेऽपनीयमाने &amp;lsquo;नमसेदुप&amp;rsquo; इत्येषा । सूत्रितं च-’ नमसेदुप सीदत संजानाना उप सीदन्नभिज्ञु&amp;rsquo; (आश्व. श्रौ. ४.७ ) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;11 (723)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Much of this hymn consists of exhortations to the priests to perform their parts of  the soma preparation, interspersed with addresses to Soma to purify himself for  our benefit. Unlike the last few hymns attributed to the same poet, the language and  syntax present no difficulties, and there is almost no imagery or verbal figuration. It  is a no-nonsense production.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/012/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/012/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘सोमा असृग्रम्&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं द्वादशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्यायाः पूर्ववत् । ‘सोमा असृग्रम्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्तो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;12 (724)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Although entirely focused on the process of soma preparation, this hymn displays  the common rhetorical inflation of this process by associating it with cosmic ele ments. Thus, for example, in verse 4 Soma is both “in the navel of heaven” and “in  the sheep’s fleece”—both referring to the filter; the “surface of the sea” in verse 6  is either the soma itself collected in the vessel or the water with which it mixes; the  “dear tracks of heaven” in verse 8 are the meanderings of soma through the fleece  filter (see also IX.10.9). The buffalo-cow in verse 3 is probably the hide on which the  pressing apparatus is set. Only in the last verse (9) does the poet make any requests  of the god.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/013/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत्।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;षष्ठस्य सप्तमोऽध्यायः संग्रहात्संप्रदर्शितः ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथाष्टमः सुमतिना संगमेन प्रदर्श्यते ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तत्र सोमः पुनानः&amp;rsquo; इति नवचं त्रयोदशं सूक्तम् । असितो देवलो वर्षिः। सोमो देवता । ‘ पवमानगुणः सोमो विज्ञेयः काश्यपावृषी । इति विद्यादनुक्तेऽपि लाघवाया दृळ्हच्युतात् ॥ ‘सोमः इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;13 (725)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first verse, with its mention of Vāyu and Indra, identifies this as the first soma offering of the day. Otherwise the hymn is a confection of clichés familiar from  many other soma hymns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/014/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘परि प्र&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं चतुर्दशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्यादि पूर्ववत् । “परि प्राष्टौ&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;14 (726)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poet of this hymn seems to be practicing his figurative language, presenting us in  nonsequential verses with several different versions of the same step in the prepara tion of soma. This is especially clear in his depiction of the manual manipulation of  soma: in verse 2 the hands are called “troops of five kinsmen,” in verse 5 the same  fingers are “the granddaughters of Vivasvant” (here the prototype sacrificer), and  in verse 7 a standard word for “fingers” finally makes its appearance. Similarly he  gives two quite similar expressions for the mixing with milk, both using the image  of clothing (vss. 3, 5), and in verse 6 there is a glancing reference to Soma’s desire  for cows.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The episodic structure of the hymn also seems reflected in the shifting tenses of  the verbs. In particular, the past tense of verse 3ab seems to follow directly from  verse 1, with the presents of verses 2 and 3c in alternation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/015/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘एष धिया&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं पञ्चदशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । एष धिया&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;15 (727)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A simple device provides formal unity to this hymn: the form “this one” that begins  every verse. In the first six verses it is the nominative subject (eṣá), in the last two  (vss. 7–8) the accusative object (etám), so that there is some progression and devel opment, even while the referent remains constant.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Except for verse 2, the focus is entirely on Soma’s journey across the fleece and  into the cup, where both the waters (vs. 5) and the milk (vs. 6) await him. (The men tion of grasses in vs. 6 is unclear.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/016/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ प्र ते सोतारः&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं षोडशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘प्र ते &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;16 (728)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This little hymn presents several difficulties of interpretation, even though like  many hymns in this series it does not deviate from the ritual scene, especially the fil tering of the pressed juice, and it is built around a limited verbal lexicon, especially  the phonological near mirror images √sr̥j “surge” and √r̥ṣ “rush.” In verse 1 Soma  is implicitly identified with Etaśa, the sun’s horse, and in verse 7 he swells “like the  back of heaven.” But otherwise cosmic references and comparisons are absent, and the soma again and again runs across the filter (vss. 2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 8) and joins with  the waters (vss. 2–3) and the milk (vss. 2 and 6), to furnish Indra’s drink (vss. 3, 5). The most problematic form is the hapax ánapta in verse 3, about which there is  no scholarly agreement. We have very tentatively connected it with naptī́ “grand daughter,” a very rare word that nonetheless appears twice in this poet’s collection  (IX.9.1, 14.5), used of the preparers of soma or their equipment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/017/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र निम्नेनेव&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं सप्तदशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘प्र निम्नेनेव&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;17 (729)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A straightforward hymn: the soma juices flow quickly on their journey through the  filter into the vessels and thence to Indra and the gods, a journey compared to that  of the sun. The role of speech in the soma sacrifice is also emphasized, with soma  both inspiring speech and being strengthened by it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/018/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ परि सुवानः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चमष्टादशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘परि सुवानः सप्त&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;18 (730)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The most salient feature of this hymn is its pāda-length refrain, promising health  and wholeness. The beginning (vs. 1) and end (vs. 7) of the hymn record the ritual  moment, the purification in the filter. The intermediate verses, especially 4–6,  ascribe human and then cosmic powers to the ritual substance. Verses 4–6 are  also syntactically unresolved, as they consist of three parallel relative clauses in  the ab pādas, couched in the 3rd person, interrupted by the refrain addressing  Soma in the 2nd person in the c pāda. The 3rd-person main clause that brings  closure to this structure is found in the final verse, 7ab.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;It is noteworthy that the word “soma” is found only in the first verse.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०१९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/019/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ यत् सोम&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चमेकोनविंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् ।&amp;rsquo; यत् सोम&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;19 (731)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn contains fewer direct ritual references than recent hymns. The focus is  instead on the exchange relation between Soma and his praisers: hymns for goods,  an exchange that is seen as, literally, fecund. Our insights and the words they pro duce are depicted as females waiting to be impregnated (vs. 5) and made to swell (vs.  2), as they call to the bullish Soma for his semen (vs. 4). The impregnated thoughts  will give birth not only to inspired poetry, but also to the material goods that this  poetry will win, as verses 1 and 6 make clear. The final two verses (6–7) also call for  Soma’s help in besting rivals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/020/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र कविः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं विंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘प्र कविः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;20 (731)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like the immediately preceding hymn, this one is less concerned with the details of  the ritual (though they are not absent: the fleece filter, vss. 1, 7; the water and the  cups, vs. 6) than with the ritual economy, where, for example, our thought helps  purify Soma (vs. 3) and he in return finds wealth for the poets, singers, and patrons.  Although most of the phraseology is standard for soma hymns, the image in verse  5 of Soma entering the songs seems to be a deliberate reversal of passages in which  the songs themselves enter a god, and seems also to imitate and vary the numerous  passages in which Soma enters Indra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/021/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;एते धावन्ति&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चमेकविंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । एते धावन्ति&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;21 (733)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāsyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;For most of its length this hymn is a conventional depiction of the flowing of the  soma drops and of the benefits that attend it. Verses 5 and 6, however, which are  constructed in parallel, introduce twists of imagery. Addressed to the soma drops,  the verses urge them to instruct the ungenerous man—presumably a patron who does not distribute the appropriate priestly gifts at the soma sacrifice. In verse 6 the  drops are commanded to set their own will to this task, as a craftsman sets a new  chariot part, probably a wheel. In verse 5 they are meant to set “the tawny tracker”  in an unspecified being or thing (“in this one”); although the referents for both have  been variously identified, we believe that the tawny tracker is Soma himself, and  Indra, already mentioned in verse 1, is the desired location.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/022/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;एते सोमासः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं द्वाविंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । एते सोमासः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;22 (734)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins with the conventional image of the soma juices racing forward (vs.  1), but their journey soon becomes both cosmic and mystical. Their rush is com pared to cosmic forces in verse 2, and in verses 4–5 they travel through the cosmos  itself. But the poet reaches even further conceptually: he equates this cosmic jour ney with a ritual one. In matched expressions in verses 3 and 5 the juices pervade  not only the cosmic spaces (vs. 5) but also our “insights” (vs. 3), that is, the thoughts  that produce ritual poetry. And in verse 6 they reach a higher place than the cosmic&lt;br&gt;&#xA;space, namely the sacrifice itself, symbolized, as often, by the stretched thread. In the final verse (7) this journey theme is abruptly abandoned, and the disjunc tion between this verse and what precedes is also conveyed by the switch from plural  (“soma juices”) to singular (“Soma”), and from 3rd-person reference to 2nd. It also  contains an implicit equation of Soma with (the unmentioned) Saramā, Indra’s dog&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/023/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘सोमा असृग्रम्&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं त्रयोविंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘सोमा असृग्रम्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;23 (735)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn begins very like the last one, with the rushing of the soma juices, but  goes in a different direction. Verse 2 introduces the Āyus, men both of the past (so  vs. 2, also IX.10.6) and of the present, who are regularly credited with the prepara tion of the soma in the IXth Maṇḍala and by this very poet (IX.10.6, 15.7, 16.8,  19.3). But surprisingly in verse 4 the Āyus are identified with the soma juices, a  rhetorical strategy that must result from the fact that in this verse the juices purify  themselves into the exhilarating drink; in other words they prepare themselves and  therefore behave like the Āyus who prepare the soma.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In the last three verses (5–7) Soma’s relationship to Indra becomes the focus: in  verse 5 the rushing soma acquires the power of Indra as its essence, and in verses  6 and 7 this power is transferred to Indra, to perform his heroic deeds, both in the  past and in the present. Verse 7 thus harkens back to the ancient Āyus and their  newer path in verse 2.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/024/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;प्र सोमासः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं चतुर्विंशं सूक्तम् । असितो देवलो वर्षिर्गायत्री छन्दः सोमो देवता । ‘प्र सोमासः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;24 (736)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Asita Kāśyapa or Devala Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is the last attributed to Asita or Devala Kāśyapa, and yet again the hymn  begins with the running forth of the soma juices. It is an unremarkable hymn, but  covers the major topics, though not in strict chronological order:  the grooming  in water (vs. 1), the mixture with milk (vs. 2), the filtering (vss. 3, 5). That soma is  Indra’s drink is repeatedly emphasized (vss. 2, 3, 5, and under the qualifier “con&lt;br&gt;&#xA;queror of territories,” a word regularly applied to Indra, vs. 4). Soma himself is  given the most characteristic of Indra’s epithets—“obstacle-smasher”—in the  superlative in verse 6.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/025/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;द्वितीयेऽनुवाके षट्त्रिंशत्सूक्तानि । तत्र ‘पवस्व&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं प्रथमं सूक्तं दृळ्हच्युतनाम्नोऽगस्त्यपुत्रस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । अनुक्रान्तं च-’ पवस्व षड् दृळ्हच्युत आगस्त्यः । इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;25 (737)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Drḍ̥ hacyuta Āgastya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This is the only hymn in the R̥gveda attributed to this poet, though his patronymic  connects him to Agastya, the poet of a number of hymns in the late Ist Maṇḍala  (I.165–91)—including the dialogue hymn I.165, in which Agastya mediates between  Indra and the Maruts, who demand a share of the soma sacrifice. This connection  may account for the mention of the Maruts in verse 1 as recipients of soma, along  with Vāyu: the Maruts are quite scarce in the Soma Maṇḍala.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn is otherwise unremarkable, though one might note the insistent iden tification of Soma as a kaví (“poet,” vss. 3, 5, 6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/026/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘तममृक्षन्त&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं द्वितीयं सूक्तं दृळ्हच्युतपुत्रस्येध्मवाहनाम्न आर्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । अनुक्रान्तं च–&amp;rsquo; तममृक्षन्तेध्मवाहो दार्ढच्युतः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;26 (738)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Idhmavāha Dārḍhacyuta&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Attributed to a descendant of the poet of the previous hymn, based on his patronymic,  this hymn contains nothing novel in terms of content, but it is tightly structured. All verses but the last begin with “that one, him” (tám) referring to the Soma, while the  last begins with a 2nd-person variant on this, “you” (táṃ tvā), literally “that you.”  The last four verses (3–6) all contain a 3rd plural “they impell(ed)” (ahyan, hinvanti built to the same root √hi), and the compounds of 3c and 5c “&amp;hellip;to/of many” (bhū́ri)  phonologically echo the word for “arms” (bhuríjor) in the middle verse (4a).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/027/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/027/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/027/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘एष कविः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं तृतीयं सूक्तं नृमेधनाम्न अङ्गिरसस्यार्षं गायत्रं सौम्यम् । ‘एष कविर्नृमेधः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;27 (739)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Nr̥medha  Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Though attributed to a different poet and a different poetic lineage, this hymn,  like the last one (IX.26), is unified by a repeated initial pronoun in every verse, in  this case “this one, he” (eṣá) referring to Soma. Again, the content is conventional,  though there is emphasis on Soma’s victories and acquisitions (vss. 1, 2, 3, 4) and  his successful competition with the sun (vss. 2, 5). The cosmic aspect of Soma is  thus raised but not insisted upon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/028/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/028/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/028/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘एष वाजी&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं चतुर्थं सूक्तं प्रियमेधस्यार्षं गायत्रं सौम्यम्। &amp;lsquo;एष वाजी प्रियमेधः । इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;28 (740)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Priyamedha Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Attributed to another Āṅgirasa, whose given name is similar to the poet of the last  hymn (IX.27), this follows the same pattern, with initial “he, that one” (eṣá) opening  every verse. Otherwise it is constructed of the usual clichés, though the rhetoric is  nicely balanced.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/029/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/029/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/029/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्रास्य&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं पञ्चमं सूक्तं नृमेधस्याङ्गिरसस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । अनुक्रम्यते च &amp;ndash; प्रास्य नृमेधः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;29 (741)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Nr̥medha  Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Another short and conventional hymn, with a focus on winning goods and con quering enemies (esp. vss. 3–5). It is attributed to the same poet as IX.27.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;01-परसय-धर---गयतर&#34;&gt;01 प्रास्य धारा - गायत्री&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;5&#34; title=&#34;विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/vishvAsa-prastutiH/09/029/01_prAsya_dhArA.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h5&gt;विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;प्र᳓ अस्य धा᳓रा अक्षरन्&lt;br&gt;&#xA;वृ᳓ष्णः सुत᳓स्य ओ᳓जसा&lt;br&gt;&#xA;देवाँ᳓ अ᳓नु प्रभू᳓षतः&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/030/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/030/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/030/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ प्र धाराः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं षष्ठं सूक्तं बिन्दुनाम्न आङ्गिरसस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । ‘ प्र धारा बिन्दुः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रमणिका । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;30 (742)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Bindu Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first verse of this hymn is very like the opening verse of IX.29, and it is con structed of the usual building blocks of soma hymns, particularly those in gāyatrī meter. It clusters especially closely with the three hymns that precede it: these four  hymns (IX.27–30) are all attributed to poets with the patronymic Āṅgirasa, and all  four contain at least one form of śúṣma “tempestuous force” or śuṣmín “tempestu ous” (IX.27.6; 28.6; 29.6; 30.1, 3), mostly in the final verse. This word thus seems  to be the signature of this little group of poets. (The word does not pattern closely  with other Āṅgirasa poets, even in the IXth Maṇḍala.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/031/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/031/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/031/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र सोमासः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं सप्तमं सूक्तं राहूगणस्य गोतमस्यार्षं सौम्यम्। &amp;lsquo;प्र सोमासो गोतमः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;31 (743)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Gotama Rāhūgaṇa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Another unremarkable gāyatrī hymn. Parallel constructions and phraseol ogy (e.g., the fronted “for you” [túbhyam] in vss. 3, 5, the fronted “be/become”  [bhávā] of vss. 2, 4) give a sense of unity. Unlike many soma hymns, where the  finale delivers the soma to Indra (e.g., the final verses of nearby hymns such as  IX.23.6–7, 26.6, 27.6, 30.6), here it is “we” who declare our desire for his pres ence and partnership (vs. 6).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poet, Gotama Rāhūgaṇa, is also the composer of a soma hymn in the first  maṇḍala, I.91, and verse 4 in this hymn is identical to I.91.16, which occurs in a  triad of ritually connected verses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/032/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/032/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/032/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र सोमासः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचमष्टमं सूक्तमात्रेयस्य श्यावाश्वस्यार्षं गायत्रं सौम्यम् । अनुक्रम्यते च- प्र सोमासः श्यावाश्वः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;32 (744)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Śyāvāśva Ātreya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Although this hymn begins with the almost ubiquitous journeying forth of the  soma juices (see, e.g., the first verses of IX.10, 17, 20, 24, 29, 30, 31, 33, 34, 41, 44,  all beginning, like this, with prá “forth” followed by a verb of motion somewhere in  the verse), it breaks the pattern of the recent collections of Soma clichés, especially  with the cascade of similes in verses 3–5. This expert handling of the constricted  form of gāyatrī soma hymns may lend credence to the Anukramaṇī’s attribution to  Śyāvāśva Ātreya, the ingenious poet of the Marut cycle in Maṇḍala V.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/033/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/033/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/033/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र सोमासः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं नवमं सूक्तं त्रितस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । ‘प्र सोमासस्त्रितः &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;33 (745)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Trita Āptya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Once again the hymn begins with the soma flowing forth. There is, however, less  emphasis on the physical process of purification, and more on the sounds that  accompany it: verse 4 introduces three voices, which may be the three types of ritual  speech, the r̥c, yajus, and sāman familiar from later śrauta ritual, or may refer to the  priestly formulations (5a), the bellowing of the cows (4b), and the roar of the rush&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ing soma itself (4c). The theme continues in verse 5, which also highlights “truth,”  found in verse 2 as well.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn is bookended by watery references: the simile of the waves of water  in verse 1 returns in the final verse (6) as the seas of wealth that soma will produce  for us.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/034/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/034/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/034/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र सुवानः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं दशमं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘प्र सुवानः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;34 (746)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Trita Āptya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins with the usual rushing forth of the soma, but achieves an unusual  ring, since in the last verse (6)  it is the songs that rush (using the same verb,  arṣa(n)ti) to him. What lies between is, for the most part, unremarkable. Verse 2  lists the recipients of the soma, a longer list than usual (and a verse almost identical  to vs. 3 in the previous hymn, IX.33), and verses 3–4 concern the preparation of  the drink. However, verse 5 is difficult: the Maruts milk for themselves (or yield as  their milk) the oblation in the direction of “the upper surface of truth.” Although  in the context of the hymn, soma should be the product of milking (see vs. 3), the  liquid the Maruts ordinarily milk is rain. Moreover, “the upper surface of truth”  is a puzzling phrase, which occurs elsewhere only in the mystical and baffling Vena  hymn (X.123.2). Since the latter hymn seems to concern the mystical identification  between soma and the sun, it is likely that here too we have double reference, with  the ritual substance soma assimilated to the cosmic fecundator, the rain, and “the  upper surface of truth” referring both to the soma filter and to heaven (or the res ervoir of rain in heaven).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/035/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/035/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/035/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ नः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचमेकादशं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्य प्रभूवसोरार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । अनुक्रान्तं च-’ आ नः पवस्व प्रभूवसुः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;35 (747)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Prabhūvasu Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma as the source and support of wealth and as ally in conflict is the theme of this  hymn, which is characterized by pleasing etymological figures (e.g., vss. 3, 4, 6) and  variant repetitions (e.g., vss. 2 + 5).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/036/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/036/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/036/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;असर्जि&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं द्वादशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । असर्जि&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;36 (748)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Prabhūvasu Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins with a noble image of Soma as a racehorse racing to the finish,  and the second verse contains another equine comparison, though with a more  lowly type of horse. This theme is abandoned until the final verse (6), when Soma  goes seeking horses for the worshipers. The hymn is otherwise a fairly standard  soma hymn, though one might note that the connection of soma with light made in  the previous hymn (attributed to the same poet), IX.35.1, is also found here in verse  3. Also, every verse but the last contains a form derived from the root pū “purify,”  always pāda-initial.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/037/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/037/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/037/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘स सुतः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं त्रयोदशं सूक्तं रहूगणस्यार्षं गायत्रं सौम्यम् । अनुक्रम्यते च-स सुतो रहूगणः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;37 (749)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Rahūgaṇa Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Several overt devices provide unity to this hymn: each verse begins with sá “he,”  and each verse but 4 contains a verb of motion (“rush, run, flow”) expressing the  journey of the soma through the filter and into the cups for Indra. In addition to  the mundane details of the preparation, however, the hymn makes cosmic claims for  the ritual actions. The sheep’s fleece of verse 3 also stands for “the luminous realms  of heaven”; in verse 5 Soma finds a wide realm, usually a symbol of freedom and  the acquisition of territory.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 4, the pause on the journey, has been much discussed, and its various  phrases, “on the back of Trita,” “along with (his) relatives,” also given cosmic ref erents (though there is no scholarly agreement on just what they are). We are of  the opinion, however, that it primarily concerns the ritual preparation: the “back  of Trita” is the filter and the “relatives” (jāmí) are, as usual in a soma context, the  fingers of the officiant, namely Trita (see “Trita’s maidens,” the fingers, in the next  hymn, IX.38.2). It is this ritual preparation that allows the cosmic act of Soma,  making the sun shine (at the Morning Pressing), in that same verse (4).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/038/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/038/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/038/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘एषः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं चतुर्दशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘एष उ स्यः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;38 (750)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Rahūgaṇa Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like the previous hymn, attributed to the same poet, this hymn is unified by the  repetition of a pronominal phrase at the beginning of every verse (eṣá syá “this  very one,” except for vs. 2, which has only the first pronoun). It, too, concerns  Soma’s journey through the filter (especially the first and last verses, 1 and 6) and  his manipulation by the officiant’s fingers (vss. 2, 3). The hymn is enlivened by meta&lt;br&gt;&#xA;phors and similes, particularly those of verse 4.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/039/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/039/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/039/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ आशुरर्ष&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं पञ्चदशं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्य बृहन्मतेरार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । ‘ आशुरर्ष बृहन्मतिः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;39 (751)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Brhanmati ̥ Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is structured as a ring of sorts: it begins and ends with quoted direct  speech, uttered by unidentified speakers but most likely priests. In verse 1 Soma  makes his journey through the filter to the place on the ritual ground where the  gods await their oblation. When he arrives there in verse 6, the priests order him to  take his seat. In between, Soma’s journey involves travel in both ritual and cosmic  space (see esp. vss. 2, 4).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/040/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/040/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/040/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘पुनानः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं षोडशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘पुनानः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;40 (752)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Brhanmati ̥ Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins with a martial theme that is not developed in what follows. Instead,  beginning with verse 3, the focus is on the wealth that Soma will bring us, and the  repetition of vocabulary in these four verses induces a sense of claustrophobia,  with the same elements recycled: “o Soma,” “o drop,” “purifying,” “bring us,” and  “wealth.” Although claustrophobia is to some extent endemic to the IXth Maṇḍala,  most hymns make some attempt to vary the lexicon and phraseology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/041/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/041/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/041/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र ये गावः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं सप्तदशं सूक्तं काण्वस्य मेध्यातिथेरार्षं  गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- प्र ये गावो मेध्यातिथिः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;41 (753)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Medhyātithi Kāṇva&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn and the next two (IX.41–43) are attributed to Medhyātithi Kāṇva,  the poet of several hymns in Maṇḍala VIII (VIII.1, 3, 33), who names himself  in IX.43.3. This hymn begins strikingly, with an incomplete sentence describing  the stampede of a wild mob, against the “black skin,” presumably the Dasyu  referred to in verse 2. The constituents of the mob are not identified, but are  presumably the soma juices, here mobilized against the non-Ārya enemy. The  second verse rewrites this scene more tranquilly, though with the victory over  the Dasyu more explicit. But the violence of Soma’s purificatory journey returns  in verse 3.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The second half of the hymn is more conventional, though with Soma’s cosmic  associations clear in the last two verses (5–6).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/042/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/042/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/042/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘जनयन्&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचमष्टादशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘जनयन्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;42 (754)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Medhyātithi Kāṇva&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The double affiliation of Soma with the ritual and cosmic realms leads off the  hymn: in verse 1 he performs major cosmogonic deeds while participating in his  ritual preparation, mixing with milk and being washed in water. This twofold theme  continues through the hymn, as, for example, in verse 4 where Soma begets the gods  while being poured in the filter. The hymn ends (vs. 6) with a wish for the same  material benefits found in the preceding hymn, IX.41.4.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/043/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/043/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/043/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यो अत्यइव&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचमेकोनविंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । “यो अत्यइव&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;43 (755)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Medhyātithi Kāṇva&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In this last hymn attributed to Medhyātithi, he is at particular pains to draw atten tion to the importance of the poet’s role in the preparation of the soma. Not only  does he name himself in verse 3, but the first three verses emphasize the clothing  (vs. 1), beautification (vs. 2), and adornment (vs. 3) of Soma with hymns. In the  final verse (6) he asks for a proper recompense for the poet (that is, himself) who  produces these hymns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/044/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/044/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/044/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥ यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथ सप्तमाष्टकस्य प्रथमाध्याय आरभ्यते । ‘प्र णः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं विंशं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्यायास्यस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- प्र णोऽयास्यः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;44 (756)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ayāsya Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poet of the next three hymns (IX.44–46) seems to owe his Anukramaṇī identifi cation to the word ayā́sya “irrepressible” in the first verse of this first hymn, where it  is applied to Soma. Insofar as there is a theme in this hymn, it is Soma’s relation to  the gods (vss. 1, 3, 5) and his intermediary role between the gods and us, especially  us poets (vss. 2, 5).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/045/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/045/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/045/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘स पवस्व&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचमेकविंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘स पवस्व &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;45 (757)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ayāsya Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn is defined by a thematic ring: Soma has his gaze on men in verse 1 and in  the final verse (6) he gazes out on the reward he gives to his human praiser. Soma,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/046/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/046/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/046/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ असृग्रन्&amp;rsquo; इति षडृ चं द्वाविंशं सूक्तम्। ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । “ असृग्रन्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;46 (758)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ayāsya Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn surveys some familiar themes, particularly the role of the fingers in prepar ing the soma (vss. 4, 6), though it is perhaps noteworthy that the filter, so prominent in  many soma hymns, is not explicitly present here. In contrast, some qualities of soma  known from elsewhere that are rarely or never mentioned in the IXth Maṇḍala make  their appearance—in particular his source in the mountains (vs. 1) and in verse 4 the  technical distinction between “pure” (that is, unmixed) soma (śukrá) and soma with  grain stirred in (manthín, a word otherwise only found once elsewhere in the R̥gveda  [III.32.2]). (In the later śrauta ritual, cups of śukra and manthin soma form both a  ritual and a grammatical pair, in the dual dvandva compound śukrā-manthinau, here  found in discontinuous form.) The gods Vāyu (vs. 2) and Indra (vss. 3, 6), recipients  of the first soma oblations at the Morning Pressing, are named. Verse 2 contains a  striking image of the soma drops adorned like a girl for marriage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/047/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/047/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/047/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘अया सोमः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं त्रयोविंशं सूक्तं भृगुपुत्रस्य कवेरार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम् &amp;ndash; ‘अया सोमः पञ्च कविर्भार्गवः&amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;47 (759)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kavi Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The next three hymns (IX.47–49) are attributed to Kavi Bhārgava, to whom the  Anukramaṇī also credits the five Jagatī hymns IX.75–79. The Soma of this hymn is  distinctly militant, using the power he has acquired (vs. 1) to destroy the Dasyus (vs.  2) and win spoils, as Indra’s very mace (vss. 3, 5). But the same Soma is both a poet  (vs. 4) and a recipient of poetry (vs. 3), who facilitates the human poet’s acquisition  of treasure from his patron (vs. 4).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/048/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/048/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/048/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ तं त्वा&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं चतुर्विशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘तं त्वा&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;48 (760)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kavi Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poet begins his hymn with a request for benefit, though a rather generic one (vs.  1). The militant theme of the previous hymn is visible in verse 2, while the story of  the falcon’s theft of Soma from heaven, a myth not prominent elsewhere in Maṇḍala  IX, is the subject of verses 3–4. Unlike most of the gāyatrī soma hymns, this one  contains no explicit reference to the preparation of the soma, with only a glancing  mention of the “impelling” of soma in the final verse (5), a term generally used in IX  of the push that starts the soma on its purificatory journey through the filter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/049/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/049/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/049/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘पवस्व&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं पञ्चविंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । “ पवस्व&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;49 (761)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kavi Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Each verse of this hymn contains a form (two in vs. 3)  of the root pū “purify,”  all verbs except for the “filter” word (pavítram) in verse 4; the three middle verses  (3–5) also all contain the instrumental dhā́rayā “in a stream.” The hymn thus has  a tight lexical structure, and the content is similarly limited, to wishes for rain as  refreshment and nourishment (vss. 1, 3–4) and for increase in cattle (vs. 3). The first  four verses contain imperatives addressed to Soma, the last verse a 3rd-person past  tense, suggesting that the wishes expressed have been fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/050/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/050/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/050/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘उत्ते&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं षड्विंशं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्योचथ्यस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्&amp;mdash;’ उत्ते शुष्मास उचथ्यः&amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;50 (762)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ucathya Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The next three hymns (IX.50–52) are attributed to the same poet, who is not otherwise  found in the R̥gveda. This hymn has a distinct focus on sound, that of Soma as he is  being prepared (vs. 1), of (probably) the officiating priests (vs. 3), and of the ritual  chant (vs. 4). A potential pun in verse 2 suggests that the priestly voices there are both  competing with each other and seeking the sacrificial reward. Verse 5 contains another  potential pun, with the same word (aktú) meaning both “ointments” and “nights.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/051/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/051/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/051/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘अध्वर्यो &amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं सप्तविंशं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्योचथ्यस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते-&amp;rsquo; अध्वर्यो &amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;51 (763)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ucathya Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This simple hymn sets Soma in relation both to the humans involved in his prepa ration, namely the Adhvaryu priest (vs. 1) and the praiser (vs. 4), and to the gods  who consume him, Indra (vss. 1–2), the gods in general, and the Maruts (vs. 3).  The entry into the filter, mentioned in verses 1 and 5, provides an elementary ring.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/052/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/052/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/052/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘परि द्युक्षः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चमष्टाविंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । “परि द्युक्षः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्तो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;52 (764)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ucathya Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Unlike the very straightforward preceding hymn (IX.51) attributed to the same  poet, this one is full of tricks, especially in the middle verse (3), which can thus  be viewed as an omphalos. The contents of the first two verses are conventional  enough—the entry of Soma into the filter—but they contain several instances of  phonological and morphological play, as do the final two verses (4–5). These cannot  be conveyed in translation.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 3, characterized by the repetition of the verb īṅkhaya (“push, shove”) of highly  marked formation, has a slangy and disparaging tone. Its object is generally interpreted,  in our opinion correctly, as a reference to an ungenerous rich man, perhaps the poet’s  patron. He is compared to a pot, no doubt both because he is full of goods and because  of his stodgy demeanor, and the soma drop is urged to prod this miser into giving.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Two matching compounds, sanád-rayiḥ “gaining wealth” (vs. 1)  and  maṃhayád-rayiḥ “readying wealth” (vs. 5), provide a thematic and grammatical ring.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/053/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/053/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/053/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘उत्ते&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचमेकोनत्रिंशं सूक्तं काश्यपस्यावत्सारस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुकान्तम्&amp;ndash; उत्ते चतुष्कमवत्सारः&amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;53 (765)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Avatsāra Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verse: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The next eight hymns (IX.53–60) are attributed to the same poet as V.44, a hymn  to the All Gods often declared to be the hardest hymn in the R̥gveda. Although  these brief soma hymns have some interesting features, they lack the mind-boggling  verbal pyrotechnics of that hymn.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;On the other hand, the organizing principle of V.44 is the double application of  each verse to two different divinities, Agni and Soma, with a lexicon ambiguous  enough to allow both interpretations. Something of the same thing is visible in this  hymn, in which each verse but the last (4) invites the audience to supply a refer&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ent different from the one meant. The first verse deploys clear Indraic vocabulary,  particularly the vocative “possessor of the stone,” though Soma can, and should,  be its subject. The first two-thirds of the second verse (2ab) suggest either Indra or  Soma as referent, until the 1st singular verb form “I will praise” that opens the last  pāda establishes the 1st-person speaker as the referent. Again, the third verse opens  like a verse to Varuṇa or another Āditya, and only the “self-purifying” that begins  the second pāda ties it to Soma. It is only the last verse that contains unmistakable  somian vocabulary and which, in its final pāda, clarifies the roles of the drop (índu)  and Indra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/054/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/054/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/054/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अस्य प्रत्नाम्&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं त्रिंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘ अस्य प्रत्नाम्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;54 (766)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Avatsāra Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like the last hymn, this one withholds unambiguous identification until the end  of the hymn, while employing suggestive vocabulary in the earlier verses. However,  unlike the last hymn, the poet does not try to mislead the audience into supplying&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/055/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/055/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/055/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“यवंयवं नः&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचमेकत्रिंशं सूक्तं काश्यपस्यावत्सारस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । ‘यवंयवम्&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;55 (767)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Avatsāra Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first three verses of the hymn are unified by a reference to the stalk (ándhas) of  the soma plant, although the role of the stalk is somewhat vague. Verse 1 is notable  for its mention of agriculture, though again the relevance is not entirely clear. The  martial Soma is on display in verse 4.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/056/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/056/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/056/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘परि सोमः&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं द्वात्रिंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । “परि सोमः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;56 (768)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Avatsāra Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first three verses of this simple hymn describe Soma’s journey in the filter (vs.  1), as the liquid separates into multiple streams in the channels of the fleece (vs. 2),  and his preparation by the fingers (vs. 3). The fourth verse then requests protection  for ourselves and our men, while urging the soma to flow for its divine recipients.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/057/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/057/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/057/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र ते धाराः&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं त्रयस्त्रिंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘प्र ते धाराः &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;57 (769)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Avatsāra Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In this little hymn, Soma is explicitly or implicitly compared to rain (vs. 1), a war rior (vs. 2), a law-abiding king or his subject (vs. 3), and a falcon in its nest (vs. 3).  The ambiguity of the term “keeping his commandments well, having good com mandments” in verse 3 allows the description to apply either to the imposer of the  commandments, the king, or to those who abide by them, the vassals. The final  verse (4) is, as so often, the locus of our requests.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/058/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/058/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/058/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘तरत्सः&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं चतुस्त्रिंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । “तरत्सः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् ।। उक्तो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;58 (770)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Avatsāra Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A curious little hymn or hymn-fragment. All four verses have a pāda-length refrain,  which is entirely applicable to Soma, and the hymn begins with this same refrain.  The first verse is clearly a soma verse throughout, but verse 2 is more appropriate to  Dawn and verses 3 and 4 appear to be an abbreviated dānastuti. The patrons named  in verse 3 are identified as protegés of the Aśvins in I.112.23 (though with the first in  slightly different form); middle Vedic literature also has a confused tradition about  these same personages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/059/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/059/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/059/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘पवस्व &amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं पञ्चत्रिंशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । &amp;rsquo; पवस्व&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;59 (771)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Avatsāra Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Each of the four verses contains at least one form of “purify oneself/self-purifying,”  with three such imperatives in verse 2. That verse seems to contain a trio of elemental  substances, which are also connected with the ritual: waters, plants, and, in our interpre tation, the hearths as holy places, representative of fire. Soma as finder of good things  for us provides a thematic ring for the hymn; in verse 1 he finds the material and psy chological goods men desire, while in verse 4 he has raised the stakes to the cosmic level.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/060/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/060/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/060/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र गायत्रेण&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं षट्त्रिंशं सूक्तं काश्यपस्यावत्सारस्यार्षम्। तृतीया पुरउष्णिगाद्यद्वादशका द्व्यष्टका । शिष्टा गायत्र्यः । पवमानः सोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- प्र गायत्रेणोपान्त्या पुरउष्णिक्&amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;60 (772)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Avatsāra Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: gāyatrī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A satisfyingly tight structure knits together this little hymn. The first and last verses  contain the epithet “boundless” (vícarṣaṇi) providing a faint ring. More salient is  the chaining from verse to verse: a significant portion of the final pāda of one verse  opens the next verse.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn also has extra-hymnic structural echoes: its final pāda is identical to  the final pāda of the first verse of the preceding hymn (IX.59.1), ascribed to the  same poet, save for “semen” in place of “treasure.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/061/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/061/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/061/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तृतीयेऽनुवाके सप्त सूक्तानि । तत्र ‘अया वीती&amp;rsquo; इति त्रिंशदृचं प्रथमं सूक्तम् । अमहीयुर्नामाङ्गिरस ऋषिः । गायत्री छन्दः । पवमानः सोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्- अया वीती त्रिंशदमहीयुः&amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;61 (773)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Amahīyu Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;30 verses: gāyatrī, arranged in trcas ̥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first sixty hymns of the Soma Maṇḍala, all in gāyatrī meter, are arranged in the  normal order of descending number of verses, starting with hymns of ten verses  and ending with those of four. (The only exception is the Āprī hymn, IX.5, which  has eleven.) But the gāyatrī sequence ends with six thirty-verse hymns (IX.61–66),  followed by one with thirty-two verses (IX.67)—all arranged in tr̥cas (the final two  verses in IX.67 are supplements) and each attributed to a different poet or group  of poets—before the jagatī group begins. It is probably not an accident that these  groupings of tr̥cas come at the end of the gāyatrī sequence, since, as agglomerations  of three-verse sequences, they logically follow the four-verse hymns.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In this particular hymn there is little evidence of unity either within tr̥cas or between  them: the standard topics of soma hymns—the details of preparation (e.g., vss. 4–5)  and the gods for whom he’s prepared (e.g., vss. 8–9), the cosmic connections of Soma  (e.g., vss. 10, 16, 18), and the largesse and aid we ask him for (e.g., vss. 3, 23–24)—&lt;br&gt;&#xA;are strung together in no apparent order. There is a discernible tendency, however, to  emphasize Soma’s role in combating hostile forces, either directly or by strengthening  someone else to do so, especially Indra. The hymn begins with two verses mention ing some of Indra’s exploits performed under the influence of Soma, though without&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/062/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/062/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/062/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘एते असृग्रम्&amp;rsquo; इति त्रिंशदृचं द्वितीयं सूक्तं भार्गवस्य जमदग्नेरार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्&amp;ndash; एते असृग्रं जमदग्निः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;62 (774)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Jamadagni Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;30 verses: gāyatrī, arranged in trcas ̥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Though long, this hymn remains focused on the familiar details of the preparation  of the soma, often ennobled by establishing cosmic parallels. The journey across1284 IX.62&lt;br&gt;&#xA;the fleece is especially prominent, and the soma is frequently likened to a fast horse.  One verse, 17, is more specific than the usual generic treatments: here the soma is  a horse yoked to the chariot of the sacrifice, which has three backs and three seats,  presumably the three pressings and the three fires, by the visionary thoughts of the  seven seers. It is also notable how often Soma is called a poet or connected with  poetry in the second part of this hymn (vss. 13, 14, 25, 26, 27, 30). In the final verse  he is in fact called “the entruthed poet” or “the poet (who is) truth (itself),” a power&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ful expression of his relationship to creative speech.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Though some of the tr̥cas display internal formal unity (e.g., vss. 19–21 begin ning with ā́), most do not. The poet to whom the hymn is attributed names himself  in verse 24.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/063/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/063/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/063/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ पवस्व&amp;rsquo; इति त्रिंशदृचं तृतीयं सूक्तं काश्यपस्य निध्रुवेरार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्- आ पवस्व निध्रुविः काश्यपः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;63 (775)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Nidhruvi Kāśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;30 verses: gāyatrī, arranged in trcas ̥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like the last hymn, this one is much concerned with the ritual preparation of soma,  but it sketches a larger conceptual world in which this preparation takes place. On the  one hand, the purification is seen as a process of Ārya-ization (vs. 5), and the spaces  that Soma traverses, for example the filter, become “Ārya domains” (vs. 14). The waters  that Soma crosses (vss. 5, 21) and the rivers in which he is groomed (vs. 17) are both  the ritual waters in which the soma plant is rinsed and rehydrated and, metaphorically,  the frontier rivers the Āryas crossed in expanding their realms. (See also the mentions  of finding or making “wide space” in the two preceding hymns [IX.61.12; 62.3, 9].)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;On the other hand, Soma is compared to and identified with the Sun (espe cially in the third tr̥ca, vss. 7–9, also vs. 13), and his journey across the filter is also  metaphorically the Sun’s daily journey across the heaven. Since the ritual activity  happens on earth, at the hands of Manu (vss. 7–8), the first sacrificer and the cul tural ancestor of the Ārya, even the rising of the Sun is thus implicitly attributed  to human agency.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn is, of course, also full of requests for material goods of all sorts, and,  especially toward the end, for Soma to smite all manner of enemies and hostile  forces (vss. 24, 26, 28–29; also 5).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Although the hymn does not seem tightly structured, some tr̥cas show formal  unity (e.g., vss. 25–27 with forms of the root sr̥j “surge”), and the hymn begins and  ends with verses containing the imperative dhāraya “secure, sustain.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/064/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/064/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/064/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘वृषा सोम&amp;rsquo; इति त्रिंशदृचं चतुर्थं सूक्तं मारीचस्य कश्यपस्यार्षं गायत्रं पवमानसौम्यम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- वृषा सोम कश्यपः&amp;rsquo; इति । उक्तो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;64 (776)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kaśyapa Mārīca&lt;br&gt;&#xA;30 verses: gāyatrī, arranged in trcas ̥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins with an insistent tr̥ca establishing Soma as a bull. What follows is  for the most part a conventional treatment of the purification process, with special  emphasis on his entry into “the sea” (that is, the purificatory waters, vss. 8, 16, 17,  19, 27). The association with the Sun found in the preceding hymn is also present  here, with Soma not merely yoking the Sun’s horse, Etaśa, but identified with him  (vs. 19) and with the Sun himself in the final words of the hymn (vs. 30; see also  vss. 7, 9). Soma’s light and brilliance are also mentioned throughout (vss. 1, 8, 13,  15, 28).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/065/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/065/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/065/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ हिन्वन्ति&amp;rsquo; इति त्रिंशदृचं पञ्चमं सूक्तं वरुणपुत्रस्य भृगोरार्षं भार्गवस्य जमदग्नेर्वा गायत्रं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते&amp;ndash; हिन्वन्ति भृगुर्वारुणिर्जमदग्निर्वा &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;65 (777)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Bhrgu V ̥ āruṇi or Jamadagni Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;30 verses: gāyatrī, arranged in trcas ̥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Even in this maṇḍala devoted to “self-purifying” Soma, the constant repetition of  that epithet and its associated verbal forms (“purify yourself,” etc.) in this hymn is  remarkable. In particular, the idiom “by purifying yourself bring here &amp;hellip;” (much  more economically expressed in Sanskrit by ā́ pavasva) is insistent, along with other  demands that Soma bring or convey goods here. Intermingled are verses treating the familiar details of soma preparation. All in all, the hymn seems flat, uninspired,  and repetitive.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The tr̥ca consisting of verses 22–24 breaks the monotony to some degree, with  the first two verses listing various places where the soma may be pressed (the  meaning of some of these words is disputed and their translation provisional),  and only the third returning to the dominant theme of the hymn. The final tr̥ca  (vss. 28–30) brings the hymn to a close with a flurry of repetitions of the preverb  ā́ “here, hither,” in a list of items we wish to bring to hand as a result of the soma  offering.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/066/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/066/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/066/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘पवस्व&amp;rsquo; इति त्रिंशदृचं षष्ठं सूक्तम् । अत्रानुक्रम्यते- पवस्व शतं वैखानसा अष्टादश्यनुष्टुप्परास्तिस्र आग्नेय्यः&amp;rsquo; इति । शतसंख्याका वैखानसाख्याः संहता ऋषयः । ‘ त्वं सोम सूरः &amp;rsquo; इत्येषानुष्टुप् । शिष्टा गायत्र्यः । ‘ अग्न आयूंषि&amp;rsquo; इत्याद्यास्तिस्रः पवमानविशिष्टाग्निदेवताकाः । अन्यासां पवमानः सोमो देवता । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;66 (778)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna, except Agni 19–21&lt;br&gt;&#xA;One hundred Vaikhānasa poets&lt;br&gt;&#xA;30 verses: gāyatrī (except anuṣṭubh 18), arranged in trcas ̥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn sets larger rhetorical goals for itself than the last one and inhabits  a less airless rhetorical space. Indeed, the hymn is in part about space: the con stricted area in which the soma is prepared and the materials employed in the  preparation are likened to various cosmic domains and natural phenomena (see,  e.g., vss. 2–3, 5–6, 12–13). Soma himself is explicitly or implicitly identified with  other deities and natural forces, and they with him:  the sun (vss. 18, 22, 27),  probably Indra (vs. 26), and especially Agni (vss. 19–21). This last identification  is so complete that the Anukramaṇī identifies Agni as the divinity of this tr̥ca— not surprisingly, as it begins (vs. 19) with an address to Agni, who is assigned  the archetypal Soma epithet “self-purifying” (vs. 20, with verbal forms in vss. 19  and 21), while also keeping his own characteristic vocabulary (esp. “installed in  front” [puróhita] vs. 20).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The poet also seeks comradeship with Soma (vss. 1, 4, 14, 18), in addition to the  usual good things.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;From an Indo-European perspective, the hymn is notable for containing one of  three R̥gvedic occurrences of the famous phrase ákṣiti śrávaḥ “imperishable fame,”  cognate with Greek kléos áphthiton “idem,” and the formula, identified by Adelbert  Kuhn in 1853, that launched the field of comparative Indo-European poetics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/067/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/067/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/067/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;त्वं सोमासि&amp;rsquo; इति द्वात्रिंशदृचं सप्तमं सूक्तम् । आद्यतृचस्य बार्हस्पत्यो भरद्वाज ऋषिः । द्वितीयस्य मारीचः कश्यपः । तृतीयस्य राहूगणो गोतमः । चतुर्थस्य भौमोऽत्रिः । पञ्चमस्य गाथिनो विश्वामित्रः । षष्ठस्य भार्गवो जमदग्निः । सप्तमस्य मैत्रावरुणिर्वसिष्ठः । सूक्तशेषस्याङ्गिरसः पवित्रो वसिष्ठो वोभौ वा समुदितावृषी । ‘ पवस्व सोम मन्दयन् &amp;rsquo; इत्याद्यास्तिस्रो द्विपदा गायत्र्यः । अलाय्यस्य&amp;rsquo; इत्येषा त्रिंशी पुरउष्णिक् आद्यद्वादशकद्व्यष्टकवती सप्तविंश्येकत्रिंशीद्वात्रिंश्यस्तिस्रोऽनुष्टुभः । शिष्टा गायत्र्यः । ‘ अविता नो अजाश्वः&amp;rsquo; इत्याद्यास्तिस्रः पवमानपूषदेवत्याः पवमानसोमदेवताका वा । ‘ यत्ते पवित्रमर्चिषि&amp;rsquo; इत्याद्याः पञ्चर्चः पवमानाग्निदेवत्याः । आसां पञ्चानां मध्ये उभाभ्यां देव सवितः&amp;rsquo; इति तृतीया पवमानसवितृदेवताका वा । चतुर्थी त्रिभिष्ट्वं देव सवितः इत्येषा विकल्पेन पवमानाग्निसवितृदेवताका । ‘पुनन्तु माम्&amp;rsquo; इत्येषा विकल्पेन वैश्वदेवी । ‘ यः पवमानीरध्येति&amp;rsquo; इत्यादिके द्वे पवमानमण्डलाध्येतृस्तुतिप्रतिपादिके। अतः सैव देवता । शिष्टाः सर्वाः पवमानसोमदेवताकाः । तथा चानुक्रम्यते-’ त्वं सोमासि द्वात्रिंशद्भरद्वाजः कश्यपो गोतमोऽत्रिर्विश्वामित्रो जमदग्निर्वसिष्ठ इति ह तृचाः सप्त ऋषयः शेषे पवित्रो वसिष्ठो वोभौ वा पवस्व सोम तिस्रो नित्यद्विपदा गायत्र्योऽविता नस्तिस्रः पौष्ण्यो वा यत्ते पवित्रं पञ्चाग्नेय्यः सावित्र्यग्निसावित्री वैश्वदेवी वासामन्त्यास्त्रिंशी पुरउष्णिक् सप्तविंश्यनुष्टुबन्त्ये च ते पावमान्यध्येतृस्तुती&amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/068/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/068/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/068/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;चतुर्थेऽनुवाकेऽष्टादश सूक्तानि । तत्र ‘प्र देवम्&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं प्रथमं सूक्तं भलन्दनपुत्रस्य वत्सप्रेरार्षं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । दशमी त्रिष्टुप् शिष्टा जगत्यः । तथा चानुक्रम्यते- प्र देवं दश वत्सप्रिर्भालन्दनस्त्रिष्टुबन्तं ह&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;68 (780)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vatsaprī Bhālandana&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: jagatī, except triṣṭubh 10&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first of the Soma hymns in jagatī meter (IX.68–86), this poem well dem onstrates the increased possibilities for verbal and conceptual richness that the  longer meter affords, in contrast to the concision and constriction of gāyatrī.  The hymn has an omphalos structure: since verse 10 is a summary verse and in  a different meter (triṣṭubh), verse 5 is the middle verse and encodes the esoteric  knowledge that is the hymn’s message. This verse is framed by a number of verbal  and semantic responsions (though not as tightly arranged as in some omphalos  hymns): for instance, the fingers of verses 4 and 7, as well as the same phrase “held  by men” in both verses; the forms of the root vid “find, discover” in verses 3 and  6 (and 9).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;More important is the conceptual architecture: the hymn leads up to the ompha los and away from it, returning to its conceptual starting point. It begins with the ritual soma and the familiar details of its preparation (vss. 1–2): the journey across  the filter and the mixing with milk, complete with details about the actual filtering  process, as the juice leaves its detritus in the filter. But toward the end of verse 2, the  journey gains a larger resonance, however vague: soma circles “the wide expanse,”  an area that sounds more ample than a mere sheep’s fleece. In verses 3 and 4 the  journey has turned cosmic: heaven and earth are now the domain for Soma’s travel  and for his fecundating activity, and in our view the contrast between Soma’s swell&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ing footprint in 4b and his head in 4d expresses his cosmic reach, from his feet on  earth, swelling with rain, to his distant head in heaven.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 5, the omphalos, provides an explanation, albeit a mystical one, for the  difference between the ritual soma of the first two verses and the cosmic one of  verses 3–4. He really had two births, one in secret even beyond the two worlds and  one made evident to all. And as a consequence there are actually two Somas, a fact  first recognized by Heaven and Earth. (Such is our reading of this verse, which has  generally been interpreted quite differently: one influential opinion identifies the  Aśvins as the twins mentioned, a solution of desperation in our opinion.)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The second form of Soma, the physical and visible one, is brought to earth in  verse 6, and the poets and ritualists transform him into the ritual soma now familiar  to us. The remaining verses before the summary (7–9) bring us back to the current  ritual soma with which we began, but with a clearer awareness of the powers his  dual nature has bestowed on him. For example, in verse 1 the drops are simply “pro&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vided with speech,” but in verses 8–9 Soma “rouses speech” all the way to heaven.  Similarly, in verse 2 he simply “circles around” the wide expanse, whereas in 9d, the  last pāda of the hymn proper, he “finds” wide space, a feat much desired and much  celebrated by the Vedic Āryas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/069/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/069/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/069/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;इषुर्न&amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्य हिरण्यस्तूपस्यार्षं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । नवमीदशम्यौ त्रिष्टुभौ । शिष्टा जगत्यः । तथा चानुक्रान्तम् - &amp;rsquo; इषुर्न हिरण्यस्तूपोऽन्त्ये त्रिष्टुभौ &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;69 (781)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Hiraṇyastūpa Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: jagatī, except triṣṭubh 10&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Attributed to the same poet as the author of the famous Indra hymn I.32 (and  indeed I.31–35, as well as IX.4), this hymn is dense with ever-shifting imagery,  expressed in many forms: similes, metaphors, identifications. Sometimes several ref erents are simultaneously possible, as in verse 1, where both “thought” and “soma”  could be the subject of the middle part of the verse. This verbal richness is quite  appropriate, since at least the first two verses concern the poetic impulse; note the  nice description of the tongue as “the gladdening goad” in 2b.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The middle verses (3–7) treat Soma’s journey across the filter to meet and mix  with the cows/milk. This mixture is described in increasingly elaborate images of  clothing in verses 4–5, ending with the cosmos as his garment (5cd). The journey is  completed in the first half of verse 7, and the hymn comes to a more conventional  ending with prayers for goods and aid.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/070/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/070/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/070/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ त्रिरस्मै &amp;rsquo; इति दशर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तं वैश्वामित्रस्य रेणोरार्षम् । दशमी त्रिष्टुप् शिष्टा जगत्यः ।। पवमानः सोमो देवता । &amp;rsquo; त्रिरस्मै रेणुः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;70 (782)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Reṇu Viśvāmitra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;10 verses: jagatī, except triṣṭubh 10&lt;br&gt;&#xA;An intricate and difficult hymn, some of whose puzzles remain unsolved. The  theme of the hymn is the difference between, and ultimate unity of, heavenly Soma  and earthly, ritual Soma—a theme that was also the subject of nearby IX.68. The  disjunction is announced in the first verse, where the “real” milk-mixture is pro&lt;br&gt;&#xA;duced in heaven, and the worlds are Soma’s garment. In verse 2, by contrast, it  seems that the earthly Soma is seeking a share of his heavenly counterpart by per forming cosmic deeds through ritual means. A rapprochement is effected in verse  3, where Soma’s beacons (kétu) go to and work upon both men and gods, and as a  consequence they accept him as their king; on the basis of other passages in which  this term is found, the beacons appear to be both his cosmic sunlike rays and the  glinting streams of ritual soma as they circle in the filter. The intermediary role of  Soma between gods and men and Heaven and Earth remains the subject of the fol lowing verses (4–6), though not all is clear, especially the first half of verse 4 and  the last half of verse 6. The last four verses (7–10) return us to the ritual Soma and  his ultimate goal, the body of Indra, but the cosmic associations he acquired in the  earlier parts of the hymn make him nourishment fit for the gods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/071/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/071/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/071/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘आ दक्षिणा&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं चतुर्थं सूक्तं वैश्वामित्रस्यर्षभस्यार्षं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । नवमी त्रिष्टुप् शिष्टा जगत्यः । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्-‘ आ दक्षिणा नव ऋषभस्तौ वैश्वामित्रौ&amp;rsquo; इति । ‘तौ&amp;rsquo; इत्यनेन प्रकृतो रेणुर्ऋषभश्चोभे परामृश्येते । श्रूयते हि-&amp;rsquo; अथ ह विश्वामित्रः पुत्रानामन्त्रयामास मधुच्छन्दाः शृणोतन ऋषभो रेणुरष्टकः&amp;rsquo; (ऐ. ब्रा. ७. १७) इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;71 (783)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;R̥ṣabha Vaiśvāmitra&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: jagatī, except triṣṭubh 9&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The subject of this hymn is, as so often, Soma’s journey across the filter to take  his seat as ritual drink after the various stages of preparation. The journey is pre sented as a straightforward trajectory on the one hand, with his arrival among  the gods and his union with the praise hymn the last step, in verse 8. But the  hymn is also structured by a number of responsions between the earlier and the  later verses; note especially 2b and 8a, with the almost identical phrases “the  color that is his” and “this is his color.” In this particular example the forward  movement of the journey and the architectonic structure of responsions comple ment each other, for in verse 2 Soma sheds his original form and color and in  verse 8 he gains new ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/072/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/072/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/072/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ हरिं मृजन्ति &amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं पञ्चमं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्य हरिमन्तस्यार्षं, पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । ‘ जागतमूर्ध्वं प्रागुशनसः&amp;rsquo; ( अनु. ९.६७ ) इति परिभाषया जागतम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- हरिं मृजन्ति हरिमन्तः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;72 (784)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Harimanta Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The role of humans in both the physical and the verbal preparation of Soma is  emphasized in this hymn. The first verse sets this tone, with the anonymous priestly subjects of “they groom” of pāda a and the anonymous praisers who impel the  soma in the second half, a division of labor found as well in verse 2; see also verses  4–6, 8. The exact responsion of the last parts of 4d and 5b seem to mark an ompha los, but there is little other evidence for such a structure.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn contains one major problem: the hapax vinaṃgr̥sá in 3c. The phrase ology in this pāda is strongly suggestive of erotic slang, but unfortunately the word  has so far defeated all attempts to decode it. It is worth noting, however, that it is a  partial anagram of the patronymic of the poet Harimanta Āṅgirasa, and he may be  punning on his name in this playful, erotic context.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/073/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/073/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/073/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘स्रक्वे&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं षष्ठं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्य पवित्रस्यार्षं जागतं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते- स्रक्वे पवित्रः&amp;rsquo; इति । प्रवर्ग्येऽभिष्टव एतत् सूक्तम् । सूत्रितं च-&amp;rsquo; स्रक्वे द्रप्सस्यायं वेनश्चोदयत्पृश्निगर्भाः &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ४.६ ) इति ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;73 (785)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Pavitra Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A complex and enigmatic hymn, whose difficulties stem primarily from the double  system of reference that pervades the hymn. The signature phrase is “they have  sounded in unison” (sám asvaran, vss. 1, 4, 5, 6); in none of its occurrences is there  an overt subject, an omission that is surely deliberate. The verb forms in ques&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tion, and indeed most of the hymn, can be interpreted as referring either to the  soma streams as they noisily cross the filter or to the priests/poets who provide  the hymns that accompany soma’s journey. This double reference is found even in  the name of the poet to whom the hymn is attributed: Pavitra (“Filter”): the filter  is both the sheep’s wool filter that purifies the soma and the poet who creates the  ritual speech; the word pavítra occurs several times in the hymn (vss. 3, 7, 8, 9, and  implicitly 4). The “solution” to the central riddle of the hymn, this dual reference,  is suggested in the first half of verse 7 and definitely expressed in the final verse  (9), where “the thread of truth” (r̥tásya tántuḥ) is stretched both on the filter and  on the tongue-tip. The thread may be both the track of the soma across the filter  and the continuous line of speech. The second half of the verse emphasizes the  importance of united action to attain it, and the necessity of always advancing.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Another thematic strain is the deployment of the power of this unified sound  against enemies and hostile forces (see esp. vss. 5, 6, 8), a power associated with  Varuṇa and his māyā́ (“magic power, artifice,” vss. 5 and 9), with whom Soma is  identified, first in verse 3.  Varuṇa is of course the protector of commandments  (vratá, vss. 3, 5, 8) and is associated with truth/true speech (r̥tá, vss. 1, 6, 8, 9), words  prominent in the hymn. Thus, Soma, as the embodiment of Varuṇa, and the poets  who assist him can marshal Varuṇa’s weapon, “true speech,” against forces that  deny or attempt to thwart it.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Many individual puzzles remain, but the overall structure and purpose of the  hymn are clear.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/074/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/074/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/074/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘शिशुर्न&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं सप्तमं सूक्तं दैर्घतमसस्य कक्षीवत आर्षं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । अष्टमी त्रिष्टुप् शिष्टा जगत्यः । तथा चानुक्रम्यते- शिशुर्न कक्षीवांस्त्रिष्टुबष्टमी&amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;74 (786)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kakṣīvant Dairghatamasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: jagatī, except triṣṭubh 8&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is attributed to Kakṣīvant, the skilled and crafty poet of I.116–126,  who names himself in verse 8. Although it is not as intricate as some of his Ist  Maṇḍala productions, it invites the same sort of double readings as the previous&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/075/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/075/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/075/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘अभि प्रियाणि &amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चमष्टमं सूक्तं भार्गवस्य कवेरार्षं जागतं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथानुक्रम्यते-’ अभि प्रियाणि पञ्च कविः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;75 (787)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kavi Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma’s deep, almost reflexive, involvement in verbal products and production is  the subject of the first two verses of the hymn. He strengthens himself on his own  names in verse 1, and in verse 2 is both the physical (tongue, speaker) and concep tual (father) source of truth and insight. In the second half of verse 2, in the sort of  paradox much beloved by R̥gvedic seers, he not only knows the hidden names but  as son bestows them on his parents.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The remaining three verses are more conventionally concerned with the prepara tion of the ritual soma, though his connection with cosmic entities remains clear,  especially in verse 4.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn and the four following (IX.75–70) are attributed to the same poet as  the gāyatrī hymns IX.47–49.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/076/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/076/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/076/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे  तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;व्याख्यायाव्याहतप्रज्ञः सप्तमस्य द्वितीयकम् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अध्यायं सायणामात्यस्तृतीयं व्याकरोत्यथ ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तत्र ‘ धर्ता &amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं नवमं सूक्तं भार्गवस्य कवेरार्षं जागतं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । ‘धर्ता&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;76 (788)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kavi Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This portrait of Soma militant resembles the martial spirit of another of Kavi  Bhārgava’s hymns, IX.47. The dense series of combative images also track Soma’s  journey through the purificatory procedure, and his warlike power is to be har nessed for our own ends in the final verse (5). But Soma is not merely a warrior; he  is also a master of verbal art, who triumphs in poetic competitions (vs. 4). A short  but very satisfying poem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/077/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/077/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/077/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘एष प्र कोशे&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्च दशमं सूक्तम् । ऋष्यांद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘एषः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;77 (789)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kavi Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In addition to familiar tropes of soma-preparation (e.g., vss. 1, 3, 4), the hymn  briefly treats the famous myth in which a falcon steals soma from heaven (vs.  2), with one of the few R̥gvedic mentions of the heavenly archer Kr̥śānu, who  attempted retaliation. As noted, verse 4 for the most part is a standard soma verse,  but pāda c skates fleetingly and unemphatically over an apparent paradox, with a male Soma conceiving himself as his own embryo. In the final verse Soma is com pared to Varuṇa, because of his control over truth and deceit, and to Mitra, in his  role as mediator among communities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/078/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/078/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/078/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ प्र राजा वाचम्&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चमेकादशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘प्र राजा&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;78 (790)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kavi Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A fairly straightforward hymn. The first three verses treat the preparation of the  soma: after being swollen with water it is sent forth into the filter, which captures  the plant detritus, on its way to the milk mixture (vs. 1); it goes across the filter and  into the cup (vs. 2); and it is mixed with waters, here unusually personified as the  nymph-like females, the Apsarases (vs. 3). The last two verses list the benefits that  will accrue to us when the gods drink the soma.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/079/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/079/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/079/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ अचोदसः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं द्वादशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘ अचोदसः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;79 (791)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kavi Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The combative spirit of this hymn is reminiscent of that in other hymns attributed  to Kavi Bhārgava, especially IX.47 and IX.76. The hymn is especially interesting  because of the light it throws on social divisions in the R̥gvedic period. The word arí (vss. 1, 3), here translated “stranger” following Thieme (1938), is a much-discussed  and much-contested one, underlying as it does derivatives such as ā́rya “Ārya.”  We are of the opinion that an arí is a member of the larger Ārya society, but not  of one’s immediate community. He is thus a stranger, but one with whom one in  principle shares social values and to whom one owes certain reciprocal duties, such  as hospitality. But as a stranger he may also pose a threat to the smaller community  one belongs to, if he exhibits hostility rather than a communal spirit. The scenario  sketched in this hymn involves the latter type of arí, whose hostility menaces the  success of our sacrifice (vs. 1). Verse 3 is quite explicit about the affinity of the  arí: he is “one of our own,” while a person who does not belong to the larger Ārya  society is called a “wolf,” an outlaw, when his actions threaten us. The poet calls on  Soma to destroy both types of enemies.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 4 provides a brief interlude, outlining the cosmic dimensions of Soma— from heaven to earth, where his “fingers,” the shoots of the plant, grow—and a few  details of the preparation, vividly rendered. This verse cleverly incorporates four  different body parts (navel, fingers, skin, and hands) each belonging to a different entity. The final verse summarizes the process of pressing and calls once more for  Soma to display his feistiness on our behalf.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/080/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/080/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/080/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘सोमस्य धारा&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं त्रयोदशं सूक्तं भारद्वाजस्य वसुनाम्न आर्षं जागतं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- सोमस्य वसुर्भारद्वाजः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;80 (792)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasu Bhāradvāja&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;On the one hand, this hymn is somewhat static, stuck at the same stage of soma’s  preparation, as the almost exact responsion of the last two verses (4–5) emphasizes.  On the other hand, Soma’s relationship with the gods, especially Indra, a relation ship that figures in every verse, enlarges the conceptual frame of the hymn and  keeps it from seeming airless.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/081/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/081/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/081/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र सोमस्य&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं चतुर्दशं सूक्तम् । ऋषिदेवते पूर्ववत् । अन्त्या त्रिष्टुप् शिष्टा जगत्यः । ‘प्र सोमस्य&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;81 (793)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasu Bhāradvāja&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī, except triṣṭubh 5&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Attributed to the same poet as the preceding hymn (IX.80), this hymn concerns  itself even more strongly with Soma’s connection with the gods, devoting the final  two verses of a five-verse hymn to a litany of gods invited to the soma sacrifice. The  preceding verse contains two occurrences of the word vásu “good (one),” which is  also the name of the poet. Soma’s task of mediating between the world of gods and  men is treated in verse 2, anticipating the appeal for his help to the poet in verse 3  and the invitation to the gods in verses 4–5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/082/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/082/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/082/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘असावि&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं पञ्चदशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । अत्रानुक्रमणिका– असावीति त्रिष्टुबन्ते&amp;rsquo; इति । अनेन द्विवचनेन प्रकृतयोः ‘प्र सोमस्य&amp;rsquo; इत्यादिकयोर्द्वयोरपि त्रिष्टुबन्तता प्रतिपादिता । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;82 (794)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasu Bhāradvāja&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī, except triṣṭubh 5&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first two verses of this hymn are conventional treatments of Soma’s journey  across the filter and his mixing with milk (here called ghee). Verse 3, however, is more  cryptically phrased, and the name Soma is not mentioned. He appears as a buffalo  with feathers and/or leaves, and his father is Parjanya (“thunder”): the image is of a  plant produced by the rains. As often, his home is in the mountains, here identified  as the navel of the earth. And the rinsing waters, the milk, and the pressing stones  of the ritual preparation appear in the second half of the verse. Verse 4 is notable  for its 1st-person singular speaker; the abrupt phrase “Listen:  I  am speaking to  you” is reminiscent of the famous command given by the goddess Speech (Vāc) in  X.125.4 “Listen to me, you who are listened to. It’s a trustworthy thing I tell you.”  First-person singular speech is quite rare in Maṇḍala IX. The combination of a rid dling middle verse and the poet’s announcement of his own speech is reminiscent of  omphalos hymns, though there is little other support for such a structure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/083/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/083/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/083/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;पवित्रं ते &amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं षोडशं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्य पवित्रस्यार्षं जागतं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं-’ पवित्रं ते पवित्रः&amp;rsquo; इति । अभिष्टव आद्ये ऋचौ वक्तव्ये । सूत्रितं च&amp;mdash;’ पवित्रं ते विततं ब्रह्मणस्पत इति द्वे वि यत्पवित्रं धिषणा अतन्वत &amp;rsquo; ( आश्व. श्रौ. ४, ६) इति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;83 (795)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Pavitra Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;A well-known hymn, whose manifold difficulties are also well known. It in many  ways resembles the famous Vena hymn, X.123, which also involves a mystical iden tification between Soma and the sun. The double meanings and enigmas are, as  often, fostered by the suppression of overt reference. Crucial verbs lack expressed  subjects, and unidentified asya “of him/it” substitutes for expressed possession (see  2b, 2c, 3c, 4a). The word sóma does not appear in the hymn at all, nor do his com mon epithets. The hymn has elicited many different and contradictory interpreta tions, to which we add our own.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Attributed to the same poet as IX.73, this hymn shares with that earlier one  the mystical metaphor of the filter (pavítra), which is also the name of the poet.  Indeed, the words “outstretched” and “filter,” construed with each other in the last  verse of IX.73 (vs. 9), open this hymn, and the two verses (73.9 and 83.1) both con&lt;br&gt;&#xA;cern the qualities required to attain the filter and what it represents. In this hymn  the necessary quality is being cooked, rather than raw; it is somewhat startling to  encounter this whiff of Claude Lévi-Strauss very much avant la lettre. In this con text “cooked” must refer in the first instance to the ritual preparation of soma.  Although this preparation does not involve literal cooking, via application of heat,  it clearly turns the raw material extracted from the natural plant into a cultural  product, both through physical manipulation and through verbal accompaniment.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;But the filter metaphor has a cosmic dimension, as is especially clear in verse  2, where it is compared to the sun with its rays spread across the sky like the  tracks of the soma across the filter. The “cooking” of verse 1 provides a neat  transition to the “hot one” of verse 2, heat being an obvious characteristic of  the sun.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verse 3 and the first half of verse 4 are quite enigmatic—not surprisingly, given  their position in the middle of the hymn. Both the “dappled one” and the “ox” can  refer both to the Sun and to Soma, each of whom is also associated with dawn,  and the first half of the verse thus continues the Sun/Soma identification of verse  2. The second half of verse 3 appears to contain one of those paradoxes beloved  of R̥gvedic bards. In our (very tentative) interpretation, the forefathers are the  ancestral poet-sacrificers or their divine prototypes. They both “set” the embryo  of Soma/Sun, that is, engendered it, and they were themselves made into poets by  the magic power or artifice (māyā́) of the same Soma/Sun. In this way the Soma/ Sun is both progenitor of the forefathers in their ritual role and, as they fulfill their  ritual role, their child. The identity of the Gandharva in verse 4 is not entirely clear,  but on the basis of parallels, especially in the Vena hymn mentioned above, it seems  likely that it is again a double reference to Soma and the Sun, each guarding his track (or perhaps the track of the other), thus taking up the theme of the track  found in verse 2.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;With the second half of verse 4 we return to a much clearer ritual context  and to the filter with which we began. The filter traps the impurities of the soma  as the liquid passes over it, and the priests attain (a reprise of the verb found  twice in vs. 1) the prepared soma. The final verse (5) returns to the 2nd-person  address to the ritual Soma, last found in the first half of verse 1. But the Soma  thus addressed has achieved a much-elevated status:  he is proclaimed a king,  outfitted with cosmic garments and traveling a cosmic course, with the filter, the  focus of the hymn, as his chariot. The very last words of the hymn attribute to  him “lofty fame.”&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The omphalos structure of the hymn is quite pronounced. The outermost verses  (1ab, 5)  are couched in the 2nd person and have a clear ritual content, with an  inner ring (vss. 1cd/2ab, 4cd) serving as transition between the ritual context and  the mystical identifications. There are a number of formal responsions that mark  these rings, besides the 2nd versus 3rd person of verses 1 and 5: pavítram (1a, 2a)  / pavítra(-ratha) (5c); páry eṣi (1b) / pári yāsi (5b); āśata (1d, 4d); padá- (2a, 4a).  Enclosed within these rings are the mysterious and shifting identifications that  make the hymn both aggravating and mesmerizing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/084/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/084/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/084/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ पवस्व देवमादनः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं सप्तदशं सूक्तं वाचः पुत्रस्य प्रजापतेरार्षं जागतं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- पवस्व वाच्यः प्रजापतिः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;84 (796)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Prajāpati Vācya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: jagatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Unlike the last hymn, this one concentrates on the preparation of the soma, and,  although he has a cosmic dimension (see esp. vs. 2), it is always clear that Soma is  the topic and the referent. The most interesting image is found in verse 2, where  Soma “performs the knotting and unknotting.” On the ritual level, this phrase  probably refers to Soma’s journey through the tangle of sheep’s wool on the filter,  but comparison with IX.97.18 suggests that it also has moral force, with Soma  separating and distinguishing the straight way from the crooked one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/085/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/085/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/085/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ इन्द्राय&amp;rsquo; इति द्वादशर्चमष्टादशं सूक्तं भृगुगोत्रस्य वेनस्यार्षं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । एकादशीद्वादश्यौ त्रिष्टुभौ शिष्टा जगत्यः । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्-&amp;rsquo; इन्द्राय द्वादश वेनो भार्गवो द्वित्रिष्टुबन्तम्&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;85 (797)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vena Bhārgava&lt;br&gt;&#xA;12 verses: jagatī, except triṣṭubh 11–12&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The last two hymns of the jagatī group, IX.85–86, break the standard pattern of  decreasing numbers of verses, having twelve and forty-eight verses respectively, after  a group of hymns with five verses (IX.75–84). However, each of these longer hymns  can be divided into a series of shorter ones, which then conform to the patterns of  hymn arrangement. In the case of IX.85, it consists of three groups of four verses  each. The entire assemblage is attributed to Vena Bhārgava, also the supposed poet of the enigmatic “Vena” hymn (X.123; see also a brief discussion under IX.83). As  we will see, there are certainly striking similarities between the last quartet of IX.85  (vss. 9–12) and X.123.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first quartet (vss. 1–4) begins with Soma the militant, keeping unworthy and  hostile forces at bay and aiding Indra in the same enterprise (vss. 1–2). His relation ship to Indra persists in verses 3–4, which show a more positive side of the militant  Soma: his status as king (vs. 3) and winner of space for us (vs. 4).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The second section (vss. 5–8) is quite straightforward and focuses on the purifi cation of the soma, deploying the standard tropes.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As noted the final four verses (9–12) strongly resemble the Vena hymn (X.123),  but they are considerably easier to decode. They concern heavenly Soma, who is  identified with the sun, but who also appears in a number of different guises: a bull,  a poet, and a king (all in vs. 9), an ox (vs. 10), an eagle, a child, and a bird (vs. 11),  and finally a Gandharva (vs. 12).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/086/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/086/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/086/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अथ पञ्चमेऽनुवाक एकादश सूक्तानि । तत्र प्र ते &amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टाचत्वारिंशदृचं प्रथमं सूक्तम् ।। प्रथमदशर्चस्य आकृष्टा&amp;rsquo; इति माषा इति च द्विनामान ऋषिगणा द्रष्टारः । द्वितीयस्य दशर्चस्य सिकता इति नीवावरी इति द्विनामान ऋषिगणाः । तृतीयस्य दशर्चस्य पृश्नय इत्यजा इति च नामद्वयोपेता ऋषिगणाः । अदृष्टार्थमेषां द्विनामत्वमवगन्तव्यम् । चतुर्थस्य दशर्चस्य आकृष्टा माषा इत्यादिद्विनामानस्त्रयो गणा द्रष्टारः । एवं चत्वारिंशद्गताः । अथ पञ्चानां भौमोऽत्रिर्ऋषिः । ततस्तिसृणां गृत्समदः । जगती छन्दः । पवमानः सोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तं&amp;mdash;-&amp;rsquo; प्र तेऽष्टाचत्वारिंशदृषिगणा दशर्चा आकृष्टा माषाः प्रथमे सिकता निवावरी द्वितीये पृश्नयोऽजास्तृतीये त्रयश्चतुर्थेऽत्रिः पञ्चान्त्यास्तिस्रो गृत्समदः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/087/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/087/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/087/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र तु द्रव&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तं काव्यस्योशनस आर्षमनादेशपरिभाषया त्रैष्टुभं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं &amp;ndash; प्र तु नवोशना &amp;rsquo; इति । &amp;lsquo;जागतमूर्ध्वं प्रागुशनसः&amp;rsquo; (अनु. ९. ६७ ) इति वचनाज्जगत्यधिकारो निवृत्तः । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;87 (799)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Uśanas Kāvya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn, attributed to Uśanas Kāvya (perhaps because of the mention of that  figure in vs. 3), is built in part of standard soma-hymn tropes, but the militant&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/088/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/088/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/088/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;अयं सोमः&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । अयं सोमोऽष्टौ &amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;88 (800)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Uśanas Kāvya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is structured by a series of similes; only the first verse lacks an explicit  simile. Many of the similes also involve identification of Soma with other divinities  (see esp. vss. 3–5, 7), and so the powers and mythological deeds of these gods are  implicitly attributed to Soma by way of these comparisons.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The two outer verses (1, 8) are complementary to each other. The first is addressed  to Indra and announces the soma as distinctively his, while verse 8, emphasizing the  2nd-person pronoun as verse 1 did, declares that to Soma belong the distinctive  qualities and attainments of the Ādityas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/089/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/089/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/089/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्रो स्य वह्निः&amp;rsquo; इति सप्तर्चं चतुर्थं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः पूर्ववत् । ‘प्रो स्य सप्त&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;89 (801)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Uśanas Kāvya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;7 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The standard tropes of soma preparation, the swelling of Soma in water, his  manipulation by the priests’ fingers, his journey across the filter, and his mixing  with milk, provide the subject of this hymn, but, as often, each of these depic tions has a cosmic dimension—as in verses 1–2, where Soma is compared with  heavenly rain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/090/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/090/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/090/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र हिन्वानः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं  पञ्चमं सूक्तं मैत्रावरुणेर्वसिष्ठस्थार्षं त्रैष्टुभं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- प्र हिन्वानः षड्वसिष्ठः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;90 (802)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Vasiṣṭha Maitrāvaruṇi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Attributed to Vasiṣṭha, the poet of the VIIth Maṇḍala, this hymn ends (vs. 6d) with the  Vasiṣṭha clan refrain, encountered constantly in VII. Martial images dominate, start ing with verse 1 and showcased especially in verse 3 (see also 4cd and 5ab). The aim  of war, to secure peace and prosperity, is depicted in the center of the hymn (vs. 4ab).  Some of the divine beneficiaries of Soma’s invigorating capability are listed in verse 5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/091/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/091/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/091/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तृतीयं श्रुतितत्वज्ञः सप्तमस्याष्टकस्य सः ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;व्याख्याय सायणामात्यश्चतुर्थं व्याचिकीर्षति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तत्र ‘असर्जि&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं षष्ठं सूक्तं मारीचस्य कश्यपस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । ‘ असर्जि कश्यपः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;91 (803)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kaśyapa Mārīca&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The first three verses of this hymn concentrate on the journey of the soma across  the filter toward the mixing milk and toward Indra, but the militancy characteristic  of the previous hymn (IX.90) asserts itself in verse 4. The final two verses (5–6) ask  for bounties and blessings in return for our verbal and ritual service.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/092/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/092/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/092/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘परि सुवानः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं सप्तमं सूक्तं मारीचस्य कश्यपस्यार्षं त्रैष्टुभं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । ‘ परि सुवानः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;92 (804)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kaśyapa Mārīca&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like many hymns in the IXth Maṇḍala this hymn describes Soma’s journey, but  here the focus is on the endpoint, on Soma’s reaching his goal and taking his seat  in the vessels: the “seat” theme is found in three of the six verses (2, 3, 6). Soma is also a poet (vs. 2) and surrounded by poetry (vs. 3). It is this association with the  kaví, the sage poet and master of words, that probably prompted the most striking  statement in the hymn, that all the gods are “in your secret” (vs. 4). This statement  comes in the middle of the hymn and may constitute a weak omphalos, especially  as it is embedded in a series of verses that play with numbers (2–4), often a sign of  an omphalos structure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/093/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/093/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/093/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“ साकमुक्षः&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चमष्टमं सूक्तं गौतमस्य नोधस आर्षम् । पूर्ववच्छन्दोदेवते । तथा चानुक्रम्यते- साकमुक्षः पञ्च नोधाः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;93 (805)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Nodhas Gautama&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Attributed to Nodhas Gautama, the poet of I.58–64, this hymn ends with the clan  refrain found in most of those Ist Maṇḍala hymns, although it does not display the  virtuosity characteristic of those compositions. The first three verses concern the  journey of the soma to the vessels and the mixing with water and with milk. The  last two (4–5) are requests for bounties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/094/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/094/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/094/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ अधि यत्&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं नवमं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्य कण्वस्यार्षम् । तथानुक्रम्यते&amp;mdash;- अधि यत्कण्वः&amp;rsquo; इति । पूर्ववच्छन्दोदेवते । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;94 (806)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kaṇva Ghaura&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The word sóma does not appear until the last pāda (5d) of this hymn, which plots a  sometimes difficult course to this ending. The hymn features similes that exploit idi omatic ambiguity to produce different meanings in the simile proper and the frame  (see esp. vss. 1 and 3) and by obscure turns of phrase (see esp. 4d). It is therefore  not surprising that, as in IX.92, Soma is identified as a kaví, a poet, enmeshed in  poetry (vs. 3), and the main focus of the hymn, especially in the first three verses,  is the interchange between the poetic products of the mortal participants in ritual  and those of Soma himself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/095/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/095/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/095/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘कनिक्रन्ति&amp;rsquo; इति पञ्चर्चं दशमं सूक्तं कण्वपुत्रस्य प्रस्कवस्यार्षम् । तथानुक्रम्यते&amp;mdash; कनिक्रन्ति प्रस्कण्वः&amp;rsquo; इति । पूर्ववच्छन्दोदेवते । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;95 (807)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Praskaṇva Kāṇva&lt;br&gt;&#xA;5 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As in the preceding hymn, IX.94, the complementarity and interaction between  Soma’s poetic efforts and those of the ritualists provide the subject of this hymn.  Soma’s speech is the topic of the first two verses, culminating in 2cd in his revelation  of the “hidden names of the gods” that will be proclaimed aloud on the ritual ground.  But the verbal compositions of the mortals take center stage in verses 3–4. In the final  verse (5), Soma both prompts the speech of others and (it seems) produces his own.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/096/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/096/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/096/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र सेनानीः&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्विंशत्यृचमेकादशं सूक्तं दिवोदासपुत्रस्य प्रतर्दनाख्यस्य राजर्षेरिदं त्रैष्टुभं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते-’ प्र सेनानीश्चतुर्विंशतिर्दैवोदासिः प्रतर्दनः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;96 (808)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Pratardana Daivodāsi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;24 verses: triṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This twenty-four-verse hymn, immediately following three five-verse hymns in the  same meter, can easily be made to fit the sequence if it is analyzed as consisting of  a collection of four-verse hymns, as Oldenberg clearly states (1888: 201). The six  hymns thus obtained show different degrees of internal cohesion.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;For example, the first four verses display clear thematic unity and development.  The first verse is explicitly martial, with Soma as a warrior about to charge, a pic ture continued in the following verse. In verse 3 he achieves one of the most desired  results of Vedic warfare, wide space for us to inhabit, and with this obtained, verse  4 articulates a counter-message, that of peace and nonviolence. Indra is explicitly  mentioned in the first three verses, and comradeship is a central theme, as is seen in  verses 1, 2, and 4.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The second hymn (vss. 5–8) shows stylistic progression. It begins with a rhe torically restricted verse (5), consisting primarily of seven repetitions of the word  “begetter” with different genitive complements. The next verse (6)  continues the  dominantly nominal construction of vs. 5, but with a more varied verbal repertoire,  though the nominative-genitive syntagm persists. Verse 7 continues to describe the  qualities and characteristic actions of Soma, in the 3rd person, though it abandons  the strict nominal style. And finally vs. 8 breaks out into the dynamic 2nd person  and imperative mood.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The third group (vss. 9–12) ends with a characteristic hymn-final summary verse,  which seems to mark a decisive break from what follows. Although no clear the matic unity imposes itself on the four verses, the focus on Soma’s relationship with  our ancestral ritualists and our hope that this relationship will continue fruitfully is  noticeable, especially in the last two verses (11–12). On the other hand, it is difficult  to identify any unifying features in the next group of four (vss. 13–16), which con sist primarily of standard soma-hymn tropes. In verses 17–20 Soma as poet (esp. in  vss. 17–18) and his journey from the filter to the cups provide a weak cohesion. In  the final group (vss. 21–24), three verses (22–24) contain courtship imagery, and the  root krand “roar” is prominent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/097/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/097/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/097/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;षष्ठेऽनुवाके सप्त सूक्तानि । तत्र  अस्य प्रेषा  इत्यष्टापञ्चाशदृचं प्रथमं सूक्तं त्रैष्टुभं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तत्राद्यस्य तृचस्य मैत्रावरुणो वसिष्ठ ऋषिः । द्वितीयस्येन्द्रप्रमतिर्नाम । तृतीयस्य वृषगणः । चतुर्थस्य मन्युः। पञ्चमस्योपमन्युः । षष्ठस्य व्याघ्रपात् । सप्तमस्य शक्तिः । अष्टमस्य कर्णश्रुत् । नवमस्य मृळीकः । दशमस्य वसुक्रः । एते सर्वे वसिष्ठगोत्राः । एवं त्रिंशदृचो गताः । अथ चतुर्दशानामृचां शक्तिपुत्रः पराशर ऋषिः । शिष्टानामाङ्गिरसः कुत्सः । तथानुक्रम्यते- अस्य प्रेष्ठाष्टापञ्चाशदाद्यं तृचं वसिष्ठोऽपश्यदुत्तरान्नव पृथग्वसिष्ठा इन्द्रप्रमतिर्वृषगणो मन्युरुपमन्युर्व्याघ्रपाच्छक्तिः कर्णश्रुन्मृळीको वसुक्र इति चतुर्दश पराशरोऽन्त्याः कुत्सः  इति । गतो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/098/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/098/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/098/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;rsquo; अभि नः&amp;rsquo; इति द्वादशर्चं द्वितीयं सूक्तम् । वृषागिरो राज्ञः पुत्रोऽम्बरीषो भरद्वाजपुत्र ऋजिश्वोभौ सहितावस्यर्षी। इदमुत्तराणि च त्रीण्यानुष्टुभानि । अत्र त्वेकादशी बृहती। पवमानः सोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रम्यते&amp;ndash;&amp;rsquo; अभि नो द्वादशाम्बरीष ऋजिश्वा चानुष्टुभं ह बृहत्युपान्त्या &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;98 (810)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Ambarīṣa Vārṣāgira and R̥jiśvan Bhāradvāja&lt;br&gt;&#xA;12 verses: anuṣṭubh, except br̥hatī 11&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The themes that dominate this hymn are standard soma tropes. The normal stages  in the preparation of the soma are treated (see esp. vss. 2–3, 6–10), and the poet  regularly reminds Soma of the gifts he should bring to his mortal preparers (see esp.  vss. 1, 4–5, 12). Indeed the hymn begins and ends with an appeal for vā́ja “prizes”  (vss. 1a, 12cd), in a sort of ring composition.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;However, although the sentiments expressed and descriptions provided are unre markable, the hymn is characterized by very choppy and sometimes incoherent syn tax (which for purposes of translation has been cleaned up somewhat). Since there  are also metrical disturbances in the hymn, one wonders if it has been transmitted  entirely correctly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/099/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/099/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/099/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ आ हर्यताय&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तम् । कश्यपगोत्रौ रेभसूनू एतत्संज्ञौ द्वावृषी । आद्या बृहती सप्तानुष्टुभः। पवमानसोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तम्-&amp;rsquo; आ हर्यतायाष्टौ रेभसूनू काश्यपौ बृहत्याद्या &amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;99 (811)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Two sons of Rebha, the Kāśyapas&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: anuṣṭubh, except br̥hatī 1&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The varieties of thought and its poetic expressions are the focus of this hymn, espe cially in its earlier verses (1–2, 4–5), and Soma’s mental and verbal powers comple ment those of his mortal worshipers (vs. 6). The physical preparation of soma is not  neglected, however (esp. vss. 3, 7–8).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१००</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/100/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/100/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/100/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ अभी नवन्ते&amp;rsquo; इति नवर्चं चतुर्थं सूक्तम् । पूर्ववदृषिदेवते । सर्वा अनुष्टुभः । तथा चानुक्रम्यते’ अभी नवन्ते नव&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;100 (812)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Two sons of Rebha, the Kāśyapas&lt;br&gt;&#xA;9 verses: anuṣṭubh&lt;br&gt;&#xA;As Oldenberg suggests (1888:  128–29), in order to conform to the principles of  arrangement, this hymn must have originally consisted of two separate hymns, of  five and four verses respectively. This division, made solely on numerical grounds,  is confirmed by the structure of the hymn, for the final four verses repeat or ring  changes on the first five. Verse 6, the first of the original second hymn, is structur&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ally, and in part verbally, identical to the final verse of the original first hymn (5),  but also incorporates, in variant form, verse 4d. Verse 7 repeats much of verse 1 in  different order. Verse 8 deviates more from its model, verse 2, but reproduces verse  2d verbatim as verse 8d. Verse 9 is the most distant from its model, verse 3, but  contains the “heaven and earth” found in the “earthly and heavenly goods” of 3cd.  Once again we see the ways in which the R̥gvedic poet uses formulaic language and  poetic templates for his own purposes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/101/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/101/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/101/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;॥ श्रीगणेशाय नमः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यस्य निःश्वसितं वेदा यो वेदेभ्योऽखिलं जगत् ।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;निर्ममे तमहं वन्दे विद्यातीर्थमहेश्वरम् ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;विज्ञातवेदगाम्भीर्यस्तुर्यं व्याख्याय सप्तमे।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सायणार्यस्ततोऽध्यायं पञ्चमं व्याचिकीर्षति ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तत्र ‘ पुरोजिती वः&amp;rsquo; इति षोडशर्चमनुवाकापेक्षया पञ्चमं सूक्तम् । आद्यस्य तृचस्य श्यावाश्वपुत्रोऽन्धीगुर्नामर्षिः। द्वितीयस्य नहुषस्य राज्ञः पुत्रो ययातिर्नाम । तृतीयस्य मनोः पुत्रो नहुषो नाम राजर्षिः । चतुर्थस्य संवरणाख्यस्य राज्ञः पुत्रो मनुः । एवं द्वादश गताः । शिष्टस्य चतुर्ऋचस्य वाचः पुत्रो वैश्वामित्रो वा प्रजापतिर्ऋषिः । द्वितीयतृतीये गायत्र्यौ शिष्टाश्चतुर्दशानुष्टुभः । तथा चानुक्रम्यते’ पुरोजिती षोळश श्यावाश्विरन्धीगुर्ययातिर्नाहुषो नहुषो मानवो मनुः सांवरण इति तृचाः शेषे प्रजापतिरुपाद्ये गायत्र्यौ&amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/102/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/102/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/102/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘क्राणा शिशुः&amp;rsquo; इत्यष्टर्चं षष्ठं सूक्तमाप्त्स्य त्रितस्यार्षम् । इदमुत्तराणि चत्वारि सूक्तान्यौष्णिहानि । पवमानः सोमो देवता। तथा चानुक्रम्यते- क्राणाष्टौ त्रित औष्णिहं वै&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;102 (814)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Trita Āptya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;8 verses: uṣṇih The many obscurities in this hymn exist in tension with the clarity of its larger  structure: it is a ring composition, with a pāda-length phrase in the first and last  verses (1b, 8c) defining the ring: “spurring on the visionary power of truth.” This  phrase also sets one of the underlying themes, that Soma during his preparation  inspires and creates poetic truth. There is clarity also in the general progression of  the hymn, which follows Soma’s journey from the press (vs. 2) and across the filter  (vs. 3) to his final preparation (vs. 7). Another theme that runs throughout is that of  Soma as a child in relation to his mothers (vss. 1, 4, 7; see also 6), who not only gave  him physical birth but also formed him in his ritual rule (see vs. 4).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;It must be admitted, however, that much remains puzzling in the hymn. There  are a number of problems of syntax and lexicon. The two adjacent appearances  of Trita (or “the third one,” vss. 2–3) are also unclear, though they clearly play  on the numerals two and three found in those verses. The hymn is ascribed by the  Anukramaṇī to Trita Āptya, and so it might be that the poet is simply inserting  himself in the poem. But, since Trita Āptya is actually a mythological figure, it is  more likely that the Anukramaṇī has assigned the hymn to that figure on the basis  of the occurrences of tritá in those two verses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/103/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/103/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/103/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘प्र पुनानाय&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं सप्तमं सूक्तमाप्त्यस्य द्वितस्यार्षम्। पूर्ववच्छन्दोदेवते । तथा चानुक्रम्यते-‘प्र पुनानाय षड् द्वित आप्त्यः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;103 (815)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dvita Āptya&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: uṣṇih&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The most salient stylistic feature of the hymn is the preverb that begins each verse— pári “around” in all but the first verse—with the preverb increasingly less integrated  syntactically with the rest of the verse. The focus on pári arises from the description  of the motion of the soma as it is poured in circles into the filter.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like the last hymn, this one follows the journey of Soma and also focuses on his  ritual role and his participation in reciprocal ritual speech. Not only do we find the  technical term vedhás “ritual adept’ (vs. 1), as in IX.102.4 and 101.15, but also the  likewise technical vāghát “cantor” (vs. 5) in its only appearance in the IXth Maṇḍala.  The poet’s presentation of his speech and poetic thoughts in verse 1 and the voices  of the seers in verse 3 are met by Soma as himself “leader of thoughts” in verse 4.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn shares some lexical and thematic material with the immediately pre ceding IX.102. In addition to the aforementioned vedhás, note, for example, the  cleverly variant pādas 102.5b and 103.4b, which both contain “all the gods” and  lack of deceit. But in 103 all the gods are embedded in a compound modifying  Soma, whereas in 102 they are syntactically independent; moreover, the “deceit”  theme is carried by two different roots (dabh, druh) in two different valences: the  gods of 102 do not deceive, while Soma in 103 cannot be deceived. It is difficult  not to consider 102 and 103 as composed in conversation with each other, and the  Anukramaṇī’s ascription of 103 to Dvita Āptya (“the second Āptya”) clearly plays  off 102’s Trita Āptya (“the third Āptya”—but also the original Āptya from a myth&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ological perspective, since he is a commonly mentioned figure and has an Avestan  correspondent, whereas Dvita Āptya is essentially found only here).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/104/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/104/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/104/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;सप्तमेऽनुवाक एकादश सूक्तानि । तत्र ‘ सखायः&amp;rsquo; इति षड़ृचं प्रथमं सूक्तम् । काण्वौ पर्वतनारदावृषी । अथवा कश्यपस्य पुत्र्यौ शिखण्डिन्याख्ये द्वे अप्सरसावस्य सूक्तस्य दृष्ट्यौ । पूर्ववच्छन्दोदेवते। तथा चानुक्रम्यते- सखायः पर्वतनारदौ काश्यप्यौ द्वे शिखण्डिन्यौ वाप्सरसौ &amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;104 (816)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Parvata Kāṇva and Nārada Kāṇva, or the two Apsarases named Śikhaṇḍinī, daugh ters of Kaśyapa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: uṣṇih&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn forms a close pair with 105 and the two are a textbook demonstration  of how R̥gvedic poets generate variations on underlyingly identical lexical and the matic material. The two hymns correspond verse by verse, and even in translation  the identity of many of the words, their grammatical forms, and whole phrases is  clear. But the poets avoid pāda-length repetitions and introduce variation via lexical  replacement or grammatical transformation.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The contents are unremarkable; both hymns deploy the usual soma-hymn tropes,  though the final apotropaic verse is refreshingly vivid.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/105/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/105/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/105/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;तं वः&amp;rsquo; इति षडृचं द्वितीयं सूक्तं पर्वतनारदयोरार्षम् । अन्यत् पूर्ववत् । &amp;rsquo; तं वः&amp;rsquo; इत्यनुक्रान्तम् । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;105 (817)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Parvata and Narada&lt;br&gt;&#xA;6 verses: uṣṇih&lt;br&gt;&#xA;For discussion of this twin to IX.104, see the introduction to that hymn.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton Notes&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As noted ad IX.104, this hymn has a very palpable twinned relationship with 104, though extensive exact repetition is avoided. What follows explicitly traces the parallels and the variations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/106/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/106/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/106/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘इन्द्रमच्छ &amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्दशर्चं तृतीयं सूक्तमौष्णिहं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । प्रथमस्य तृचस्य चक्षुराख्यपुत्रोऽग्निर्ऋषिः । द्वितीयस्य मनुपुत्रश्चक्षुर्नामा । अप्सुनाम्नः पुत्रो मनुस्तृतीयस्य । एवं नवर्चो गताः । शिष्टानामपि पञ्चानां चाक्षुषोऽग्निः । तथा चानुक्रम्यते&amp;mdash; इन्द्रमच्छ षळूनाग्निश्चाक्षुषश्चक्षुर्मानवो मनुराप्सव इति तृचाः पञ्चाग्निः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;106 (818)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Agni Cākṣuṣa (1–3), Cakṣus Mānava (4–6), Manu Āpsava (7–9), Agni Cākṣuṣa (10–14) 14 verses: uṣṇih&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This last hymn in the uṣṇih collection, as is common with hymns positioned at  the end of their metrical grouping, is too long and needs to be broken down into  smaller units: four tr̥cas (vss. 1–3, 4–6, 7–9, 10–12) followed by a two-verse hymn  (13–14). In this case the division is in general accord with the Anukramaṇī, which  ascribes the hymn to three different mythical poets, marked by their patronymic  relationships as grandson, son, and father, each with a tr̥ca. The grandson returns  as poet of the last five verses, that is, of the final tr̥ca (10–12) and the two-verse unit  that ends the hymn.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The contents of the hymn are entirely conventional, with a focus on Indra as  drinker of the soma, especially in the first part of the hymn. Note that “finding the  sun” is also a preoccupation, and that word (svarvíd) appears once in each of the  first three tr̥cas (vss. 1, 4, 9).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/107/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/107/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/107/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘परीतः&amp;rsquo; इति षड्विंशत्यृचं चतुर्थं सूक्तम् । ‘त्वं सोमासि&amp;rsquo; (ऋ. सं. ९. ६७ ) इत्यत्रोक्ता भरद्वाजकश्यपाद्याः सप्तर्षयः । आद्या बृहती द्वितीया सतोबृहती। अयमेकः प्रगाथः । &amp;lsquo;परि सुवानः इत्येषा तृतीयैकविंशत्यक्षरा भुरिग्विराड् द्विपदा । &amp;lsquo;नृभिर्येमानः&amp;rsquo; इति षोडशी विंशत्यक्षरा द्विपदा विराट् । चतुर्थ्यादिद्वौ प्रगाथौ । दशम्यादित्रयः सप्तदश्यादिपञ्च प्रगाथाः । पवमानः सोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रम्यते – “परीतः षड्विंशतिः सप्तर्षयः प्रागाथं तृतीयाषोळश्यौ द्विपदे अष्टम्याद्ये बृहत्यौ&amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/108/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/108/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/108/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ पवस्व&amp;rsquo; इति षोडशर्चं पञ्चमं सूक्तम् । आद्यद्वृचस्य गौरिवीतिर्नाम शक्तिपुत्र ऋषिः । तृतीयायाः शक्तिर्नाम वासिष्ठः । ततः पञ्चानां द्वृचानामूरुर्नामाङ्गिरस ऋजिश्वा नाम भारद्वाज ऊर्ध्वसद्मा नामाङ्गिरसः कृतयशा नाम कश्चित् सोऽप्याङ्गिरस ऋणंचयो नाम राजर्षिरित्येते क्रमेणर्षयः । एवं त्रयोदश गताः । ततस्तिसृणा वासिष्ठः शक्तिः। प्रथमातृतीयाद्या अयुजः ककुभः । द्वितीयाचतुर्थ्याद्या युजः सतोबृहत्यः। स सुन्वे यो वसूनाम्&amp;rsquo; इत्येषा तु यवमध्या गायत्री । पवमानः सोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रम्यते&amp;ndash; पवस्व षोळश गौरिवीतिर्द्वृचं शक्तिरेकामुरुर्ऋजिश्वोर्ध्वसद्मा कृतयशा ऋणंचय इत्यृषयो द्वृचास्तिस्रः शक्तिः काकुभाः प्रगाथाः स सुन्वे गायत्री यवमध्या&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/109/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/109/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/109/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘परि प्र&amp;rsquo; इति द्वाविंशत्यृचे द्वैपदं षष्ठं सूक्तम् । यज्ञे सदस्यवस्थितहोत्रीयादिधिष्ण्योपेता अग्नयो नामेश्वरपुत्रा ऋषयः । विंशतिका द्विपदा विराजः । पवमानः सोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तं &amp;ndash; परि प्र द्व्यधिकाग्नयो धिष्ण्या ऐश्वर द्वैपदम्&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;109 (821)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dhiṣṇya Fires, descendants of Īśvara&lt;br&gt;&#xA;22 verses: dvipadā virāj, arranged in trcas ̥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The Anukramaṇī’s fanciful ascription of this hymn to the dhiṣṇya (“holy”) fires  finds no echo in the composition itself.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The lightness and brevity of this meter (each verse containing four pādas of  a mere five syllables each) do not lend themselves to complex phraseology or elaborate images. Instead the hymn consists primarily of standard apostrophes to  Soma (e.g., the imperative “purify yourself” occurs five times in the hymn: vss. 4, 5,  6, 7, 10) and simple present-tense descriptions of the process of preparation (e.g.,  vs. 11 “they purify”; vs. 12 “they groom”).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;For links with the next hymn, see the introduction to IX.110.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>११०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/110/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/110/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/110/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“पर्यु षु&amp;rsquo; इति द्वादशर्चं सप्तमं सूक्तम् । त्र्यरुणत्रसदस्यू राजर्षी अस्य सूक्तस्य द्रष्टारौ । आदितस्तिस्रः पिपीलिकमध्या अनुष्टुभो द्वादशकाष्टकद्वादशकवत्यः । ततः षडूर्ध्वबृहत्यो द्वादशकत्रयवत्यः । अथ दशम्याद्यास्तिस्रो विराजः । पवमानः सोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तं- पर्यू षु द्वादश त्र्यरुणत्रसदस्यू तिस्रोऽनुष्टुभः पिपीलिकमध्याः षडूर्ध्वबृहत्यस्तिस्रश्च विराजः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;110 (822)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Tryaruṇa and Trasadasyu&lt;br&gt;&#xA;12 verses: pipīlikamadhyā 1–3, ūrdhvabr̥hatī 4–9, virāj 10–12, arranged in trcas ̥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is made up of verses in three rare meters; in fact verses 4–9 are the only  ones in all of the R̥gveda in this meter (consisting of verses of three pādas of twelve  syllables each), and the first three verses are the only pipīlikamadhyā stanzas in the  R̥gveda with this syllable count (12 8 12). (The meter’s name means “ant-middled,”  because a short pāda is sandwiched between two longer ones.) Despite the hetero&lt;br&gt;&#xA;geneity of the meters, there is evidence that the hymn is a conceptual unity, par ticularly in the signs of ring composition: the last two verses (11–12) echo the first  two. “The one who gains the prize” (11c) matches “to gain the prize” in 1a; the two  forms of the root sah “vanquish” in verse 12 (a and c) recall the “vanquisher” in 1b;  the “difficult plunges” in 12b are the negative counterpart of Soma’s plunge in 2c.  Internally we may note that the begetting of the sun in verse 3, at the end of the first  tr̥ca (3a, with its initial verb ájījanaḥ) is immediately reprised in 4a, in a new meter,  again with the fronted verb ájījanaḥ.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn also echoes some of the vocabulary and phraseology of the preceding  hymn, X.109, whose metrical simplicity is in marked contrast to this hymn. Both  hymns begin almost identically, though adjusted by the addition of particles for the  metrical difference: IX.109.1a pári prá dhanva and 110.1a páry ū ṣú prá dhanva &amp;hellip;,  both meaning “run forth and around.” The rare word pīyū́ṣa “beestings, first-milk,”  which makes two appearances in 109 (vss. 3, 6), recurs in 110.8, qualified as “the  beestings of heaven” (diváḥ pīyū́ṣam) like the “heavenly beestings” of 109.3 (divyáḥ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pīyū́ṣaḥ).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In content the first three and the last three (10–12) verses are fairly straight forward, and, especially the last three verses, are concerned with the earthly soma  of the ritual, though also celebrating his great powers in confronting enemies and  obstacles. A hint of the cosmic soma comes in verse 3, in the aforementioned beget ting of the sun, though in this verse this action is linked with Soma’s ritual progress.  The middle six verses (4–9), in an otherwise unattested meter, are more difficult  and treat the interaction and blurred boundaries between earthly, ritual soma and cosmic soma. The gods’ yearning for soma (see esp. vs. 6) and the primal prepara tion of soma (see esp. vss. 7–8) are described, and the final verse of this group (vs.  9) declares Soma’s universal power.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१११</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/111/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/111/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/111/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘ अया रुचा&amp;rsquo; इति तृचमष्टमं सूक्तं परुच्छेपपुत्रस्यानानताख्यस्यार्षमत्यष्टिच्छन्दकं पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते-‘अया रुचा तृचमनानतः पारुच्छेपिरात्यष्टम्&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ।।&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;111 (923)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Anānata Pārucchepi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;3 verses: atyaṣṭi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This hymn is the only one in the IXth Maṇḍala in the intricate atyaṣṭi meter, with  its variable lines and patterned repetition. The poet, according to the Anukramaṇī,  is Anānata son of Parucchepa, a poet not otherwise represented in the R̥gveda.  However, his putative father, Parucchepa, is the author, again according to the  Anukramaṇī, of I.127–39, the only sustained corpus of atyaṣṭi in the R̥gveda.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The hymn begins with a description of Soma’s journey, and the final verse (vs.  3) returns to this theme. The middle verse (vs. 2) is a brief, and quite enigmatic,  treatment of the Vala myth. In our view it involves something of a reversal of some  standard tropes. The 2nd-person subject of the first three pādas of the verse is  Soma, who is here credited with retrieving the cows stolen by the Paṇis. These cows,  of course, also represent the milk with which the soma will be mixed. Soma then  grooms or cleans these cows along with his (or their?) mothers. Now ordinarily it is  Soma who is groomed; he doesn’t perform any grooming on others. And a number  of translators and commentators have attempted to make the verb used here (mar jayasi) reflect this normal usage. However, this particular verb form is emphatically  and unambiguously transitive, and it seems likely that the poet is thus drawing our  attention to the role reversal, with the usual female agents of Soma’s grooming  relegated to auxiliaries.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The reference of the next item, the melody or sāman, is equally obscure. If it  is part of the Vala myth, it may refer to the song sung by Indra/Br̥haspati and the  Aṅgirases to open the cave and free the cows; they came “from afar” bringing their  song, and to the cows within the cave the song would have sounded “from afar.” It  is also possible that the simile just refers to a general situation, the pleasure one gets  from hearing a snatch of song out of nowhere. In any case in the last portion of this  verse Soma acquires vigor or vitality from the cows, who are also identified as the  three forms of ritual speech.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>११२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/112/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/112/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/112/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘नानानम्&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचं नवमं सूक्तमाङ्गिरसस्य शिशुनाम्न आर्षम् । पञ्चपदा पङ्क्तिश्छन्दः । पवमानः सोमो देवता । तथा चानुक्रान्तं &amp;ndash; नानानं चतुष्कं शिशुः पाङ्क्तं हि&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;112 (824)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Śiśu Āṅgirasa&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: paṅkti&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This charming little hymn has no obvious connection to soma except through its  refrain (which it shares with the next two hymn, 113–114, also in the same meter),  which sits oddly in each verse, and through the glancing mention of the soma-presser  in 1d. The diversity of people’s occupations and of their goals is the theme, presented  in casual style and sometimes colloquial language (see especially the designations for  father and mother in vs. 3), with the gently cynical message that what everyone really  wants is gain or an easy life. The final verse (4) opens out to the nonhuman world.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Perhaps the most interesting verse, as a small window on realia, is the second  one, which presents a rare picture of a smith and his equipment. The “old plants”  must be for producing a hot fire, the “feathers of birds” for fanning the flames, and  the stones are probably whetstones.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Casting about for a reason for the refrain and for the inclusion of this hymn in  the IXth Maṇḍala—it may be that the point of the refrain is that, like the people  and animals mentioned in the body of the text, the drop has its own goal, particular  to itself, namely simply to seek Indra. Or perhaps the hymn was simply too delight&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ful to abandon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>११३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/113/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/113/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/113/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘शर्यणावति&amp;rsquo; इत्येकादशर्चं दशमं सूक्तं मारीचस्य कश्यपस्यार्षम् । पूर्वत्र ‘हि&amp;rsquo; इत्युक्तत्वादिदमुत्तरं च पाङ्क्तम् । पवमानसोमदेवताकम् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते- शर्यणावत्येकादश कश्यपः&amp;rsquo; इति । गतो विनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;113 (825)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kaśyapa Mārīca&lt;br&gt;&#xA;11 verses: paṅkti&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The special interest of this hymn rests in the vision of heaven in its second half.  Most strikingly, the imagery that describes this heaven—its freedom, joy, and sat isfaction of all desires—occurs again in the Upaniṣads to characterize the mysti cal realization of the self. The hymn begins more or less as a conventional soma  hymn, however. In verse 1 Indra is urged to drink the soma to strengthen himself  for action, and in verse 2 Soma is commanded to purify himself, with the signature  imperative pavasva. Verse 2 also introduces the theme of true ritual speech, which is  taken up again in verses 4–6. Verse 3 seems to contain an interlude about the rain,  which provides the sap to the soma plant, though the mythological sequence involv ing the Daughter of the Sun and the Gandharvas is obscure.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Verses 6 and 7 are the omphalos verses and provide a dramatic transition from  the poet’s description of the preparation of soma in the first half of the hymn to  a vision of heaven (vss. 7–11), where immortality and the fulfillment of all desires  are attained. Verse 6 is still set on the ritual ground and is in some ways the climax  of the hymn, for it anticipates the drinking of the soma. Since soma is the drink of  deathlessness, the ceremony becomes the place of immortality. Verse 6 is also gram&lt;br&gt;&#xA;matically incomplete, consisting only of a dependent clause and producing tension  awaiting resolution in a main clause that will answer the implicit question: “what  will happen in this ‘where’?” The first half of verse 7 is responsive to 6 and thus  builds the tension, but the locus of the “where” has changed: the poet has trans&lt;br&gt;&#xA;formed the ritual space into the heavenly realm. The tension finds its release in the  second half of verse 7, with the long-postponed main clause. The remaining verses  reproduce the structure of verse 7, enlarging and embellishing the vision of the  immortal world.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;What links the first half of the hymn to the second, besides the transforma tive responsion of verses 6–7? The answer is not entirely clear, but it seems that  the true speech that accompanies the preparation of the soma (vs. 2), perhaps the  natural speech of the thunder (vs. 3), the true speech Soma himself speaks (vs. 4),  the sacred formulation with which he is purified (vs. 5), and the verbal behavior of the formulator of that formulation (vs. 6) provide Soma with the power to bestow  immortality. He does so by placing the poet in the immortal realms, and placing is  also a recurrent theme in the first half of the hymn: Indra places soma’s strength  in himself in verse 1; the rain is placed in soma as his juice in verse 3; soma is pre&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pared by the Placer in verse 4; the sun was placed in the heavenly world in 7b, and  finally the poet implores Soma to place him in the same world in 7c. The first two  of these placings also involve clear transformation of substance:  soma becomes  Indra’s strength; the rain becomes soma’s sap. We can also see transformation in  the Placer’s preparation of soma in verse 4, as this preparation makes a physical  substance into a drink of immortality, and ultimately in Soma’s placing of the poet  in the immortal world, which will make the poet himself immortal. The command  of the second half of verse 7 “place me in that immortal, imperishable world” is fol lowed by the command refrain of the remaining four verses (8–11), “there make me  immortal,” a sequence that appears to support the notion that the “placing” both  precedes and causes the poet’s transformation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>११४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/114/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarva-prastutiH/09/114/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; newlevelforh1=&#34;2&#34; title=&#34;सर्वाष् टीकाः&#34; unfilled url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/sarvASh_TIkAH/09/114/_index.md&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;details open&gt;&lt;summary&gt;&lt;h2&gt;सर्वाष् टीकाः ...{Loading}...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;सायण-भाष्यम्&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;‘य इन्दोः&amp;rsquo; इति चतुर्ऋचमेकादशं सूक्तम् । ऋष्याद्याः: पूर्ववत् । तथा चानुक्रम्यते &amp;ndash; य इन्दोश्चतुष्कम्&amp;rsquo; इति । गतः सूक्तविनियोगः ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Jamison Brereton&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;114 (826)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Soma Pavamāna&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Kaśyapa Mārīca&lt;br&gt;&#xA;4 verses: paṅkti&lt;br&gt;&#xA;This final hymn in the Soma Maṇḍala has the feeling of an afterthought. The seer  addresses himself in verse 2, and the fortunate ritualist depicted in verse 1 is most  likely Kaśyapa as well. In verse 3 he produces a triad of heptads, which have little to  do with his call to Soma to protect us (3d). The final verse (4) repeats this call and  enlarges on the dangers we wish to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
