<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 Power of the Word on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/03_Power_of_the_Word/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 Power of the Word on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/03_Power_of_the_Word/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Words, Truth, and Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/03_Power_of_the_Word/A_Words_Truth_and_Knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/03_Power_of_the_Word/A_Words_Truth_and_Knowledge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One reason for the intricacy of R̥gvedic poetry and the careful thought that the  R̥gvedic poets put into it is the importance that Vedic culture attached to the spo ken word and to the truth that it embodied. The elegantly formulated truth, spoken  in a ritual context, was powerful. The word for “truth” is r̥tá, a crucially resonant  word that, with some reason, some other translators have rendered “order” or “cosmic order.” The term r̥tá essentially defines what a being or object is and what it  does, and it structures the relationships of beings and objects with other beings and  objects. By speaking these truths of essence and relationship, the poets could make  the truths real and actual in the present. So, for example, the great Indra hymn,  I.32, begins, “Now I shall proclaim the heroic deeds of Indra, those foremost deeds,  which the mace-wielder performed&amp;hellip;.” Why does the poet proclaim these deeds?  It is not simply to honor the god, although his proclamation surely does do that. It  is also to state the truth of these heroic deeds, so that these deeds will become real  once again. As Indra once before smashed Vr̥tra, who was the symbol and epitome  of all obstacles, so once again he will smash obstacles. Formulating the “truth” of  Indra is part of what makes Indra real and present. Similarly, the story of Indra  and the Vala cave is essentially a story of the power of the truth. According to  this myth, Indra and the Aṅgirases opened the Vala cave and released the cattle  and the dawns by the songs they recited. These songs were powerful because they  contained the truth that the cattle were the dawns, and therefore, by singing this  truth Indra and the Aṅgirases obtained both cattle and dawns.+++(5)+++ In X.108 the poet  narrates part of the story of Indra and Vala and then states his expectation that  the truth of his song, which is the truth of the Vala story, will bring cattle back to  him: “Exchanging with the truth, let the cows come up, which Br̥haspati [=Indra]  found hidden&amp;hellip;.” Or again, in IX.113.2 the poet declares the soma is pressed “with  real words of truth, with trust, and with fervor.” That is to say, it is not just the  physical pressing of the soma plant that produces soma juice. Soma is also created by the intensity of the priests, by their confidence in the effectiveness of their  actions, and by the truth they speak about the soma and about the power of the  soma to strengthen the gods and to give life to mortals. Words, commitment, and  ritual all combine to make the soma real.+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B Homology</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/03_Power_of_the_Word/B_Homology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/03_Power_of_the_Word/B_Homology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Vedic mental universe is structured, in great part, by a web of identifications  or equivalences among elements in the ritual realm, in the cosmic realm, and in the  realm of the everyday. These homologies play an enormous role in the thought of  the Brāhmaṇas and Upaniṣads, where knowing the hidden connections between  apparently disparate elements, particularly the equivalences between cosmic and  ritual elements, gives the knower some power to control the cosmic by manipulation  of the ritual.+++(5)+++ In these later Vedic texts, such types of equivalences have a technical  name—bandhu “bond, connection” (a word of course cognate with English “bind,”  etc.)—and the difference between the cosmic and the mundane system of equations  is pervasive enough to be distinguished by technical terms+++(5)+++: the cosmic level is called  adhidaivam or adhidevatam, roughly “concerned with the divine,” while the mundane is called adhyātmam, roughly “concerned with the person(al).” These two systems meet in and focus on the sacrifice, a controlled and orderly sphere of human  activity, as a way of modeling the complex web of relationships that obtain in the  two other realms, which are not under human control. The level of the sacrifice is  called adhiyajñam “relating to the sacrifice.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C The Wordsmiths</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/03_Power_of_the_Word/C_The_Wordsmiths/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/03_Power_of_the_Word/C_The_Wordsmiths/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A number of different words are used to identify the workers in words, for which  we use the cover term “poet.” These different terms often in fact have the same  referent, sometimes in the very same passage, but emphasize different aspects of  verbal craftsmanship. The most important terms are brahmán, kaví, ŕ̥ṣi, and vípra.  Although it is not always possible to draw fine distinctions among these words, and there remains considerable disagreement about their application (we two translators, for example, are not entirely agreed on the function of the kaví), the words do  point to different types of relationships between the poet and his product and its  source. As noted above, the brahmán is the “formulator,” who discerns and puts into  words the hidden truths that undergird reality. His product is a bráhman, a “sacred  formulation.” The term ŕ̥ṣi, generally rendered here as “seer,” is especially applied  to the famous seers of the past, single or as a group, and to current poets who consciously aspire to the status of their predecessors, and like other words for verbal  craftsmen, it is also regularly used of gods, especially Agni and Soma. The vípra, a  derivative of the root √vip “tremble,”+++(5)+++ appears to be an “inspired poet” and contrasts  with the kaví, the poet par excellence, but also the “sage poet,” endowed with the  knowledge embodied in poetic skill (kā́vya). The original sense of the word kaví and the function of the person so named is disputed; it has well-attested Iranian  cognates, starting with Avestan kauui, whose sense diverges from its Vedic corre spondent. We two translators have discussed these issues in separate treatments  (Brereton 2004; Jamison 2007: chap. 4).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
