<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;04 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;04 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST CHAPTER. (On the Solaśi and Atiratra Sacrifices.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(On the Nature of the Solaśi, and the Origin of its Name. On the Anuṣçubh&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nature of the Solasi Sastra.) The gods prepared for Indra, by means of the Soma ceremony) of the first day, the thunderbolt; by means (of the Soma ceremony) of the second day, they cooled it (after having forged it, to increase its sharpness); by means (of the Soma ceremony) of the third day, they presented it (to him); by means of the Soma ceremony of the fourth day, he struck with it (his enemies).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND CHAPTER. (The Aśvina Sastra. The Beginning Day of the Gavam Ayanan.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Use&amp;quot;of the Rathantara and Brihat Sāmans and their kindreds. The Mahāurata Day of the Sattra.)!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;i The “Aśvin Sastra is one of the longest recitations by the Hotar it is only a modification of the Prātaranuvāka. Its principal parts are the same as those of the Prātaranuvika, the Agneya kratu, Uṣasya kratu and Ašvina Icratu (see page 111), i,en, three series of hymns and verses in seven kinds of metre, addressed to Agni, Uṣás, and the Aśvins, which deities rule at the end of the night, and at the very commencement of the day. In addition to these three scratus of the Pratarapuvaka, in the Aśvina sastra. there are verses addressed to other deities, chiefly the sun, repeated. Before commenc ing to repeat it, the Hotar (not the Adhvaryu) must sacrifice thrice a little melted butter, and eat the rest of it. These three oblations are given to Agni, Usās, and the two Aśvins. Each is accompanied with a Yajus-like mantra That one addressed to Agui is : afarat e r a aah ah an* F# HIAAT AF FATET I Agni is driving with the Gayatri metre (this metre being his ca rriage), might I reach him ; I hold him; may this (melted butter) help me to him ; Svāhā to him.&amp;quot; The mantras repeated for the Ajya offerings to Uṣas and the Aśvins differ very little.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD CHAPTER. (The Şalaha and Viṣuvan Day of the Sattras with the Performance of the Days Preceding and Following the Viṣuvan.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Tryaha and Salaha, i. e, periods of three and six days at the Sattra. The Abhiplava.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They (those who hold the sacrificial session) perform [280] (now) the Jyotiz-Go and Ayuṣ-Stomas. This world is the Jyotis (light), the airy region the Go (Stoma), that world āyus (life). The same Stomas (as in the first three days out of the six) are observed in the latter three days. (In the first) three days (the order of the stomas is), Jyotiṣı Go and Ayuṣ Stomas. (In the latter) three days (the order is) Go-Ayus Jotis-Stomas. (According to the position of the Jyotiṣ Stoma in both parts) the Jyotis is this world and that world; they are the two Jyotiṣ (lights) on both sides facing (one another) in the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH CHAPTER. (The Dvadasāha Sacrifice. Its Origin, and General Rules for its Performa&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ance. The Initiatory Rites.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Origin of the Dvadasaha. Its Gayatri Form.) Prajapati felt a desire to create and to multiply himself. He under went (in order to accomplish this end) austerities. After having done so, he perceived the Dvadasāha sacrifice (ceremonies to be) in his limbs and vital airs. He took it out of his limbs and vital airs, and made it twelve fold. He seized it and sacrificed with it. Thence he (Prajā pati) was produced (i.e., that form of his which enters creatures, his material body), Thus he was reproduced through himself in offspring and cattle. He who&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;25 Višvakarman means it who does all work.&amp;quot; Generally, the architect of the gods is meant by the term,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/04/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIFTH CHAPTER. (The Two First Days of the Dvádasáha Sacrifice)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(The Sastras of the Morning and Midday Libations on the First Day.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;· Agni is the leading deity of the first day. The Stoma (required) is . .See page 214.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;? The purport of this paragraph is to show why on certain days of the Dyadasaha the Rathantara Sāman, and on others the Brihat Sāman, is required for forming a Pristha with another Sāman. See on these different Şāmans 4, 13.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
