<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;07 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;07 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST CHAPTER. (The Distribution of the Different Parts of the Sacrificial Animal among&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the Priests.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;22&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;04&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now follows the division of the different parts of the sacrificial animal (among the priests). We shall describe it? The tsvo jawbones with the tongue are to be given to the Prastotar; the breast in the form of an eagle to the Udgātar; the throat with the palate to the Pratibartar; the lower part of the right loins the Hotar; the left to the Brahmā ; the right thigh to the Maitrā varuna; the left to the Brahmapachhańsí; the right side with the shoulder to the Adhvaryu; the left side to those who accompany the chants; * the left shoulder to the Pratipasthātar; the lower part of the right arm to the Nestar; the lower part of the left arm to the Potar; the upper part of the right thigh to the Achhavāka; the left to the Agnidbra; the upper part of the right arm to Atreya ; the left to the Sadasya; the back bone (442) and the urinal bladder to the Grihapati (sacrificer); the right feet to the Gțihapati who gives a feasting; the left feet to the wife of that Gribapati who gives a feasting; the upper lip is common to both (the Grihapati and bis wife), which is to be divided by the Grihapati. They offer the tail of the animal to wives, but they should give it to a Brahmana; the fleshy processes (manikah) on the neck and three gristles (kakasah) to the Grāvastut; three&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND CHAPTER. The Penances for Mistaps to the Performer of the Agnihotran),&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;172&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(What Penances are required when an Agnihotri Dies).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They ask, If a man who has already established a sacred fire (an Igni hotri) should die on the day previous to a sacrifice (zparasatha), what is to become of his sacrifice (to wbich all preparations had been made) ?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;*A large piece of flesh..Sey.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;• The piece of flesh which is on the side of the heart.-Say.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD CHAPTER. (The Story of Sansepa)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;13&#34;&gt;13&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(King Harischandra wishes for a Son. Stanzas praising the Possession of a Son).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Harischandra, the son of Vedhas, of the Ilṣvāku race, mas a king who had no son. Though he had a hundred wives, they did not give birth to a son. In his house there lived the Riṣis, Parvata and Nārada. Once the king addressed to Nārada (the following stanza):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Since all beings, those endowed with reason (men) as well as those who are without it (beasts) wish for a son, what is the fruit to be obtained by having a son? This tell me, O Nārada?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH CHAPTER.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The Preliminary Rites of the Rājasuya Sacrifie.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;19&#34;&gt;19&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The Relationship between the Brahma and Kṣattra.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Prajā pati had created the sacrifice, the Brahma (divine knowledge) and the Kṣaltra (sovereignty) were produced. After both two kinds of (472) creatures sprang up, such ones as eat the sacrificial food, and such ones as do not eat it. All ealers of the sacrificial food followed the Brahma, the non-eaters followed the Kṣattra. Therefore, the Brabmans only are eaters of the sacrificial food; whilst the Kṣattriyas, Vaisyas, and Sūdras do not eat it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/07/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIFTH CHAPTER On the Sacrificial Drink uchich the King has to Taste instead of Soma, According to the Instruction given by Rāma Margaveya to the King Visvantara.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;27&#34;&gt;27&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Story of the Sy@parnas. Rama Defends their Rights.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vispantara, the son of Suṣādman, deprived the Syāparnas of their right of serving as his sacrificial [482] priests, and interdicted any one of this family to take part in his sacrifice. Having learnt (that) they went to the place of his sacrifice and seated themselves within the precincts of the Vedi. On observing them, Visvantara said (to his attendants), * There sit those Syāparnas, the scoundrels, who endeavour to sully another&amp;rsquo;s fame. Turn them out; let them not sit in the Vedi,” The attendants obeyed and turned the Syāparnas out. They then cried aloud, * \ben Janamejaya, the son of Pariṣkit, was performing a sacrifice without the Kaśyapas (who were lis hereditary priests), then the Asitamrigas from among the Kaśyapas turned the Bhūtaviras (who were officiating instead of the Kasyapas) out, not allowing them to administer the Soma rites. They succeeded because they had brave men with them. * Well, what hero is now among us, who might by force take away this Soma beverage (that we might administer it ourselves) ? &amp;quot; &amp;ldquo;This your man am I,&amp;rdquo; said Rama Mārgaveya, * This Rāma belonged to the Syāpar - nas, and had completed the sacred study. When the Syāparnas rose&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
