<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;08 Translation Principles on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/08_Translation_Principles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;08 Translation Principles on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/08_Translation_Principles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Sanskrit into English: Problems and Solutions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/08_Translation_Principles/A_Sanskrit_into_English_Problems_and_Solutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/08_Translation_Principles/A_Sanskrit_into_English_Problems_and_Solutions/</guid>
      <description>As has been repeatedly emphasized above, the R̥gveda is a poetic text, structured by intricate meters, driven by rhetorical principles based on this metrical structure, and crafted by skillful poets for a poetically aware audience.
Prose is used Nonetheless, we have chosen to translate the text into prose, not verse—for several reasons.
First and perhaps most important, we are not poets, and we would dishonor the highly trained and highly inventive poets of the R̥gveda by translating their artful creations into bad English verse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>B Format of the Translations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/08_Translation_Principles/B_Format_of_the_Translations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/08_Translation_Principles/B_Format_of_the_Translations/</guid>
      <description>No footnotes Perhaps the most unusual feature of our translation is our decision to avoid the use of footnotes entirely. We did not begin with that idea, but several considerations led us to it.
First, the notes in Geldner’s translation, especially the parallels he cites, are full and informative, and interested readers should consult them: knowledge of German is not required for tracking down the parallels. Further, this translation will appear approximately coincident with the new Witzel-Gotō translation into German, which contains annotations to verses that build on Geldner’s work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>C Hymn Distribution by Translator</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/08_Translation_Principles/C_Hymn_Distribution_by_Translator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/saMhitA/meta/articles/jamison_brereton/intro/08_Translation_Principles/C_Hymn_Distribution_by_Translator/</guid>
      <description>At the beginning of this project, we two translators each took primary responsibility for approximately half the hymns of the R̥gveda and produced first and usually second drafts of them. As the project continued, we consulted with each other at every turn, passed hymns back and forth, and read each other’s translations critically. In the end, however, the final version of each hymn became the responsibility of a single translator. The division of those final versions is as follows:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
