<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIRST CHAPTER.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The Animal Sacrifice.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(Erecting of the Sacrificial Post.) The Gods went up to the celestial world by means of this sacri fice. They were afraid that Men and Kiṣis, after having seen their sacrifice (by means of which they ascended to heaven), might come after (they had gone), and inquire (whether they could not obtain some sacri ficial knowledge). They debarred them? (from obtaining such a know ledge) by means of the Yupa, i.e., the sacrificial post. Thence the Yūpa is called so (from yoyūpayan, they debarred). The gods when going up to the celestial world, struck the Yūpa in (the earth), turning its points downwards. Thereupon Men and Riṣis came to the spot where the gods had performed their sacrifice, thinking, that they might obtain some information about the sacrifice). They found only the Yūpa struck in the earth), with its point turned downwards. They learnt that the gods had by this means (i.e., by having struck in the earth the ¥llpa) precluded the sacrificial secret (from being known). They dug the Yūpa out, and turned its points upwards, where [73] upon they got aware of the sacrifice, and beheld (consequently), the celestial world. That is the reason that the Yūpa is erected with its point turned upwards (it is done), in order to get aware of the sacrifice, and to behold the celestial world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECOND CHAPTER. (The Remaining Rites of the Animal Sacrifice. The Prātar-anuváka).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;(Why fire is carried round the sacrificial animal.) The Devas spread the sacrifice. When doing so, the Asuras attacked tbem, intending to put an obstacle in their way (to prevent the successful performance of the sacrifice). The attack was made against the sacrificial post from the eastern direction, after the animal had been consecrated by the Apri verses (see 2, 4), and before the fire was carried round the animal. The Devas awoke, and surrounded, for their own protection, as well as for that of the sacrifice (the place) with a three-fold wall resembling fire. The Asuras seeing those walls shining and blazing, did not venture an attack, but ran away. Thus the Devas defeated the Asuras on the eastern side as well as on the western. For this reason the sacrificers perform the rite of carrying fire round (the animal, when consecrated), and have a mantra recited; for they thus surround (the animal) with a three-fold wall, shining like fire, for their own protection and that of the sacrifice.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After the animal is consecrated, and fire carried around it, they take it northwards. They carry before it a firebrand, meaning thereby that the animal is ultimately the sacrificer himself ; they believe that he will go to heaven, having that light (the firebrand) [98] carried before him. And in this way he really goes to heaven.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THIRD CHAPTER. (The Apo Naptriyam Ceremony. The Upāmsu and Antaryáma Oblations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Hotar has no share in the Bahiṣpavamāna Meal. The Libation for Mitra-Varuna to be mixed with milk. On the Purodaśas belonging to the Libations. Hariṣpankti. Akṣara-paňkti. Narāšansa-pankti. Savana-parkti).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Story of the Südra Riṣi Kavaṣa?).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The Riṣis, when once holding &amp;amp; sacrificial session on (the banks of the Sarasvatī, expelled Kavasa, the (118) son of Ilūṣa, from (their) Soma&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FOURTH CHAPTER. (The Dvidevatya Graha Lihations, i.e., the Libations poured from the Aindravayava, Maitrāvaruna, and Aśvina Grahas. Rituyðjas. The Silent Praise).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;25, (Story of a Race run by the Gods for obtaining the right to drink first from a Loma Libation. The Aindra váyava Graha. Explanation of a certain custom with the Bharatas).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The gods could not agree as to who of them should first taste the Soma juice. They (all) wished for it, (each saying) &amp;ldquo;Might I drink first, might I drink first.&amp;rdquo; They came (at length) to an understanding They said: “Well, let us run a race. Ho of us who will be victor, shall first taste the Soma juice.&amp;quot; So they did. Among all those who ran the race, Vayu first arrived at the goal; next Indra ; next Mitra and Varuna, then the Aśvins. Indra thinking he would be beforehand with Vāyu, (ran as fast as he could [128]and) fell down elose to him. He&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FIFTH CHAPTER. The Different Parts of the Ajyü Śāstra : Ahara, Nivid, Sukta.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The call, sorsavona (called thāva) is the Brahma ; [142] the address (Nivid) is the Kṣatram (royal porver), and the hymn (sukta) are the subjects (vis). By repeating (first) the call somsd vom (representing the Brahma). and then setting forth the titles (representing the royal power), the Hotar joins subsequently the Kṣatram to the Brahma. By repeating the Nivid before he recites the hymu, he joins subsequently the subjects to the Kṣatram, the Ksatram being the Nivid, and the hymn the subjects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
