<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 on ऋग्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/01/</guid>
      <description>FIRST CHAPTER.
(The Animal Sacrifice.)
(Erecting of the Sacrificial Post.) The Gods went up to the celestial world by means of this sacri fice. They were afraid that Men and Kiṣis, after having seen their sacrifice (by means of which they ascended to heaven), might come after (they had gone), and inquire (whether they could not obtain some sacri ficial knowledge). They debarred them? (from obtaining such a know ledge) by means of the Yupa, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/02/</guid>
      <description>SECOND CHAPTER. (The Remaining Rites of the Animal Sacrifice. The Prātar-anuváka).
(Why fire is carried round the sacrificial animal.) The Devas spread the sacrifice. When doing so, the Asuras attacked tbem, intending to put an obstacle in their way (to prevent the successful performance of the sacrifice). The attack was made against the sacrificial post from the eastern direction, after the animal had been consecrated by the Apri verses (see 2, 4), and before the fire was carried round the animal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/03/</guid>
      <description>THIRD CHAPTER. (The Apo Naptriyam Ceremony. The Upāmsu and Antaryáma Oblations.
The Hotar has no share in the Bahiṣpavamāna Meal. The Libation for Mitra-Varuna to be mixed with milk. On the Purodaśas belonging to the Libations. Hariṣpankti. Akṣara-paňkti. Narāšansa-pankti. Savana-parkti).
Story of the Südra Riṣi Kavaṣa?). The Riṣis, when once holding &amp;amp; sacrificial session on (the banks of the Sarasvatī, expelled Kavasa, the (118) son of Ilūṣa, from (their) Soma</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/04/</guid>
      <description>FOURTH CHAPTER. (The Dvidevatya Graha Lihations, i.e., the Libations poured from the Aindravayava, Maitrāvaruna, and Aśvina Grahas. Rituyðjas. The Silent Praise).
25, (Story of a Race run by the Gods for obtaining the right to drink first from a Loma Libation. The Aindra váyava Graha. Explanation of a certain custom with the Bharatas).
The gods could not agree as to who of them should first taste the Soma juice. They (all) wished for it, (each saying) &amp;ldquo;Might I drink first, might I drink first.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_Rk/shAkalam/aitareya-brAhmaNam/haug/02/05/</guid>
      <description>FIFTH CHAPTER. The Different Parts of the Ajyü Śāstra : Ahara, Nivid, Sukta.)
The call, sorsavona (called thāva) is the Brahma ; [142] the address (Nivid) is the Kṣatram (royal porver), and the hymn (sukta) are the subjects (vis). By repeating (first) the call somsd vom (representing the Brahma). and then setting forth the titles (representing the royal power), the Hotar joins subsequently the Kṣatram to the Brahma. By repeating the Nivid before he recites the hymu, he joins subsequently the subjects to the Kṣatram, the Ksatram being the Nivid, and the hymn the subjects.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
